<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Hiking and Coding</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111107">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-01-27T20:06:11Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Connecticut</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ct/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ct/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-27T20:06:11Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-27T19:58:58Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Camping permitted only at designated sites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Connecticut begins with a steep uphill, but when you get to the top
  of that, you are at the highest point of the state.  I always like
  hitting the high-point of a state because it tells me that the net
  effort that I must expend in the remainder of that state is less
  than the effort that I&#39;ve already expended.  For my computer-science
  readers, there&#39;s also a nice little problem there: how do you
  compute the set of points on the trail for which there are no higher
  points remaining in the state?  (It turns out that you can do it
  with a simple extension of a problem that I had worked on before,
  but I won&#39;t say more than that to let you have the fun of solving it
  yourself.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked down the mountain and stopped in a the town of Salisbury,
  CT for lunch and a small resupply.  As we were walking into town,
  a northbound hiker was walking out, and he let us pick through the
  extra stuff that he had received in the mail.  I took some Jolly
  Ranchers, but they were really sticky.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked on and arrived at Limestone Spring Lean-to, which is
  pretty far off the trail on a steep downhill.  It&#39;s quite
  frustrating when this happens, because that means that you have a
  long uphill first thing in the morning.  So Picker and I went down
  to the spring to gather water.  We hiked a mile or so farther that
  evening and set up a stealth camp.  As the picture ending the
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/massachusetts&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; indicates, this is not strictly legal.  We made sure to be
  quite a ways from the trail, but we worried about rangers all
  evening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was a bit of a long one.  We decided not to camp
  illegally again, so we had two choices for camp sites &amp;ndash; one about
  13 miles away and one about 23 miles away.  Naturally, we chose to
  head for the farther campsite.  When we got within 3 miles, I
  decided that I didn&#39;t want to walk for more than another hour, so I
  really pushed hard to get to camp.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day had some nice scenery:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-cEvLxZBiQEM/TOXAywwRf9I/AAAAAAAAAvM/SHS1g8Ih370/s800/DSCF0203.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-cEvLxZBiQEM/TOXAywwRf9I/AAAAAAAAAvM/SHS1g8Ih370/s800/DSCF0203.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  after we went over a small mountain, we got to Kent, CT.  We were
  rather early to town, so we got breakfast at one of the posh
  restaurants.  I had a waffle with ice cream.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As we were walking away from Kent, we met a couple walking their
  dog.  In the course of conversation, they mentioned that they had
  sent their daughter to the prep school that we walked past between
  the trail and town.  Without batting an eye, one of them said that
  the yearly tuition was $20000!  The school had a beautiful campus,
  so we could now know where the funds for that came from, but it
  seemed excessive to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We crossed the border with New York, but we were soon back in
  Connecticut.  We stopped at a campsite just past a bridge and met up
  with Just Jill once again.  I slept with the tarp off of my hammock,
  which turned out to be a mistake as the weather in the small valley
  where we camped was extremely cold overnight.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, we would leave Connecticut for good and enter New
  York.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  New York.  Poorly-maintained trails near big roads.  The lowest
  point on the whole AT right next to caged bears (it couldn&#39;t get
  much more symbolic than that).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ct/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ct/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Massachusetts</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/massachusetts/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/massachusetts/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-14T02:09:44Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-14T02:09:44Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Massachusetts is the first of two short states along the trail that
will give me fits when I try to type them.  From now on, I will call
it MA.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Border to Great Barrington&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Just across the border with Vermont, there is a road with two small
  towns on either side of the intersection with the trail.
  Williamstown had the larger store, so that is the one we went to.
  We got a small resupply at the store and a couple of cold sodas.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We went on, with the goal of getting to the top of Mt. Greylock by
  lunch time.  For some reason, I had thought that Mt. Greylock would
  have a gondola at the top and we could take a ride as we ate our
  lunch.  Unfortunately, this turned out not to be the case (though I
  think people do use it as a ski hill, so I was not so far off), and
  it had a couple of interesting structures on top instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WAWPz3bbVek/TOXAwZ1kqAI/AAAAAAAAAuw/XATrStfxuSA/s800/DSCF0196.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WAWPz3bbVek/TOXAwZ1kqAI/AAAAAAAAAuw/XATrStfxuSA/s800/DSCF0196.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The picture above is a war memorial, and there was also an old lodge
  that had some light refreshments as well.  Since we had just been to
  the store, we didn&#39;t need the services of the lodge, so we sat
  outside and dried our shelters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When we got to the bottom of the mountain, it was getting late, and
  we got to a town, so we decided to stay there.  We heard that a
  local church would let hikers sleep inside, so we did that.  The
  church did not have any shower facilities, and this led to a rather
  embarrassing situation at dinner.  We went to a pub with some
  trail-related items on the menu, and after we sat down, the
  bartender came over and closed the window &amp;ndash; saying that she had had
  complaints about the way we smelled!  To be fair, it had been quite
  a while since we had showers, but there must have been a better way
  of handling the situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, we hiked to the town of Dalton, where we got showers
  at the YMCA and hung out for a while.  Dalton has a hostel or two,
  but since we had gotten there so early, we decided to go to the
  shelter a few miles out of town anyway.  Since we were walking such
  a short distance from town, we packed out subs and enjoyed some
  fresh vegetables at dinner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was almost completely flat, and I don&#39;t really remember
  anything beyond the fact that it rained a bit.  At the end of the
  day, however, we reached Upper Goose Pond Cabin.  This is a quaint
  cabin on a lake, with a caretaker and bunks upstairs.  Effectively,
  it is a cross between a hostel and a really good trail shelter.
  There was a mix of northbounders and southbounders that were staying
  there for the night, but they had plenty of room.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning began with pancakes, and then we set off again.  We
  came across a large group of university students on an orientation
  hike.  I think this particular group was from Yale, but we met
  groups from other Ivy League schools as well over the next week or
  so.  The really funny thing about these groups is that they would go
  about 5 miles per day.  Considering that we were going 10 miles
  before lunch, we were in a constant state of bafflement over how
  they could go so slowly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the end of the day, we got to a road and went into the town of
  Great Barrington (the birthplace of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W._E._B._Du_Bois&quot;&gt;W. E. B. Du Bois&lt;/a&gt;).  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Great Barrington to the border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Leaving Great Barrington posed a rather thorny ethical question.
  There are two roads leaving town, and we had come in on the first
  (northernmost) one.  Should we leave town on that road or on the
  second one, saving 8 miles of walking?  Some hikers would have taken
  the second, but we all considered it cheating, so we took the
  first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We got a ride just as we had taken out a camera to get a picture of
  ourselves hitchhiking, which we took as a sign.  I think we tried to
  repeat that a few times, but it never worked quite as well again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Our destination for the night was a pair shelters that between them
  had space for 16 people.  We figured that this would be more than
  enough space, but we were wrong.  More groups of Ivy Leaguers were
  on the trail, and a few had converged on the spot.  We found some
  flattish ground nearby (another advantage of a hammock is that the
  ground doesn&#39;t need to be very flat at all) and set up for the
  night.  The university kids were not too loud, but they did have
  trouble setting up their bear bag, and finally gave up at two in the
  morning with the bag suspended only a few feet off the ground.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We were out of camp the next morning before the university kids
  awoke (one way that they could move so slowly I guess), and headed
  over a small mountain to the Connecticut border.  The border was in
  a beautiful little ravine with a brook next to it, but I only got a
  picture of the sign welcoming us to the next state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hG9-JG_66Jk/TOXAyHN76PI/AAAAAAAAAvE/FjsveRuFyJY/s800/DSCF0202.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hG9-JG_66Jk/TOXAyHN76PI/AAAAAAAAAvE/FjsveRuFyJY/s800/DSCF0202.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Connecticut.  Some crazies hike the whole thing in one day, but we
  took three.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/massachusetts/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/massachusetts/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Vermont</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/vermont/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/vermont/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-07T18:00:54Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-07T18:00:54Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Hanover to Rutland&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After an enjoyable two days in Hanover, it was time to hit the road
  again.  Unfortunately, the first few miles of the trail in Vermont
  are actually on road.  Road walks are bad for a hiker for a few
  reasons.  For one thing, you are taken out of the wilderness
  experience whenever you see the road.  For another, the hard surface
  tends to hurt your feet far more quickly than trail.  While there
  were times during the hike that I was glad to be walking on road
  (mainly after hiking the rocky trails of Pennsylvania), a good trail
  is almost always preferable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Rain started around lunch time, and by the time I arrived at the
  shelter, it was a downpour.  I was still not comfortable sleeping in
  shelters at this point of the hike, so I set up my hammock anyway.
  However, I went to the shelter to cook supper and found that
  sleeping there would not have been an option anyway.  It was full of
  northbounders &amp;ndash; roughly the end of the wave of northbounders that
  happens every year on the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The rain brought out some red efts from their hiding places.  These
  are juvenile newts that look somewhat like plastic toys.  I was
  never able to get a great photo of them, but this is one of the
  better ones:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6OUn7JW_nvg/TOXAji1HJ3I/AAAAAAAAAro/kQFlcuIKLdo/s800/DSCF0156.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6OUn7JW_nvg/TOXAji1HJ3I/AAAAAAAAAro/kQFlcuIKLdo/s800/DSCF0156.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The weather was better the next day, and I made good time.  During
  the day, I met up with Just Jill, who had been staying at the same
  shelter as me.  (Just X is a common trail name for people named X
  who can&#39;t decide on a trail name.)  She had started the trail much
  earlier than me, but had family near Hanover and was just getting
  back on the trail.  We chatted a bit about people that I only knew
  from reading log books at shelters and then went on.  Late in the
  day, I got some pretty bad chafing from the previous day&#39;s moisture
  and had to knock off before I got to my intended destination.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The following day was only notable because it marked the junction of
  the AT with the Long Trail, the oldest long-distance hiking trail in
  the US.  I caught up with Just Jill again at the end of the day, at
  a shelter near the top of Mount Killington.  We agreed that we would
  get up early the next day to go to the top and take pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I did get up early the next morning, but didn&#39;t wake Just Jill.
  However, I did get some very nice pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jGaLyra_81k/TOXAkAmvm5I/AAAAAAAAArw/BfmkXk7lStw/s800/DSCF0157.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jGaLyra_81k/TOXAkAmvm5I/AAAAAAAAArw/BfmkXk7lStw/s800/DSCF0157.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ZPfRLM6pUFI/TOXAk8yLnLI/AAAAAAAAAsI/KPbC3EpHhRk/s800/DSCF0159.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ZPfRLM6pUFI/TOXAk8yLnLI/AAAAAAAAAsI/KPbC3EpHhRk/s800/DSCF0159.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-X17lFoOGdco/TOXAmAaKhOI/AAAAAAAAAsc/rj7vIirb0CQ/s800/DSCF0161.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-X17lFoOGdco/TOXAmAaKhOI/AAAAAAAAAsc/rj7vIirb0CQ/s800/DSCF0161.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-HzKRZl8eawk/TOXAnuCWEvI/AAAAAAAAAsk/C1dk_d9CMKY/s800/DSCF0162.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-HzKRZl8eawk/TOXAnuCWEvI/AAAAAAAAAsk/C1dk_d9CMKY/s800/DSCF0162.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  From there, the day was all downhill (literally, not
  metaphorically).  I crossed 500 miles and saw an owl.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-snHnV4Ge7vs/TOXAtm7sfuI/AAAAAAAAAJ8/xK14j7xlUHI/s640/DSCF0178.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-snHnV4Ge7vs/TOXAtm7sfuI/AAAAAAAAAJ8/xK14j7xlUHI/s640/DSCF0178.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That night, I got to a road and decided to go to Rutland, VT.  My
  sister was playing in a musical competition that weekend, and I was
  able to take the train up to Montreal to see her.  But not before I
  stayed at a hostel run by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twelvetribes.com/&quot;&gt;Twelve Tribes&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; a sort of religious
  commune that some characterize as a cult, but who were very nice to
  me.  And they had great food and smoothies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Rutland to the Massachusetts border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After the trip to Montreal, I was back to Rutland to start where I
  left off.  Since I got back to the trail late in the evening, I only
  walked to the first shelter a couple of miles down the trail.  I saw
  in the log book that Picker and Grinner had been there the day
  before, meaning that they were now ahead of me (I had been ahead of
  them since we split up at the beginning of the Whites).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was so excited at the prospect of catching back up with Picker and
  Grinner that I woke up at about 3:30 the next morning and, since I
  couldn&#39;t get back to sleep, I packed up and started walking.  I was
  undeterred by darkness, hills, rain, lightning, and trail re-routes
  and just kept walking all day.  Later in the day, after I had walked
  at least 20 miles, I started hearing about &quot;the best hostel on the
  trail&quot;.  I decided to make that my destination, even though it was
  another 10 miles or so.  I borrowed a mobile phone and called ahead
  to reserve a bunk.  I asked whether Picker and Grinner were there,
  and was given even more motivation to keep going when I found out
  that they were.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The last few miles of the day were down a ski run, and when I got to
  the bottom I was just about as tired as I&#39;d ever been.  However, I
  did my shopping and waited to get picked up by the guy who runs the
  hostel.  When I got to the hostel, it was as nice as it had been
  hyped to be.  It was clean and had trail memorabilia decorating the
  whole place.  On top of that, you get a pint of Ben &amp;amp; Jerry&#39;s ice
  cream as part of the low fee for staying there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Besides Picker and Grinner, there were two other couples staying at
  the hostel &amp;ndash; Lucky and Charm as well as Sherpa and Boss Lady. One
  fun way we passed the time that evening was to have everyone weigh
  their packs.  As you might expect, Sherpa&#39;s pack weight more than
  Boss Lady&#39;s, but Charm was a bit miffed to find out that her pack
  weighed at least 10 pounds more than Lucky&#39;s.  Plus, she was
  carrying a big camera, as she was (is?) an aspiring photographer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, I was rather sore, but after the effort that I had put
  in to catch Picker and Grinner, I was not going to sit around and
  let them get ahead of me again.  Thankfully, they didn&#39;t want to go
  too far either, so we found a nice river about ten miles down the
  trail and set up an early camp.  I hung up a bear bag comically low
  to the ground, and people took pictures standing next to it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t remember much from the next day, but the day after that we
  went to Bennington, VT to resupply.  It was there where we had our
  easiest hitch &amp;ndash; before we even stuck our thumbs out, an old gent
  pulled over and offered us a ride back to the trail.  He was an
  entertaining guy &amp;ndash; a veteran from the Korean War who was going
  skydiving for his eightieth birthday the following week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We slept near a shelter that night where there was a gaggle of
  northbounders, some of whom were roasting marshmallows over a camp
  fire (neither of which is a common occurrence for me &amp;ndash; I&#39;m usually
  too tired to have a camp fire at the end of the day, and
  marshmallows just waste space in the pack, but they sure were tasty
  that night), and I joined them for a little while.  One of them had
  a violin and was trying to learn to play as she was on her hike, so
  I borrowed it and played a little.  All in all, it was a great day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That night, it rained, and a dead branch fell near Picker and
  Grinner&#39;s tent &amp;ndash; a good reminder that Mother Nature doesn&#39;t care if
  you just had a great day; she&#39;ll still try to mess it up for you.
  Luckily, though, no one was hurt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, we made it to the border and completed our third
  state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XLsTa1Hkwh0/TOXAvzWt-gI/AAAAAAAAAuk/4_CndnzBvV8/s800/DSCF0195.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XLsTa1Hkwh0/TOXAvzWt-gI/AAAAAAAAAuk/4_CndnzBvV8/s800/DSCF0195.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Massachusetts, flat and short.  Also large parties of college kids
  on orientation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/vermont/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/vermont/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Two Small Clojure Packages</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/small-clojure-libs/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/small-clojure-libs/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="lru-maps" />

	<category term="thrush" />


	<updated>2012-01-07T02:23:15Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-07T02:23:15Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working on a larger project lately, but in doing so I found
two little things that were independent of the project and useful
enough for me to release as Clojure packages.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Parallel Thrush&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I discussed the Clojure &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/luhnybin&quot;&gt;thrush operator&lt;/a&gt; once before.  The way that I
  have been using it lately is to operate on a stream of data, perhaps
  condensing the stream at the end into one value.  This suggested to
  me that I should be able to operate on the stream of data in
  parallel, since all of the functions that I am using are pure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  What I have done with the new package is to create a new macro
  called &lt;code&gt;||-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  This operates just like the &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; macro already in
  Clojure, except that it splits the data in the stream and runs it in
  parallel.  Behind the scenes, it uses the Clojure &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; function,
  which advises that it should only be used when the operation being
  done is CPU-intensive enough to exceed the coordination cost.  Since
  multiple functions are put together by my macro before they are
  passed to &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt;, following this advice should become easier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As an example:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(||-&amp;gt;&amp;gt; data
       (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; big-function)
       (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt; odd?)
       &lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;:merge&lt;/span&gt;
       (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt; +))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  is the same as
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; data
     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; big-function)
     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt; odd?)
     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt; +))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  but everything before the &lt;code&gt;:merge&lt;/code&gt; statement is executed in
  parallel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Of course, the source is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/parallel-thrush&quot;&gt;my github&lt;/a&gt;.  The jar can also be easily
  downloaded from &lt;a href=&quot;https://clojars.org/parallel-thrush&quot;&gt;clojars&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;LRU maps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The project I&#39;ve been working on has partly been a struggle to
  manage resources.  Thus, I&#39;ve needed a good way to keep some of the
  resources in memory and get rid of the ones that are no longer
  relevant.  Using a &lt;code&gt;hash-map&lt;/code&gt; data structure is always nice, so I&#39;ve
  implemented a variant of a &lt;code&gt;hash-map&lt;/code&gt; that has an upper limit on its
  size.  When you try to add an element that would cause the map to
  have too many elements, it kicks out the element that was least
  recently added or modified.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt; lru-map 4 (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt; 20))
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #708070;&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f9f7f;&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt; {12 13, 14 15, 16 17, 18 19}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Sometimes, you want to do something with an element as it gets
  kicked out.  For that, there is &lt;code&gt;lru-map-with&lt;/code&gt;.  This takes two
  extra arguments &amp;ndash; a function that operates on some &quot;state&quot; and the
  element that is getting kicked out and the initial &quot;state&quot;.  (Behind
  the scenes, this &quot;state&quot; isn&#39;t really state, but it is helpful to
  think of it as state.)
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt; lru-map-with 4 conj [] (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt; 20))
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #708070;&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f9f7f;&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt; {12 13, 14 15, 16 17, 18 19, :lru-state [[0 1] [2 3] [4 5] [6 7] [8 9] [10 11]]}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Again, this little package is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/least-recently-used-map&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; and the jar is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://clojars.org/least-recently-used-map&quot;&gt;clojars&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/small-clojure-libs/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/small-clojure-libs/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Southern New Hampshire</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-05T18:32:06Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-05T18:28:43Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, my Disqus commenting system isn&#39;t letting me reply to
comments, so I&#39;ll start by answering the question that Björn asked
yesterday.  The question was about how the hut croos know if you&#39;re a
thru-hiker (or at least aspiring thru-hiker).  The answer is that they
must take your word for it.  There are some obvious signs, though.
First, thru-hikers have much larger packs than most other hikers in
the Whites, and are generally bearded by the time they get there.  The
vast majority have a trail guide sticking out of their pack, and their
pack will be really well-organized; they will know where everything is
inside it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But that does bring up a bigger question: what &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a thru-hiker?  Bar
Man, who I introduced yesterday, probably wouldn&#39;t fit any definition
(though he did get work-for-stay at every hut in the Whites), since he
was not actually hiking the length of the trail that year.  The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.appalachiantrail.org/hiking/thru-section-hiking&quot;&gt;ATC&lt;/a&gt;
defines a thru-hiker as someone who walks or is attempting to walk the
entire AT in one uninterrupted journey.  This seems reasonable to me:
it doesn&#39;t exclude people who hike the entire trail in sections as
long as their hike is uninterrupted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Ethan Pond to Mt. Moosilauke&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  From Ethan Pond, it was a relatively easy jaunt to Zealand Falls
  hut, where I once again went in to take a rest.  I tried to
  emphasize that I was a real thru-hiker in hopes of getting some
  leftovers, but the croo were busy and paid no attention.  I noticed
  a small boy with thick glasses at the hut.  He was awkwardly trying
  to walk with an unscrewed Camelbak full of water between his legs,
  and I immediately pegged him as a city kid who probably shouldn&#39;t be
  in the mountains.  Sure enough, I hadn&#39;t gone more than a quarter of
  a mile from the hut before I saw his dad consoling him after he had
  taken a hard fall.  As I walked on, I heard him yell, &quot;I hate stupid
  hiking!&quot; at the top of his lungs.  Whenever I was having a rough
  day, I would think back to this kid and know I had had it a lot
  better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The rest of the day was not too eventful.  I was lucky to see a few
  groups of Boy Scouts just before I would have gone to the shelter
  that was my destination for the day, so I stopped just before the
  shelter and set up camp.  Even though I was more than a quarter mile
  from the shelter, I could still hear them late into the night, but
  at least they were a bit more quiet than if I had been right there
  with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was up and over Mt. Garfield, another extremely steep
  mountain.  Thankfully, the trail up Garfield is just beside a
  waterfall and the waterfall is not the same as the trail, as it
  would be in Southern Maine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  From the next mountain, Mt. Lafayette, it is possible to see
  Greenleaf Hut, but since it is over a mile away, I did not go down
  to it.  Mt. Lafayette also had the most &quot;false summits&quot; of any
  mountain on the trail that I can remember.  I would think that I was
  getting to the top, and then there would be more climbing.  It&#39;s
  quite a frustrating thing.  However, the clouds that day made the
  view quite nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xnIhPV2GV34/TOXAZ41C5lI/AAAAAAAAApY/wxHoxT8l1QM/s800/DSCF0137.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xnIhPV2GV34/TOXAZ41C5lI/AAAAAAAAApY/wxHoxT8l1QM/s800/DSCF0137.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Mt. Lafayette is also the last mountain over 5000 feet for quite a
  while.  The knowledge of this probably made the descent down to
  Franconia Notch a little easier.  When I got there, I was presented
  with a confusing set of roads.  It was here that I almost got
  arrested.  I was trying to hitchhike into town, but somehow I walked
  to the interstate rather than the state highway.  I had my thumb out
  for a while and was disappointed that everyone was driving so fast,
  when I saw a car slow down coming my direction.  Too late did I see
  the lights on the top of the car.  It was a state trooper, and he
  simply yelled out the window &quot;I WILL ARREST YOU.&quot;  Needless to say,
  I got off the road pretty quickly.  However, I was so shaken up by
  the experience that I walked the wrong direction down the trail for
  about a half an hour before I realized my mistake, and had to turn
  around to get back to the state highway.  Finally I got a hitch, and
  was able to resupply in Lincoln, NH.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was back on the trail the next day, but didn&#39;t go far.  I stayed
  at the Kinsman Pond campsite, and I even had to pay for the
  privilege.  I&#39;m pretty sure that was the only time I paid to camp.
  I woke up the next day knowing that there were only two more real
  mountains in the Whites.  The first, Kinsman Mountain, was pretty
  tough in the morning, but it had this nice stream at the base of the
  other side.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-g1bvbE4YSvg/TOXAbjXiOWI/AAAAAAAAAps/FUYWTjxeJx8/s800/DSCF0141.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-g1bvbE4YSvg/TOXAbjXiOWI/AAAAAAAAAps/FUYWTjxeJx8/s800/DSCF0141.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YNuo_AGTX-s/TOXAe-aKNOI/AAAAAAAAAqU/Q_FdR84Ap3s/s800/DSCF0146.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YNuo_AGTX-s/TOXAe-aKNOI/AAAAAAAAAqU/Q_FdR84Ap3s/s800/DSCF0146.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After I was past the shelter on the other side, where I had a snack,
  I pushed pretty hard toward the next mountain: Mt. Moosilauke.
  There is a long flattish section between the two mountains, so I
  thought I might be able to make it up that night.  Unfortunately,
  Mt. Moosilauke is so steep (there are long sections where iron bars
  are embedded into the rock so that you have hand- and foot-holds)
  that I just didn&#39;t feel safe doing it.  I set up my hammock and
  waited for night to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-e6b-KBq6z7Q/TOXAfy9N68I/AAAAAAAADW4/V4JrX0b67M4/s800/DSCF0149.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-e6b-KBq6z7Q/TOXAfy9N68I/AAAAAAAADW4/V4JrX0b67M4/s800/DSCF0149.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  You can&#39;t really tell from that picture, but my hammock is nearly
  above a cliff.  I had to be extra-careful where I put my shoes that
  night so that they wouldn&#39;t roll down the mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I awoke the next morning and made quick work of the rest of the
  mountain.  I was so glad to get to the top, because it really meant
  the end of the hard stuff.  The Whites don&#39;t officially end for
  another 15 miles or so, but Moosilauke is the end of any really
  tough hiking in them.  I flew down the other side of the mountain --
  even running in places &amp;ndash; I was just so glad that the hard hiking
  was done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-OiOES6B_0YY/TOXAgN2icuI/AAAAAAAAAqo/93YDEfPdwNM/s640/DSCF0150.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-OiOES6B_0YY/TOXAgN2icuI/AAAAAAAAAqo/93YDEfPdwNM/s640/DSCF0150.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I stopped in at a small hostel in Glencliff, NH, but decided it
  didn&#39;t look very nice, so I kept going.  By the time the day was
  over, I was nearly out of the Whites.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The trail to Hanover&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After the hard hiking in the Whites, I started focusing on getting
  my mileage up.  After all, I had been hiking for over a month, and
  was only done about 20% of the trail.  At this rate, it would take
  nearly half a year.  So the first day out, I did over twenty miles.
  There were a few mountains, but I remember thinking they were
  nothing.  When I met northbounders, I was the one who could afford
  to be a bit smug.  They may have walked farther than me, but I had
  been through the hard mountains and survived.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, however, I got to Hanover, NH.  It&#39;s a beautiful
  university town, with Dartmouth University as its centerpiece.  I
  needed to resupply and get cleaned up, so I decided to stay.
  Unfortunately, I arrived on a Saturday and did not get my cleaning
  done.  The next day, the only public laundry was closed, so I had to
  stay another day as well.  It slowed me down a bit, but I was able
  to meet up with some other hikers, and we had a great time.
  Dartmouth was having some sort of orientation for new students, and
  we snuck into some of their barbecues.  There was even a fraternity
  which let me sleep in their basement for free, although they did
  have a big party the night that I slept there, which kept me up
  until far too late.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Vermont is just across the river from Hanover.  I don&#39;t remember too
  much about it.  Will I be able to recap it in one post?  Probably not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>North New Hampshire</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-05T01:02:45Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-05T01:02:45Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;The Whites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  As a southbound hiker on the Appalachian Trail, you hear about the
  White Mountains from nearly the first day.  They are reputed to be
  the Real Test &amp;ndash; if you can make it past them, you can do anything.
  However, once you get to them, you have made it past &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/southern-maine&quot;&gt;Southern Maine&lt;/a&gt;,
  and you know you can do anything anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  To be honest, though, the Whites are a real challenge, and present a
  few peculiarities when compared with the rest of the trail.  First,
  there are real buildings (unlike the shelters on the rest of the
  trail which generally only have 3 walls).  These are known as
  &quot;huts&quot;, but they&#39;re pretty nice.  Thru-hikers are allowed to stay at
  them if they do a night&#39;s work, but they cost about $100 per night
  for everyone else.  Also, there are many areas where camping is
  strictly forbidden, or where there is a fee to camp.  This seemed a
  bit of a hassle, given the fact that I had been sleeping pretty much
  wherever I wanted for the past month.  However, it&#39;s a high-use
  area, so I can understand the reasons behind the restrictions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Leaving Gorham&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Picker, Grinner, and I spent a nice day-and-a-half in Gorham despite
  a rather funny meal at a Mexican (perhaps that needs scare quotes)
  restaurant.  &quot;What kind of beers do you have?&quot;  &quot;Oh lots, just name
  one.&quot;  &quot;Okay, I&#39;ll have a Long Trail.&quot;  &quot;I don&#39;t think we have
  that.&quot;  &quot;How about a Dos Equis?&quot; &quot;Nope.&quot; &quot;Maybe you should tell us
  what you have.&quot;  &quot;We have Bud, Miller, and Miller Light.&quot;  &quot;I think
  I&#39;ll stick with water.&quot;  And it went downhill from there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first two miles out of Gorham have beautiful pine trees and a
  really easy grade.  They are probably the easiest two miles in New
  Hampshire.  After this, we started going straight up again until we
  finally got over Mount Moriah.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-fcAHof8WGPI/TOXAA_XLE2I/AAAAAAAAAlA/RlqDwELfFW0/s800/DSCF0109.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-fcAHof8WGPI/TOXAA_XLE2I/AAAAAAAAAlA/RlqDwELfFW0/s800/DSCF0109.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We got to a really nice shelter right at lunch time, and to my
  surprise Grinner wanted to stop for the day.  I really wanted to go
  on, so after an hour of discussing the situation, I decided to go on
  by myself.  I was a little scared because I had been with Picker and
  Grinner the whole way to that point, but I also knew that it might
  be a good idea, since I could be sure that I was going my own pace
  and not hurrying to stay up with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I walked about 5 more miles, not finding a camp spot (which was the
  reason that Grinner had wanted to stop), before finding a place to
  camp that was just outside the first big no-camping zone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning was up and over Carter Dome and then down to Carter
  Notch Hut.  This was the first hut that I encountered, and gave me a
  good first impression of the huts.  The croo (as the workers at the
  hut are known) was extremely welcoming and when they found out that
  I was a thru-hiker gave me some left-overs from the morning&#39;s
  breakfast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After my short stop, I pushed on, up the Wildcat Ridge.  This is a
  short mountain range with a ski area on one of the mountains.  I
  stopped at a gondola and did a little people-watching while I ate
  lunch.  After lunch, it was time for a knee-busting descent down to
  Pinkham Notch, which has a nice little interpretive center, where I
  think I got an ice-cream sandwich.  (Thinking back on this, I guess
  I was getting plenty of food in this section of the hike).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next four miles after Pinkham Notch were not too hard, but it
  was getting a bit late by the time I got to my final destination of
  the day &amp;ndash; Osgood Tent Site.  Bears are apparently a problem at this
  particular camp spot, so it was nice that they provided bear boxes
  to store our food.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Mounts Madison and Washington&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The climb from Osgood Tent Site the next morning is one of the
  longest and steepest on the trail.  The trail climbs 2866 feet over
  2.8 miles &amp;ndash; a 20% grade that just goes on and on.  Normally, when I
  got above tree line I was really happy because that meant that the
  climb was nearly over.  On this climb, it lasted for at least
  another hour.  I was lucky with the weather, though, and got some
  nice pictures.  Here is one of Mt. Washington, as seen from
  Mt. Madison.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-WWUwef9kwv8/TOXABgBmiII/AAAAAAAAAlM/h8NTmohWZ_E/s800/DSCF0110.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-WWUwef9kwv8/TOXABgBmiII/AAAAAAAAAlM/h8NTmohWZ_E/s800/DSCF0110.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  You can see the cloud on top of Mt. Washington (as well as the road
  up it).  That is a nearly-permanent feature of the place that
  advertises itself as having the worst weather on Earth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Here is a picture that is a bit more representative of the trail
  going up Mt. Madison: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Iur5kQyy8yo/TOXAFEFvQvI/AAAAAAAAAmA/9owJuOEwmh0/s800/DSCF0115.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Iur5kQyy8yo/TOXAFEFvQvI/AAAAAAAAAmA/9owJuOEwmh0/s800/DSCF0115.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It is all large granite rocks, and the trail is marked by cairns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the time I had gotten to the top, I was really pretty tired, and
  I&#39;d only been going for a couple of hours.  Plus, the wind was
  beating fairly fiercely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-a6mx1BhBkcM/TOXAHkMGwnI/AAAAAAAAAmo/SK1dESLoYSU/s800/DSCF0119.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-a6mx1BhBkcM/TOXAHkMGwnI/AAAAAAAAAmo/SK1dESLoYSU/s800/DSCF0119.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I descended to the hut and warmed myself up a bit, but was soon out
  the door, because I had a goal that was on the other side of
  Mt. Washington.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  My afternoon that day was spent navigating large rocks and asking
  northbounders about the best method for getting work-for-stay at the
  hut that was just past Washington.  The majority opinion was that
  the best method would be to hang out at the top of Mt. Washington
  until an hour before dark because the croo would not turn away a
  hiker into the dark.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Before I got to Mt. Washington, I had to cross the railroad (for
  tourists only) that goes to the top.  You can just see it in this
  picture:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uLJy3SMRqPs/TOXAKk9oLhI/AAAAAAAAAnI/h3r4zQThVtg/s800/DSCF0123.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uLJy3SMRqPs/TOXAKk9oLhI/AAAAAAAAAnI/h3r4zQThVtg/s800/DSCF0123.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But I eventually made it to the top.  There were plenty of people
  who had ridden up in cars or the aforementioned railroad who would
  take my picture with the summit sign.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-m_h-mr1VN-8/TOXAMP1DYnI/AAAAAAAAAnU/57AVGS9d5XQ/s144/DSCF0124.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-m_h-mr1VN-8/TOXAMP1DYnI/AAAAAAAAAnU/57AVGS9d5XQ/s144/DSCF0124.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The top of Mt. Washington is a fairly strange place.  It is a major
  tourist attraction, and has a large snack bar, gift shop, and post
  office, but it also has a major weather station measuring just how
  bad the weather can get.  Every now and then, someone dies because
  they venture out on a hike without the proper gear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, I was safe and sound at the top and hanging out at the gift
  shop until it was late enough to go to the hut.  I met up with a guy
  I had seen in Gorham, who had the trail name Bar Man.  He was a bit
  out of place in the hiking community &amp;ndash; older than the average hiker
  and far less outdoorsy.  In the time that we were talking, it
  emerged that he had only hiked from Osgood Tent Site to Madison hut
  the day before.  Since I had done that hike in the morning, I was
  less than impressed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked down to the hut, with the lyrical name &quot;Lakes of the
  Clouds&quot; just before sunset.  There were many other hikers that had
  already arrived, but as predicted, they took us in since darkness
  was falling.  That evening, Bar Man made a nearly complete ass of
  himself.  He was completely rude during supper, complaining about
  everything, despite the fact that we were staying and eating for
  free at a place where others were paying quite good money to stay.
  He did as little work as possible, and relentlessly hit on the
  pretty northbound hikers.  I made up my mind to get up early and
  leave him behind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After sleeping on the dinner tables of the hut, I was very glad to
  get up early.  It turned out to be a lucky decision, because clouds
  had dropped beneath us, and the views were great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZgtPpRYJ_d0/TOXANgbnvpI/AAAAAAAAAns/-u3qVQn_Bxo/s800/DSCF0126.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZgtPpRYJ_d0/TOXANgbnvpI/AAAAAAAAAns/-u3qVQn_Bxo/s800/DSCF0126.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The path from Mt. Washington was relatively easy &amp;ndash; I could have
  easily made it to the next hut the day before &amp;ndash; but before long, it
  got hard again.  During a moment of lack of focus between
  Mt. Jackson and Mt. Webster, I had my trekking pole slip on a rock,
  and I fell flat on face.  It was a good reminder to keep my
  concentration up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After a descent into another notch, I ascended back to nearly the
  same elevation, and made my way to Ethan Pond.  The caretaker at the
  campsite was a really nice guy and waived the fee for me as a
  thru-hiker.  He also told me that the camp site where I had set up
  my hammock was a favorite place for a local moose.  I didn&#39;t see the
  moose, but I did get a nice picture of the lake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-K-U4fnWnc0g/TOXAUy2PzlI/AAAAAAAAAos/9hmdqsxNM6g/s800/DSCF0133.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-K-U4fnWnc0g/TOXAUy2PzlI/AAAAAAAAAos/9hmdqsxNM6g/s800/DSCF0133.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Wrapup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This post is getting a bit long, so I&#39;ll save the southern half of
  New Hampshire until next the next post.  In it, I nearly get
  arrested, finally finish with the Whites, and rub shoulders with the
  blue-bloods at Dartmouth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Southern Maine</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/southern-maine/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/southern-maine/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-12-19T01:07:04Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-19T00:44:34Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;When I last &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/mid-maine&quot;&gt;left off&lt;/a&gt; the story of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./tags/AT&quot;&gt;Appalachian Trail&lt;/a&gt; hike, I was in
Stratton with Picker and Grinner.  We left Stratton and almost
immediately I could tell that my new hiking shoes were going to bother
me.  They had a harder sole than I was accustomed to, and so my calf
muscles were feeling some pressure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We made it to the top of North Crocker Mountain and met up with
Wounded Knee again.  He was as socially awkward as ever, and I don&#39;t
remember much of the rest of the day until we met him again at the
end.  I was limping because of the pain in my calves, and Wounded Knee
made some remark about how fast a hiker he was, considering that he
had beaten me to the camp site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day, my calves were even more sore.  It was also raining for
much of the day.  We stopped for a long break about 10 miles into the
day so that we could dry off and avoid the rain for a while.
After the rain had stopped, we climbed Saddleback Junior and went on
to a brand new campsite just past the summit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Saddleback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Some of the nicest views in Southern Maine came on the next day.
  Rather early in the morning, I caught this photo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xpDuqdqRE-o/TOW_u4MaR6I/AAAAAAAAAg8/Gfq875Iod00/s400/DSCF0078.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xpDuqdqRE-o/TOW_u4MaR6I/AAAAAAAAAg8/Gfq875Iod00/s400/DSCF0078.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We were glad that we had waited until after the rain had stopped to
  climb Saddleback, which I think is the mountain that can be seen
  here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8NpeydalE_Q/TOW_wE3rm4I/AAAAAAAAAhY/4TUvkKZ6pgU/s400/DSCF0081.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8NpeydalE_Q/TOW_wE3rm4I/AAAAAAAAAhY/4TUvkKZ6pgU/s400/DSCF0081.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  First of all, it would have been cold and unpleasant if it had been
  raining, but more than that, we got some great views.  Here is the
  view from the top of Saddleback:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-678OhdNhOfg/TOW_zrmxFjI/AAAAAAAAAic/eX-WFora4js/s400/DSCF0087.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-678OhdNhOfg/TOW_zrmxFjI/AAAAAAAAAic/eX-WFora4js/s400/DSCF0087.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After descending Saddleback, we got to a road crossing near
  Rangeley, Maine.  We got a ride to the store from a person who had
  completed his hike a little earlier and was helping hikers on his
  way back south.  After we had gotten back on the trail, Grinner
  realized that she had left her hiking poles in the trail angel&#39;s
  car.  This was a cause for some consternation, but we had to keep
  pushing on.  Picker simply lent Grinner one of his poles, and we
  kept on hiking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Our hike that evening led us to a pond with a canoe docked on it for
  hikers to use.  We took the canoe for a spin and filtered some water
  from the pond (though pond water is generally not very good).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Bemis mountain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After our little paddle, we had a nice weather for most of the next
  day.  It was a good thing, too, because after a fairly easy morning,
  we had a highly treacherous descent followed by a steep ascent.  By
  the time we had reached the shelter, it was raining again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When I awoke the next day, the clouds had dropped and fog had set
  in.  Luckily, Bemis mountain doesn&#39;t have any views to speak of
  anyway.  However, it does have one feature of the mountains in
  Southern Maine: trail that is a fairly sheer slab of rock, often
  with a stream running down it.  This is, needless to say, difficult
  to walk on.  I slipped multiple times before lunch, and was not
  having a great day.  On top of that, after lunch, there were two
  big, steep climbs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the end of the day, we got to a lean-to which contained a hiker
  who said that he had simply stayed there all day.  He had some
  rather depressing stories about how hard Southern Maine had been,
  but in a way, it cheered me up.  I could really see that others
  (even Northbounders, who had already come more than 1900 miles) were
  having trouble too.  As long as I wasn&#39;t alone, I knew I could make
  it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Notches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Our plan the next day was to make it to Baldpate Lean-to, just short
  of Grafton Notch (which contains the southernmost road that the
  trail crosses in Maine).  However, as we were nearing the shelter,
  we came across a group of teenagers.  We went to the shelter and
  found an even larger group of teens.  They had completely taken over
  the shelter and were engaged in several loud games, completely
  disturbing the peace of the outdoors.  In fact, the object of one of
  the games was to scream for the longest.  It was terrible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Luckily for me, I had been lobbying to go on to Grafton Notch for
  most of the day anyway, so I was pleased when Picker and Grinner got
  fed up with the teens and decided to go on.  We made it to Grafton
  Notch and found some trail magic.  I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve described what
  trail magic is yet.  Sometimes people who live near the trail will
  leave food or drink on the trail for hikers.  In this case, a kind
  trail angel had driven his truck to Grafton Notch and was sitting
  with a cooler full of Nestle chocolate milk.  I don&#39;t think I have
  ever been so happy to drink milk, and it started a tradition for me
  of having a chocolate milkshake whenever possible in town.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We hiked about halfway up the next mountain after our refreshment
  and set up camp for the night in the middle of the woods.  This is
  known as &quot;stealth camping&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8pltuMntIbQ/TOW_4ePY2kI/AAAAAAAAAjY/bsjfBmAyuhI/s400/DSCF0096.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8pltuMntIbQ/TOW_4ePY2kI/AAAAAAAAAjY/bsjfBmAyuhI/s400/DSCF0096.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We finished climbing the mountain the next morning, and went in the
  fog past Speck Pond.  It made for a couple of rather pretty pictures of some
  lilypads:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r0GHcdVF2X0/TOW_5EmEoJI/AAAAAAAAAjk/fDU5DQ9XK3U/s400/DSCF0097.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r0GHcdVF2X0/TOW_5EmEoJI/AAAAAAAAAjk/fDU5DQ9XK3U/s400/DSCF0097.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DSra0_gp7yw/TOW_5dWrUaI/AAAAAAAAAjs/VUN6H4ISAeM/s400/DSCF0098.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DSra0_gp7yw/TOW_5dWrUaI/AAAAAAAAAjs/VUN6H4ISAeM/s400/DSCF0098.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Going down from the pond, we had more trails on slippery sheer
  rocks.  Grinner got stuck for a couple of minutes at one point and I
  had to help her get down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the bottom of the hill, we had finally reached Mahoosuc Notch.
  Unfortunately I don&#39;t have any pictures of it (I was trying to
  remain as focussed as possible), because it is one of the most
  interesting features of the trail.  It looks like someone took a
  bunch of house-sized boulders and shook them so that they landed
  randomly at the bottom of a valley.  There are some pictures at the
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahoosuc_Notch&quot;&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; that give a good impression of what it is like.  Note
  especially the arrow painted on the rock &amp;ndash; those are essential to
  making it through in a reasonable amount of time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In any case, we did the one mile through the notch in about two
  hours.  For me, it was not the most enjoyable: I took a bad fall
  right at the entrance to the notch, so my hands were hurting from
  stopping the fall, and I was a bit shaken up.  It was all I could do
  to keep my concentration and not fall again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Finally, we got through the notch and I found that I was out of
  water.  There was no choice but to go on to the shelter to get
  water.  I hiked up the hill as quickly as I could, and fortuitously
  found a water bottle that someone else had dropped.  Not knowing the
  provenance of the water in the bottle, I wasn&#39;t able to drink from
  it, but it would come in handy later in the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I set up my hammock and Picker and Grinner decided to stay in the
  shelter.  It was their first time staying in a shelter with other
  people (they had tented until then), and Picker came over to gripe
  about it a bit.  After supper, I went to throw my bear bag.  At that
  point, I still wasn&#39;t great at it (and I guess I&#39;m still not), but
  one throw was so unfortunate as to be comical.  I had attached my
  water bottle to the line that would hold the bag up on the branch.
  On this particular throw, the water bottle arced behind me and came
  straight down on a sharp rock, splitting into multiple pieces.  I
  was glad I had found the other water bottle, but it was a pretty bad
  end to a rather unpleasant day, which should have been a lot more
  fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Run to the border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;  
  The trail away from the shelter was nearly as hard as the trail to
  it.  There were ladders and rocks to climb up.  Early in the
  morning, as I was trying to climb up one of these rocks, I lost my
  grip and fell again &amp;ndash; this time five to ten feet.  I was extremely
  lucky not to get hurt.  I think the weight of my backpack caused me
  to fall backwards onto it, keeping me from being too badly injured.
  However, I struck my jaw on a rock on the way down, and it would be
  sore for a couple of days afterwards.  After bad falls two days in a
  row, I was eager to get to town.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  First, though, we needed to cross the border between Maine and New
  Hampshire.  Here is a picture proving we did it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-YsZqdhHRV8c/TOW_7TpBdlI/AAAAAAAADfU/yupECnTzq0A/s400/DSCF0100.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-YsZqdhHRV8c/TOW_7TpBdlI/AAAAAAAADfU/yupECnTzq0A/s400/DSCF0100.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We didn&#39;t make it to town that night, but we made it within about
  six miles.  When we finally got to Gorham, NH the next morning,
  things were already seeming better to me.  We were in town and could
  hang out in a hostel for a fairly cheap zero day.  Also, the trail
  angel in whose car Picker had left her poles had left them at the
  hostel, so she got those back.  There was a place for me to get a
  milkshake.  So at least for a day and a half of not-hiking, I was a
  pretty happy hiker.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Just past Gorham is the beginning of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Mountains_(New_Hampshire)&quot;&gt;White mountains&lt;/a&gt;.  I will go
  off on my own in one of the toughest sections of the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/southern-maine/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/southern-maine/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>More ikiwiki plugin hacking</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-4/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-4/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="org-mode" />

	<category term="time-series" />


	<updated>2011-12-15T18:28:05Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-15T18:28:05Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Major progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Now I am able to write wikilinks to images on the local server and
  not just hosted remotely.  For example,
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/time-series-2/interest-rates.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/time-series-2/interest-rates.png&quot; alt=&quot;interest-rates.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an image that I wanted to show
  at the end of &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/time-series-2&quot;&gt;the article on my time-series framework&lt;/a&gt;, but which I
  couldn&#39;t because the org plugin wasn&#39;t able to show images at the
  time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another bit of progress is that I finally debugged the little shell
  shim to allow it to start up the emacs daemon properly.  Now I can
  just have one emacs window running and one emacs daemon in the
  background.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Remaining TODOs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The remaining work left to do should not be too difficult.  I have
  some of my own org customization baked into the file which would be
  better left up to the user&#39;s preferences.  I have to decide whether
  it makes more sense for the user to customize these preferences in
  the ikiwiki configuration file or just in their &lt;code&gt;.emacs&lt;/code&gt;.  The
  latter would be easier for me, but it might be easier for the user
  (especially if they have multiple wikis set up) to do it in the
  ikiwiki configuration file.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I also need to allow for verbatim inclusion of links.  I guess it
  makes more sense to do this in the standard org manner rather than
  the ikiwiki manner (with a backslash in front of the link).
  However, the link must be protected from ikiwiki interpreting it, so
  things might get a little complex there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After those two things are completed, however, I think I&#39;m going to
  call this project done unless I hear feedback from users.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-4/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-4/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Git Annex in Anything</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/anything-git-annex/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/anything-git-annex/"/>






	<category term="anything.el" />

	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="git-annex" />


	<updated>2011-12-12T20:03:17Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-12T20:03:17Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;More fun with emacs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Lately, I&#39;ve been playing around with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/Anything&quot;&gt;anything.el&lt;/a&gt;, which has been
  described as &quot;Quicksilver for emacs&quot;.  I&#39;ve played around with it
  before, but have had a hard time changing my habits so that it&#39;s the
  first thing I think of doing when changing buffers or finding
  files.  The main reason, I think, is that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/IswitchBuffers&quot;&gt;iswitch&lt;/a&gt; is usually just as
  fast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, I have started using &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/git-annex&quot;&gt;git annex&lt;/a&gt; to store my music and
  videos, and that has added some complexity to the way that I deal
  with them.  My usual flow is to do a &lt;code&gt;git annex find&lt;/code&gt; to see what
  files I have on my laptop, after which I play one of them with
  &lt;code&gt;smplayer&lt;/code&gt;.  When I am done with the file, I either use &lt;code&gt;git annex   drop&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;git annex move&lt;/code&gt; to get rid of the file from my laptop.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  All of that takes a lot of typing in the shell, so I wondered
  whether I could speed it up using &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt;.  If you guessed that I
  could (given that I am writing this article), give yourself a gold
  star.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;How I did it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt; is highly extensible.  Anyone can define their own setup
  with a command like this:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-emacs-lisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;my-anything&lt;/span&gt; ()
  (interactive)
  (anything-other-buffer
   &#39;(anything-c-source-buffers+
     anything-c-source-recentf
     anything-c-source-files-in-current-dir+
     anything-c-source-git-annex
     anything-c-source-org-headline
     anything-c-source-bookmarks
     anything-c-source-bookmark-set
     anything-c-source-emms-files)
    &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;*anything*&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  which is just a function that tells &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt; to use a bunch of
  different &quot;sources&quot; as possible interesting things that you might
  want to interact with.  For example, &lt;code&gt;anything-c-source-recentf&lt;/code&gt;
  gives a list of files that you recently had open.  That comes with
  the &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt; package, though, so it&#39;s not too interesting from our
  point of view.  What is interesting is
  &lt;code&gt;anything-c-source-git-annex&lt;/code&gt;.  It looks like this:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-emacs-lisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defvar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;anything-c-source-git-annex&lt;/span&gt;
  &#39;((name . &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;Git Annex&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
    (candidates . (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; ()
                    (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;with-current-buffer&lt;/span&gt; anything-current-buffer
                     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;with-temp-buffer&lt;/span&gt;
                       (call-process &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;git&quot;&lt;/span&gt; nil t nil &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;annex&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;find&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
                       (goto-char (point-min))
                       (split-string (buffer-string) &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)))))
    (volatile)
    (action . ((&lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;Watch&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . anything-c-git-annex-play)
               (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;Drop&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . anything-c-git-annex-drop)
               (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;Move&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . anything-c-git-annex-move)
               (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;Copy&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . anything-c-git-annex-copy)))))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It should hopefully be fairly easy to understand.  There are two
  interesting parts: getting candidate files, and the actions on the
  candidate files.  Getting the candidate files is as simple as
  putting the results of &lt;code&gt;git annex find&lt;/code&gt; into a temporary buffer
  (which must be in the same directory as the current buffer) and then
  putting the lines of the buffer into a list.  (This wouldn&#39;t work if
  the file names contained newlines, but I don&#39;t have any of those.
  If you wanted to be really careful, you could add the &quot;&amp;ndash;print0&quot;
  option to &lt;code&gt;call-process&lt;/code&gt; and split the string on &quot;\0&quot;.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The actions are all functions.  The simplest is
  &lt;code&gt;anything-c-git-annex-drop&lt;/code&gt;, which just looks like
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-emacs-lisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;anything-c-git-annex-drop&lt;/span&gt; (candidate)
  (anything-git-annex-command &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;drop&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (concat &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; candidate &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  where &lt;code&gt;anything-git-annex-command&lt;/code&gt; just starts a shell command.
  More interesting is &lt;code&gt;anything-c-git-annex-copy&lt;/code&gt;, which is defined as
  follows
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-emacs-lisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;anything-c-git-annex-copy&lt;/span&gt; (candidate)
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;let*&lt;/span&gt; ((to (anything-comp-read
              &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;To Git Annex: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;
              (anything-c-git-remotes)
              &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;:must-match&lt;/span&gt; nil)))
    (anything-git-annex-command &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;copy&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (concat &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; candidate &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
                                &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;--to&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (concat &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;anything-c-git-remotes&lt;/span&gt; ()
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;with-temp-buffer&lt;/span&gt;
    (call-process &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;git&quot;&lt;/span&gt; nil (current-buffer) nil &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;remote&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
    (delete &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (split-string (buffer-string) &lt;span style=&quot;color: #cc9393;&quot;&gt;&quot;\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The &lt;code&gt;anything-c-git-annex-copy&lt;/code&gt; command needs to know to which
  repository it should copy the candidate that has been selected.  I
  find out which one I want to copy to by listing the remotes that are
  known about by the git repository that the file is in.  Using
  &lt;code&gt;anything-comp-read&lt;/code&gt; means that the remotes are listed in the same
  style all of the &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt; candidates are listed in.  It&#39;s pretty
  nice, because it keeps me in the same mode of operation as before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It&#39;s a bit hard to write about what makes &lt;code&gt;anything.el&lt;/code&gt; an
  interesting way of doing things in emacs &amp;ndash; a screencast might be
  more helpful &amp;ndash; but I hope some of the power is evident from this
  little writeup.  I&#39;m going to try to train myself to use &lt;code&gt;anything&lt;/code&gt;
  more often.  We&#39;ll see how it goes.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/anything-git-annex/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/anything-git-annex/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Lessons learned (so far) from the ikiwiki plugin</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2011-12-07T22:42:09Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-07T22:00:36Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Writing my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin&quot;&gt;new plugin&lt;/a&gt; in Emacs Lisp, I learned a few things.  Here are
some of them, in no particular order.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;xml-rpc.el has some problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t mean to be unkind here.  xml-rpc.el seems pretty good if you
  are doing exactly one kind of thing: calling a method on a server
  that can be reached by http.  For anything else, it is very hard to
  use.   My plugin has the following requirements:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It must be called by another program through xml-rpc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It must read from and write to files (and not http).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;    
  Neither of these things is made easy with xml-rpc.  The first I can
  understand &amp;ndash; xml-rpc would have to somehow insinuate itself into
  the emacs event loop and watch for calls all the time.  The second
  is less easy to understand.  Parsing xml-rpc is not really related
  to reading from http.  So why are the two things tied together?  In
  my opinion, xml-rpc.el would be a much nicer library if parsing the
  xml-rpc was separated completely from the http stuff.  There could
  be convenience functions, but they would be a layer of abstraction
  on top of the other two layers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;xml.el has some problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There isn&#39;t a function to get a list of all nodes with a given name?
  Are you kidding me?  Here is my implementation, but I bet there is a
  better one somewhere:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;xml-find-nodes-matching&lt;/span&gt; (node name)
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&quot;Returns all children of `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;node&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39; that have an `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;xml-node-name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39; equal to `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (or (eq node &#39;()) (not (listp node)))
      &#39;()
    (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (equal (xml-node-name node) name)
        (cons node (delq nil (mapcar (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; (nd) (xml-find-nodes-matching nd name)) (xml-node-children node))))
      (delq nil (apply &#39;append (mapcar (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; (nd) (xml-find-nodes-matching nd name)) (xml-node-children node)))))))
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In general, both xml-rpc.el and xml.el use a distressing number of
  calls to &lt;code&gt;car&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;cdaddr&lt;/code&gt; (and all the versions in
  between).  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Perl has some problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Ikiwiki sends named parameters as an even-lengthed xml-rpc array
  rather than as an xml-rpc struct.  This is because not all of the
  functions that can be called via xml-rpc take named parameters and I
  guess Perl isn&#39;t smart enough to tell a hash from an even-lengthed
  array.  This isn&#39;t a huge problem, but it does mean that I need to
  convert the input to each of the functions that I write into a hash
  before I use it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Ikiwiki has some problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I would like to be able to ignore files that don&#39;t have a particular
  extension.  For &lt;code&gt;htmlify&lt;/code&gt;, this is the way it works by default.  It
  seems like most of the functions that plugins can implement are not
  this way by default, though, and that is a shame.  If the plugin is
  not external &amp;ndash; that is, it is written in Perl &amp;ndash; there is really no
  problem.  The function is called, checks the extension of the source
  file, and returns without doing anything.  However, when the plugin
  is external and the call must happen through xml-rpc, ikiwiki must
  transmit the data via xml-rpc and receive the returned data back via
  xml-rpc.  Unnecessary calls take a lot longer in that context.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I would like for most calls to &lt;code&gt;hook&lt;/code&gt; to take an optional
  &lt;code&gt;extension&lt;/code&gt; parameter that takes an extension (or even better, a
  regexp), and only call the function if the file name has the same
  extension (or matches the regexp).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Working with emacs buffers is pretty nice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Does a function that you&#39;re trying to write in emacs lisp give you a
  string?  It&#39;s pretty easy to throw it in a temporary buffer and then
  tell emacs to do the things that you would normally do while you
  were editing in order to get the proper information out of the
  string.  The &lt;code&gt;with-temporary-buffer&lt;/code&gt; macro makes it especially easy
  to do just that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Getting info from a structured list is easier to do as a recursive function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  One of the things that took me the longest was to figure out what
  this couple of lines of code was doing:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(setq valtype (car (caddar xml-list))
      valvalue (caddr (caddar xml-list)))  
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  What should the value of &lt;code&gt;xml-list&lt;/code&gt; look like in order to get the
  correct thing out of it?  It turned out that I needed to take the
  &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;cdaddr&lt;/code&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;caddar&lt;/code&gt; of the parsed xml in order to
  get the correct value.  That only worked when ikiwiki was responding
  to a method call, though.  I had a much easier time getting the
  right values out when I simply started using the
  &lt;code&gt;xml-find-nodes-matching&lt;/code&gt; function that I showed above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When you see yourself writing more than a few &lt;code&gt;car&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt; calls
  in a row (or &lt;code&gt;first&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rest&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;nth&lt;/code&gt; calls in Clojure), stop and
  try to write a function that finds what you are looking for.  The
  function doesn&#39;t have to be recursive, but that might be the easiest
  way to do it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-7&quot;&gt;It&#39;s nice when all calls and responses are dumped to a file&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In a sense, this is just saying that code can be easier to debug if
  you&#39;re tracing it.  But since the calls between ikiwiki and the
  plugin must go through files anyway, we get the program traced
  automatically.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
