<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Hiking and Coding</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111107">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-03-14T15:47:03Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Org Plugin Rethink</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2012-03-14T15:47:03Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-14T15:47:03Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I am glad to announce a new version of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/ikiwiki-org-plugin&quot;&gt;ikiwiki org plugin&lt;/a&gt;.  This is
a major change to the way things had worked previously, and is much
faster than previous versions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The installation procedure has changed, so please read the
&lt;code&gt;README.org&lt;/code&gt; file in the repository for information about how to
install the plugin.  Also, if you have installed a previous version,
please remove that since it may conflict.  Also be sure that you kill
any daemonized versions of emacs that are running.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This version of the plugin is no longer what ikiwiki calls an
  &quot;external plugin&quot;.  The overhead associated with XML-RPC was simply
  too high (at least on the emacs side of things).  I tried
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/ikiwiki-hacking&quot;&gt;working around&lt;/a&gt; it by having less communication between the compiler
  and the plugin, but the ikiwiki developers &lt;a href=&quot;http://ikiwiki.info/todo/be_more_selective_about_running_hooks/&quot;&gt;didn&#39;t really think it was a great idea&lt;/a&gt;.  So I have basically scrapped the idea of the
  plugin being external.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The nice thing about that is that it allowed me to remove a lot of
  code on the emacs side.  Instead of communication via XML-RPC, the
  new plugin can put the content to be interpreted in a file and call
  emacsclient directly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I note in &lt;code&gt;README.org&lt;/code&gt; that there is a concern about security.  This
  is because any program that calls another program with
  user-generated arguments should be concerned about security.  As far
  as I can tell, the only way that something bad can happen is if
  someone creates a filename with an unmatched double-quote and
  convinces ikiwiki to accept it.  Since ikiwiki doesn&#39;t accept
  filenames with double-quotes anyway, there really shouldn&#39;t be a
  problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, I would recommend that this plugin not be used in
  situations where untrusted people can create files (such as from the
  CGI interface), unless you personally verify that nothing bad can
  happen.  As always, this is free software and comes with no
  warranty.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Remaining todos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I would like to get rid of the potential security hole so that
  people could feel safe running this plugin from the CGI interface.
  I would also like to get rid of the hardcoded org configuration and
  let that be stored in the user&#39;s setup file.  I have a branch that
  does that using the old architecture, so it should not be too
  difficult to port to the new architecture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Hiking Philosophy</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="PCT" />

	<category term="gear" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-14T04:52:20Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-13T19:50:44Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have written an account of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./tags/AT&quot;&gt;AT hike&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I would
write down some things that I think are true about hiking before
writing about the next hike.  The first thing to note is that I
subscribe completely to the hike-your-own-hike (HYOH) philosophy, so
this should be read as descriptive more than prescriptive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, I lied.  This is the one prescription.  Read the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lnt.org/programs/principles.php&quot;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;
  and follow them.  Also follow any other rules that are in place for
  the area that you&#39;re in.  If it says not to make camp fires, then
  don&#39;t.  It&#39;s a pity to need to say this, but I&#39;ve seen experienced
  hikers break the rules (and I&#39;m not perfect either, but I do my
  best).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So much of the conversation about hiking with non-hikers or
  inexperienced hikers is about dangerous animals.  I probably saw
  less than one bear for every month of hiking that I did, and they
  were all running away from me.  I never hiked in grizzy country, and
  if I ever do, I&#39;ll think about maybe carrying bear spray, though I
  doubt I will in the end.  Wilderness is vast and bears and other
  dangerous animals are sparse.  They generally don&#39;t want anything to
  do with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most scared I was of an animal on the AT was the time I saw a
  skunk on the trail in the Shenandoahs.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m generally not an ultralighter, though I&#39;m moving more in that
  direction.  This is the gear that I used.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-1&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I love my hammock.  It&#39;s lighter than many tents, far more
   comfortable than sleeping on the ground, and you don&#39;t need to find
   a flat spot to set it up.  On the other hand, you do need to find
   suitable trees.  This is easy in a pine forest and is probably
   impossible in the plains.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-2&quot;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Not boots.  I grew to be very happy with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004C0ZOEG/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004C0ZOEG&quot;&gt;North Face Singletrack&lt;/a&gt;
   trail-running shoe.  It is a bit more rugged than a normal running
   shoe, but far less stiff and heavy than a boot.  I like my shoes to
   last at least 10 miles per dollar.  The Singletrack normally costs
   about $100 and lasts about 1000 miles, so that works out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-3&quot;&gt;Pack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I wore the same pack for both of my thru-hikes: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0034NUZ8M/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0034NUZ8M&quot;&gt;Black Diamond Infinity 60&lt;/a&gt;.  It worked well, though I came to feel that it was
   heavier than it needed to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-4&quot;&gt;Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   All synthetic.  For the AT hike, I wore the same shirt and shorts
   most of the way.  I got a new pair of shorts in Damascus, just
   because I was getting tired of the pair that I was wearing.  I
   started my AT hike with three pairs of socks and they lasted me the
   whole way.  I would generally change socks only as needed because
   they were wet or once per week during dry sections.  I carried the
   following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One short-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One long-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two pairs of underwear
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of shorts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of long pants
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three pairs of socks
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One fleece
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One rain jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One down jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;     
   On sections that I knew would be very cold, I carried a hat and
   gloves.  In the Sierras I carried wool tights as well, and there
   were nights where I wore everything that I was carrying.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-5&quot;&gt;Sleeping Bag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have a fairly generic down sleeping bag from &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt;.  Since it&#39;s
   down, I must be very careful to keep it dry.  To do this, I keep it
   in a trash bag inside its stuff sack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-6&quot;&gt;Bear canister&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   It&#39;s the law that you must carry one in the Sierras, so I did.
   They are the worst &amp;ndash; heavy and bulky, and they still don&#39;t fit as
   much food as a normal food bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-7&quot;&gt;Hiking poles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   As far as I can tell, simpler is better.  A strap is good and
   telescoping is good so that they fit in cars when hitching.  I&#39;ve
   never used poles with shock absorbers, but I really don&#39;t see how
   they would help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-8&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-8&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-8&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The main change between my hikes was my stove.  On my AT hike, I
   used a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004P78F88/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004P78F88&quot;&gt;MSR Whisperlite&lt;/a&gt; stove.  It&#39;s a great stove &amp;ndash; it puts out
   varying levels of heat and is very fuel efficient &amp;ndash; but I thought
   it was a bit heavy for one person.  So on my PCT hike, I took a
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003LDCVBY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B003LDCVBY&quot;&gt;Vargo&lt;/a&gt; titanium alcohol stove.  It was lighter, but only had one
   temperature, was more prone to accidents, was a pain to fill, and
   required more fuel.  I know that if I was going on a hike with more
   than one person, I would take the Whisperlite, but I don&#39;t know
   what I&#39;d do on another solo hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-9&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-9&quot;&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-9&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   For some hikes, they are necessary, for others emphatically not.  I
   took the &lt;a href=&quot;http://theatguide.com/&quot;&gt;AWOL guide&lt;/a&gt; on my AT hike and printed out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pctmap.net/&quot;&gt;Halfmile maps&lt;/a&gt;
   for my PCT hike.  Since the AT is so well marked, only an elevation
   profile is necessary so that you know how difficult the next
   stretch of trail will be.  On the other hand, it is important to
   have maps on the PCT because there are places where the trail is
   not obvious.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-10&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-10&quot;&gt;Bear Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-10&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have about 50 feet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parachute_cord&quot;&gt;parachute cord&lt;/a&gt; that I attach the lightest
   possible carabiner to.  I then use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qgBLDMuPuvE&quot;&gt;PCT Method&lt;/a&gt; to hang the food
   bag from the tree (with varying degrees of success).  As I noted
   earlier, I&#39;m generally not too concerned about actual bears, but
   hanging food is always a good thing, especially near established
   campsites where there is a high probability of rodents.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Packing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m a firm believer that you should always pack in a consistent
  manner.  This saves you time rooting around in your pack.  The only
  tip that I have is that the sleeping bag should go on the bottom.
  You won&#39;t need it all day, and it&#39;s nice to have something soft on
  the bottom of your pack if you put it down quickly or fall down
  backwards.  Other than that, I don&#39;t think the order matters too
  much as long as it&#39;s consistent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Both of my long hikes have been solo hikes in the sense that I made
  no explicit arrangement with anyone else to hike together.  In both
  hikes, I have had periods of being truly alone and periods where I
  would regularly meet up with the same people nearly every night.  I
  probably enjoyed myself the most when I was in groups of three or
  four, but I also think that it would be nearly impossible for me to
  stay with one single group for an entire hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The community aspect of hiking is one of its strongest
  selling-points.  You meet all kinds of people who are all doing the
  same thing as you.  So that gives you something to talk about right
  away.  Nothing bonds like shared misery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is also a strong sense that everyone is looking out for each
  other.  This was put into the starkest relief for me when I was
  hiking in the Sierras on the PCT, so I&#39;ll go into it in more detail
  when I get around to writing about that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I might write another of these more general posts about hiking later.
  I still haven&#39;t touched on things like a daily schedule or what town
  stops are like.  For now, however, I think this post has gotten long
  enough.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Georgia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ga/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ga/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-06T18:24:58Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-06T18:24:58Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I entered Georgia with one goal: get to Springer Mountain by my
birthday.  It&#39;s about 75 miles from the border to Springer, and I had
three and a half days, so I thought that I had a pretty good chance of
getting there on time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I needed to make one final stop in town before I got to the end for my
last resupply.  I got to the highway at about 5:00 and soon got a
hitch into Hiawassee.  67.5 miles to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Hiawassee to Springer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, back on the trail with three days of food, I took
  an early break.  I went to put my pack on, and the buckle for the
  hip belt broke!  Some people with ultralight packs can hike without
  a hip belt, but I am not one of them (though I wish I was).  For
  me, the hip belt is the thing that bears most of the weight of the
  pack and the shoulder straps are more for stabilization.  In short,
  this almost rose to the level of an emergency.  Had it been earlier
  in the trip, or if I had not set a self-imposed deadline for the end
  of the hike, I might have turned around and hiked back to the road.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There was no way I was going to do that though.  I tried hiking
  without the hip belt for a little while, but it quickly became
  obvious that that wouldn&#39;t work.  It was time for some
  out-of-the-box thinking.  I seriously considered just leaving the
  pack behind and running the rest of the way to Springer.  I know
  that people run that far in less than 24 hours all the time, and
  considering the shape I was in, I probably could have done it.
  However, leaving all my stuff in the back woods of Georgia seemed
  like something to do only as a last resort, and spending a night
  without my pack would be too awful to risk.  Finally, I realized
  that I had my rope that I used to hang my bear bag.  I cut about a
  foot from that and tied the straps of my hip belt together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Thankfully, it worked.  I soon got just as good at tying the hip
  belt together as I had been at buckling it.  It looked a little
  funny, like a person with a rope for a belt, but in the woods
  there&#39;s really no one to judge that sort of thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The terrain was hilly that day, and between that and my hip-belt
  disaster, I didn&#39;t make it that far.  I ended up on the top of Rocky
  Mountain with 52.2 miles to go and two full days of hiking left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Fortunately, the hills were less steep the next day, the weather was
  great, and I was on a roll.  With each mile that I got closer to the
  end of my journey, the better I felt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OBun7vrnzl4/TOXC8p5RC1I/AAAAAAAABPI/gWK7F1WvMdY/s800/DSCF0429.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OBun7vrnzl4/TOXC8p5RC1I/AAAAAAAABPI/gWK7F1WvMdY/s800/DSCF0429.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Near the end of the day, I came to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_Mountain&quot;&gt;Blood Mountain&lt;/a&gt;.  There is a
  shelter near the top, but it is 28.3 miles from Springer, so I kept
  on going.  I walked for about two more hours to get to a small
  campsite near a stream 22.3 miles from the finish line.  One day
  left, and within striking distance.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The final day was much like the previous 131.  I got up early, had
  breakfast and walked.  I did see a small family of wild pigs in the
  morning, but it was otherwise a day pretty much like any other.  As
  I got closer to the end, my pace picked up, and I flew past some
  day-hikers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Springer Mountain is nothing compared to &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness&quot;&gt;Katahdin&lt;/a&gt;.  I am willing to
  stipulate that much.  Some will say that makes finishing a
  southbound AT hike anticlimactic, and that is one step too far for
  me.  I had walked nearly 2200 miles in the wilderness to get there;
  it was pretty damn climactic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vasthhIyDsw/TOXDBoTkJqI/AAAAAAAABQg/2XvPPR9mj_Q/s640/DSCF0437.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vasthhIyDsw/TOXDBoTkJqI/AAAAAAAABQg/2XvPPR9mj_Q/s640/DSCF0437.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I finished on my birthday, just as I had hoped.  It really was a
  great way to spend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-oucyoSno3wE/TOXDFWGUSkI/AAAAAAAABRc/yJsPJxobONY/s800/DSCF0450.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-oucyoSno3wE/TOXDFWGUSkI/AAAAAAAABRc/yJsPJxobONY/s800/DSCF0450.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Coda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The terminus of the trail is the top of a mountain.  There is no
  road up to there &amp;ndash; to get home you must take another trail.  I
  walked about a mile down that after finishing the AT, and camped one
  last time.  I was out of fuel, so I made my only campfire of the
  entire hike and made supper over that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I hiked out the next day past &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amicalola_Falls&quot;&gt;Amicalola Falls&lt;/a&gt;.  At the end, there is
  a visitor&#39;s center, where I made sure to sign the final log book,
  and then I had to think about getting home.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-MHSIhlA5HjA/TOXDMRbU5kI/AAAAAAAAAYY/R50fqbApYss/s800/DSCF0466.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-MHSIhlA5HjA/TOXDMRbU5kI/AAAAAAAAAYY/R50fqbApYss/s800/DSCF0466.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Hitching in a tourist area is never easy, so in the end I resorted
  to asking for rides from people who wanted to talk about my hike.  A
  nice older couple gave another hiker and me a ride into Atlanta, and
  just like that I was back in civilization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  That&#39;s it for the AT, but it&#39;s less than half of my long hikes.
  Depending on my mood, I might start right in on the PCT, or I might
  go a little deeper into the gear I used and other more general
  thoughts that I have about hiking.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ga/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ga/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Tennessee and North Carolina</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/tn-nc/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/tn-nc/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-05T21:19:25Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-05T21:19:25Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Damascus to Erwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I had a great time in Damascus with the little crew that I had met
  up with a few days earlier, but they wanted to stay in town a little
  longer than I did, so I went on without them.  The first day out of
  town, I had a certain shelter in mind to end at, but it got dark
  before I got there and, having no desire to night-hike, I simply
  stopped in the middle of a hill and set up my hammock.  I&#39;m fairly
  sure that was one of my most random campsites.  I didn&#39;t think it
  looked any good as a campsite, but I was tired and wanted to stop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8fZ-ti3dcz4/TOXCLpKx74I/AAAAAAAABEs/hkBzRoF-np0/s800/DSCF0357.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8fZ-ti3dcz4/TOXCLpKx74I/AAAAAAAABEs/hkBzRoF-np0/s800/DSCF0357.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laurel Fork Falls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Maybe my thinking was skewed by the fact that I knew that if I could
  hike 25 miles per day for the next four days, I could stay at a
  hostel for each of them.   The first of these days took me to the
  Kincora hostel, home of Bob Peoples.  Bob is a trail maintainer in
  addition to being a hostel-keeper, and is a trail fixture.  Most of
  the graffiti in the shelters leading to his hostel consists of Chuck
  Norris-style jokes about him (all complimentary of course).  He has
  been running the hostel for over 20 years and still only charges $4
  per night.  While I was there, we sat and chatted a bit.  He told me
  about his previous hike in Europe and his plan for the next summer
  to work on the International AT in Canada, adding cairns so people
  can find their way in Newfoundland.  For an older guy (he must be
  nearly 70), he sure gets his kicks on the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-lBicNB2_kco/TOXCKDcoHUI/AAAAAAAABEY/rAERWP-mCKo/s800/DSCF0355.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-lBicNB2_kco/TOXCKDcoHUI/AAAAAAAABEY/rAERWP-mCKo/s800/DSCF0355.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The leaves by this point had all turned, and most of them were
  brown.  There were a few patches of color left, though.  For the
  most part, I was still in the &quot;tunnel&quot; of trees and branches, but
  the falling leaves gave some more opportunities to see outside it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WZ8VczQj33M/TOXCMx27zhI/AAAAAAAABFE/cLmrOJSzRwg/s800/DSCF0359.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WZ8VczQj33M/TOXCMx27zhI/AAAAAAAABFE/cLmrOJSzRwg/s800/DSCF0359.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next night I made it to the next hostel.  This was the Mountain
  Harbour Hostel.  They have a room above a barn that is really nice,
  but unfortunately it was booked by the time that I got there.  I did
  use it to shower in and watched City Slickers (a great trail movie
  by the way) before going to bed in an RV.  It was comfortable, but
  not as neat as the barn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day started with a big climb up Hump Mountain.  It is the
  first of the &quot;balds&quot; that a southbound hiker hits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-S1hfxMHYxhA/TOXCPGGVckI/AAAAAAAABFw/-xlAKwyqRBc/s800/DSCF0366.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-S1hfxMHYxhA/TOXCPGGVckI/AAAAAAAABFw/-xlAKwyqRBc/s800/DSCF0366.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As you can see, there are no trees &amp;ndash; it is just long grass.  After
  nearly 1800 miles of nearly consistent tree cover (and alpine
  terrain on the tops of mountains), this is a welcome change.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xv4qN3hMZf0/TOXCQy1_0lI/AAAAAAAABGQ/Uu7uw2GRvfQ/s800/DSCF0370.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xv4qN3hMZf0/TOXCQy1_0lI/AAAAAAAABGQ/Uu7uw2GRvfQ/s800/DSCF0370.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually the trail goes over 6000 feet elevation at Roan High
  Knob.  There is a shelter at the top, where I am sure it gets quite
  cold at night, but I wouldn&#39;t know because I wanted to get to the
  next hostel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next hostel was not a hostel but a &quot;friendly&quot; (get it?
  hostel&amp;hellip; hostile&amp;hellip; friendly (it&#39;s not a great joke)).  The
  proprietress, who was quirky but nice, wasn&#39;t there when I arrived,
  but she left a key so that I could get situated and watch a little
  TV.  She cooked me a great breakfast the next morning and I was on
  my way to the next one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The weather that day was rainy, and I got to use the rain jacket
  that I had purchased in Virginia for the first time.  Going up some
  rather high mountains in a thunderstorm wasn&#39;t so fun, but I was on
  a mission.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-18-yC2TThzA/TOXCUUsDYDI/AAAAAAAABHE/RlzjBWtuZEA/s800/DSCF0376.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-18-yC2TThzA/TOXCUUsDYDI/AAAAAAAABHE/RlzjBWtuZEA/s800/DSCF0376.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Luckily, the rain didn&#39;t last long, and soon it was a mere memory.
  I kept pushing on and made it to Erwin, TN by mid-afternoon.  The
  hostel in Erwin had a bunch of old guys just hanging around.  I
  might have found them amusing under other circumstances, but as it
  was I just found them (and Erwin by extension) a little sad.
  I got a resupply that evening and was out early the next morning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-bNeMS0NsS-0/TOXCU1n69JI/AAAAAAAABHM/qHUwMddoRbQ/s800/DSCF0377.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-bNeMS0NsS-0/TOXCU1n69JI/AAAAAAAABHM/qHUwMddoRbQ/s800/DSCF0377.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Erwin to Gatlinburg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Out of Erwin, there is some significant climbing, and that combined
  with the threat of rain conspired to stop me after only 16 miles.
  I was glad to have stopped, because it did rain that evening and
  some the next morning as well.  Once again, the rain cleared up by
  the afternoon, and by the end of the day I was happy to be walking
  down the trail.  At the end of the day I came upon Hot Springs, NC.
  It was dark by the time I found the hostel that I had heard about.
  It is run by a Buddhist monk who makes gourmet vegetarian food.
  Naturally, I took a zero there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By this time, I had done the math and determined that I could finish
  on my birthday if I kept a decent pace.  The zero set me back a
  little bit, so from then on I needed to really push: the only thing
  in my way was the Great Smoky Mountain National Park.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I met up with Skittles again the day after I left Hot Springs.  He
  had a bit of a falling-out with the rest of the group (as I
  understood it) and had hiked ahead of them.  It was nice to be
  around someone that I knew again, but we had such radically
  different paces during the day that we were never around each other
  for very long.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day ended just inside the national park at a shelter that
  had a chain-link fence enclosing it to keep the bears out.  There
  was a group there, and after a while it became clear to me that they
  were a church group.  Skittles showed up late and he never got the
  memo.  The next morning, he went with them to the top of a mountain
  off-trail (there were a couple of pretty young ladies in the group,
  and he thought he had a chance) and only found out then.  As he told
  me, he was pretty mad when he found out and spent a couple of hours
  arguing with them about the existence of God.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I, on the other hand, went to a shelter half a mile off the trail
  and spent the night alone at a mile high.  There were bear warnings
  all over, but I didn&#39;t see one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-oSiqXRADocw/TOXCfollvCI/AAAAAAAABJc/jmQjhW8uoE0/s800/DSCF0391.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-oSiqXRADocw/TOXCfollvCI/AAAAAAAABJc/jmQjhW8uoE0/s800/DSCF0391.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I love views where the mountains seem to be stacked one behind the
  other.  The Smokies had that in abundance, and the haze in these
  photos really shows where they got their name.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-USFWqkYdXng/TOXCgu51wWI/AAAAAAAABJ0/CkG9EF1uqOo/s800/DSCF0394.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-USFWqkYdXng/TOXCgu51wWI/AAAAAAAABJ0/CkG9EF1uqOo/s800/DSCF0394.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was only about 10 miles from the road Gatlinburg, and got there
  easily by noon.  Despite the throngs of tourists, I wasn&#39;t able to
  get a hitch for over an hour (and even that was in the back of a
  pickup truck &amp;ndash; not fun for 15 miles at 60 miles per hour).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Gatlinburg is a strange place.  It&#39;s now overshadowed by Dollywood,
  but it was once the premier tourist destination in the area.  As
  such, it has everything you wouldn&#39;t expect: a Ripley&#39;s Believe it
  or Not, cable cars, a wax museum.  The only thing that isn&#39;t
  accessible in town is a grocery store.  I had to wait for a bus to
  take me out of town and back in order to resupply.  By the time I
  had gotten everything that I needed, it was getting pretty late, so
  I decided to stay in town.  The one advantage of it being such a
  touristy town is that there are many motels, and they&#39;re all pretty
  cheap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gatlinburg to the border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I got picked up by a guy going back to the trail to do some trail
  maintenance the next day.  Soon after getting dropped off, I hit the
  highest point on the trail &amp;ndash; Clingman&#39;s Dome.  For some reason
  unknown to man, there is a completely ugly structure on top.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DoWWt_id7ug/TOXCqBMQf_I/AAAAAAAABLU/C2ebU9qnbQQ/s800/DSCF0404.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DoWWt_id7ug/TOXCqBMQf_I/AAAAAAAABLU/C2ebU9qnbQQ/s800/DSCF0404.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The hike was all relatively downhill from there&lt;a href=&quot;http://instantrimshot.com/&quot;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;  The next morning
  it snowed for the first time on the hike.  At first, this seemed
  exciting and fun, but it really was just a colder version of rain.
  I stayed at a shelter called the &quot;Fontana Hilton&quot; that night, so
  called because it&#39;s a large shelter near the Fontana Dam.  It&#39;s
  nowhere near as comfortable as a Hilton hotel, though, and it was
  packed for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was even snowier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-q0DG66O-4Fw/TOXCvSy-B6I/AAAAAAAABMg/dd4ADNAEevY/s800/DSCF0411.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-q0DG66O-4Fw/TOXCvSy-B6I/AAAAAAAABMg/dd4ADNAEevY/s800/DSCF0411.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The snow didn&#39;t slow me down too much, because I was on a mission to
  get to the Nantahala Outdoor Center.  I hit a shelter full of people
  at about 5 pm with about 7 miles left to go before I got there.  I
  didn&#39;t even hesitate about staying at the shelter.  I knew that if I
  was going to make it to the end by my birthday, I would have to do
  the miles that night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I eventually did make it to the outdoor center, after a little bit
  of night-hiking.  I am almost always against the idea of
  night-hiking, but it really is magical in the snow: everywhere that
  your headlamp hits just sparkles.  I was really glad to be inside
  that night &amp;ndash; it snowed more and got quite cold outside and I was
  snug inside.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning was still cold, so I went and bought a cap at the
  outfitter.  It was a good thing that I did too, because I was cold
  almost all of that day.  That night it got the coldest that it ever
  was on the trail.  My sleeping bag, rated at 0 C (meaning that
  I should be comfortable all the way down to that temperature) was
  really not warm enough.  I slept in all my clothes and had just my
  nose poking out the top.  It was cold.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Thankfully, that was the coldest night that I spent on the trail.
  The sun came out the next day and never went away again.  I passed
  the point where I only had 100 miles left and at that point I was
  pretty certain that I would make it.  I had 4 days left until my
  birthday, and I was also pretty certain that I would make it by
  then.  Thinking back to the beginning of my hike, that would have
  been hubris, but now that I had gotten near the end, it really was
  justified confidence.  That said, there were some tests to come, but
  no more in North Carolina, because I was almost out of there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Acn7auhOXgQ/TOXC3T_cAcI/AAAAAAAABN4/k6GNwAfjk-s/s800/DSCF0419.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Acn7auhOXgQ/TOXC3T_cAcI/AAAAAAAABN4/k6GNwAfjk-s/s800/DSCF0419.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--e9fCfWHt4E/TOXC7Gn8PBI/AAAAAAAABO4/EZwr8ffhoWw/s800/DSCF0427.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--e9fCfWHt4E/TOXC7Gn8PBI/AAAAAAAABO4/EZwr8ffhoWw/s800/DSCF0427.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final state line&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Georgia.  The last state on the trail, containing the final
  challenge for my hike.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/tn-nc/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/tn-nc/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Central and Southern Virginia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/central-va/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/central-va/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-29T19:10:24Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-29T19:10:24Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Waynesboro to Daleville&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/north-va&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned what a hard time I had in the
  Shenandoah National Park because of the rain.  In Waynesboro, I
  decided to do something about that.  I mailed my rain jacket home
  and went to an outfitters to get a new one.  I got a nice compact
  down jacket while I was at it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is a diner in town that has all-you-can-eat pancakes, so
  breakfast and lunch were taken care of.  I couldn&#39;t walk very fast
  with so much food in my stomach, though, so I didn&#39;t go far past
  Waynesboro.  At the shelter, I met Farm-a-sea, whose trail name had
  a double meaning.  He was training to become a fish farmer when he
  wasn&#39;t hiking, and he also had a sizable cache of medicinal herbs.
  He was an interesting guy though.  He would pack a dozen eggs and a
  large hunk of bacon out of town.  He had a skillet for frying them
  in, and would build a fire at every shelter and cook his supper in
  the skillet.  Really old-school stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The terrain in Virginia became hilly once again.  After the flatness
  of Pennsylvania, this took some getting used to.  Also, since
  Southern Pennsylvania, the leaves had been falling, and by Central
  Virginia, they were falling in earnest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/---71aZGG9Pw/TOXBaqs19sI/AAAAAAAAA5A/yMiEIbVmITA/s800/DSCF0279.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/---71aZGG9Pw/TOXBaqs19sI/AAAAAAAAA5A/yMiEIbVmITA/s800/DSCF0279.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was in this section that I realized that I had not packed enough
  food for the number of days that I would need if I was going to
  continue at the same average speed.  Thus, I needed to pick up my
  average mileage considerably.  I did two 30-mile days and two
  25-mile days into Daleville.  There was some interesting scenery on
  the way, including this rock formation, rather ominously named &quot;The
  Guillotine&quot;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5QG7ZkAwCsw/TOXBkYjN3vI/AAAAAAAAA7w/ToGxgOOKRSo/s800/DSCF0298.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5QG7ZkAwCsw/TOXBkYjN3vI/AAAAAAAAA7w/ToGxgOOKRSo/s800/DSCF0298.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the time I got to Daleville, I was in a pretty serious calorie
  deficit.  I went and had a big supper at a crappy Mexican
  restaurant, followed by two beers from the store in my motel room.
  I could tell midway through the second beer that it wasn&#39;t a good
  idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Daleville to Damascus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I was hung over all the next day.  However, following my experience
  from the previous week, I tried to make miles and not allow it to
  slow me down.  I didn&#39;t want to be stuck without food once again.
  Hiking with a hangover is really terrible, though, and it seemed
  like every 10 minutes I needed to sit down or bend over and try to
  vomit.  I didn&#39;t get anything out all day, but I didn&#39;t eat anything
  either, so by the end of the day I was getting hungry.  I took this
  as a good sign and ate some Teriyaki Noodles.  I couldn&#39;t keep them
  down through the night, but after I had gone into the woods to
  deposit them on the ground, I finally felt better.  However, the
  memory of that day has been enough to keep me from drinking alcohol
  ever since.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/4/4c/McAfee_Knob.jpg/1024px-McAfee_Knob.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/4/4c/McAfee_Knob.jpg/1024px-McAfee_Knob.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  
  The next days were better, though marred by bad trail maintenance
  and ragweed.  One highlight was the second-largest oak tree on the
  trail:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6sYDOs4YlL4/TOXBsVEoBOI/AAAAAAAAA9w/uI7VlAy6UmY/s800/DSCF0312.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6sYDOs4YlL4/TOXBsVEoBOI/AAAAAAAAA9w/uI7VlAy6UmY/s800/DSCF0312.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The day after that picture was taken, I ended up at The Captain&#39;s
  place, a small hostel with tenting in the yard.  The really
  interesting feature of it was that you needed to take a cable car
  across the creek to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The following day, I ended up at Pearisburg.  It is another
  spread-out town, and I had to walk a couple of miles to get to the
  store.  However, I had had a sleeping bag sent there because mine
  had been leaking feathers for quite a while, and I was able to pick
  it up, so that was nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I went to the Woods Hole hostel the next day, which was a greatly
  relaxing day.  One of the hostel-keepers teaches yoga and the other
  is a masseur (though the massages weren&#39;t free, and I didn&#39;t feel
  like getting one).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-as7GEIfL9gY/TOXB5mbZT9I/AAAAAAAABA0/VeqESiZRKfc/s800/DSCF0332.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-as7GEIfL9gY/TOXB5mbZT9I/AAAAAAAABA0/VeqESiZRKfc/s800/DSCF0332.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After Woods Hole, I really started rolling.  I did a 20-mile day the
  next day and a 34-mile day the day after that.  This took me to the
  Chestnut Knob shelter, which is a completely enclosed shelter on the
  top of a mountain.  It was windy all night, but I slept fairly
  comfortably after my long day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next two days weren&#39;t too special.  I stayed in a motel near the
  interstate and a shelter that was reportedly haunted (though I saw
  no evidence of a haunting).  The day after that, though I entered
  the Grayson Highlands State Park.  This is a park that is famous for
  the wild ponies that roam it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pi9paLjIp4w/TOXCC-zwgTI/AAAAAAAABCw/2s80vuVgMmk/s800/DSCF0345.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pi9paLjIp4w/TOXCC-zwgTI/AAAAAAAABCw/2s80vuVgMmk/s800/DSCF0345.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got a picture with me near them that shows how small they really
  are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-W6OOfZuUnlM/TOXCD941S_I/AAAAAAAABDE/I7ZbXLwWgY4/s800/DSCF0347.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-W6OOfZuUnlM/TOXCD941S_I/AAAAAAAABDE/I7ZbXLwWgY4/s800/DSCF0347.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had heard that they will come up to you and lick or chew your pack
  in order to get the salt from your sweat, but that didn&#39;t happen to
  me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Just before I got to the Grayson Highlands, I met up with another
  group of hikers: Skittles, Flora, Abear, and Coyote.  I had been
  following most of them in the shelter logs for months, so it was
  like meeting old friends.  Flora in particular signed her name with
  a large flower (her hiking partner Fauna had left near Washington,
  DC), so her entries were hard to miss.  We hiked together off and on
  for a few days, and it was nice to be hiking with people once again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We all stopped together in Damascus, VA and found cheap
  accommodation in a building run by a local church.  It was empty,
  but it had strict rules (no cooking in the rooms was the one they
  seemed most concerned with) and a person came during the night to
  make sure that we were following them.  I found a new pair of shoes
  on sale in Damascus, so I got them and got rid of my previous pair
  which were falling apart.  They had only lasted about 500 miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I left Damascus early the next day, leaving the group behind.
  Skittles would catch up with me and we would hike together a bit
  longer, but I didn&#39;t see the rest again.  Just past Damascus, I left
  Virginia for Tennessee.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hwZeFpMUAJk/TOXCIxbQ-3I/AAAAAAAABEI/DC0DPcb6umI/s800/DSCF0353.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hwZeFpMUAJk/TOXCIxbQ-3I/AAAAAAAABEI/DC0DPcb6umI/s800/DSCF0353.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Tennessee and North Carolina.  A run of four straight hostels, and
  the weather finally turning cold.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/central-va/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/central-va/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>4-State and Northern Virginia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/north-va/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/north-va/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-29T03:08:36Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-29T03:08:36Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;4-State Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The challenges long-distance hikers create for themselves are
  essentially stupid.  You generally don&#39;t get anything for completing
  them, and they have a tendency to make you feel bad.  For example,
  on the PCT, there is a challenge that involves hiking from a town to
  a hostel while drinking a beer every mile.  Since the distance
  between the places is 24 miles, it seems remarkably foolhardy to
  me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  With that out of the way, let me tell you about the challenge that I
  did.  It involves hiking in 4 states in under 24 hours.  I started
  in Pennsylvania, hiked most of the day in Maryland, went through
  Harpers Ferry in West Virginia, and ended the day in Virginia.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I started the day just after midnight, and wished Picker and Grinner
  a silent &quot;good luck&quot;.  Even though there was a nearly-full moon, the
  night was pretty dark, and I needed my head lamp all night.  Shortly
  into Maryland, I tweaked my ankle pretty badly, and so I was slowed
  a bit for the rest of the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By 4 in the morning, I had not gone very far, and I decided to take
  a nap.  I found a reasonably flat rock and laid down right beside
  the trail.  I slept until about 6, by which time the sun was coming
  up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had gone around 20 miles by lunch time, so I took it at the
  Washington Monument:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-VDW_BuMm5kI/TOXBGjbmAHI/AAAAAAAAAzY/V_Ga-ezEt4Q/s800/DSCF0238.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-VDW_BuMm5kI/TOXBGjbmAHI/AAAAAAAAAzY/V_Ga-ezEt4Q/s800/DSCF0238.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  This is clearly not the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_monument&quot;&gt;Washington Monument&lt;/a&gt; that is in Washington,
  DC, but it was the first one, and that should count for something.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The trail in Maryland was pretty good, and there was a lot of
  history associated with the places that I was hiking.  In some
  sense, it is a shame that I went through so quickly.  In particular,
  the last shelter in Maryland was one of the nicest that I saw.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was about 6 or 7 by the time I left Maryland, and the sun was
  starting to set.  I entered &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harper%27s_Ferry&quot;&gt;Harpers Ferry&lt;/a&gt; and started to look for a
  place to get some food.  It took me a while to get my bearings, and
  by the time I found a street with bars and restaurants, they were
  all closed.  It seems that Harpers Ferry is completely a
  tourist town, and no restaurants are open after about 8:00.
  Finally, I found a restaurant with open doors and went in, despite a
  sign saying that the restaurant was closed.  I practically begged
  the waitress to get me some food, and in the end I overpaid quite a
  lot for a mediocre sandwich.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I went to the headquarters of the Appalachian Trail Conservancy,
  which was also closed, and looked around, trying to find a hose.
  Someone must have thought that I looked suspicious, because one of
  the workers eventually showed up and showed me where the hose was.
  I filled my water bottles, thanked the employee, and went on my
  way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It seems cruel, but the trail climbs a hill for about two miles from
  Harpers Ferry to the Virginia border.  I had walked 43 miles by the
  time I made it to the border, and I was completely beat.  I hung my
  hammock just past the border sign and settled into bed at about
  10:30 PM.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I awoke the next morning later than usual, and hung most of my gear
  in a tree.  I wanted to go back to Harpers Ferry, since it is
  customary for thru-hikers to visit the ATC and have their picture
  taken.  So I went back with a mostly-empty pack.  I had my picture
  taken and hung around until nearly noon.  During the time that I was
  there, some section-hikers also came in.  We talked for a while
  about the differences between the thru-hiking experience and the
  section-hiking experience, and they gave me some of their
  freeze-dried meals, which were of a much higher quality than the
  meals I generally ate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Harpers Ferry to Waynesboro, VA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually, I left the ATC.  I climbed the hill again, got the rest
  of my gear, and hiked about 7 miles further down the trail.  The
  next day I did 10 miles by lunch time and called it a day at a
  really nice hostel: the Bear&#39;s Den.  If you are ever in the
  Washington, DC area and would like a hostel experience, this is the
  place for you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I lounged and let my legs recuperate.  The Bear&#39;s Den has a nice
  deal where you can stay at the hostel, get a frozen pizza and a pint
  of Ben &amp;amp; Jerry&#39;s ice cream for pretty cheap.  Even though I had
  recently completed the half-gallon challenge, I was certainly ready
  for some Ben &amp;amp; Jerry&#39;s.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After the Bear&#39;s Den, there is a section of trail called &quot;The
  Roller Coaster&quot;.  This is primarily meant to scare northbounders who
  haven&#39;t seen any real mountains yet.  The terrain is a bit bumpy,
  but there was really nothing to worry about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The following day I stopped in at Front Royal, VA for a resupply.  I
  had to wait a very long time for a hitch (the famed Southern
  hospitality had apparently not yet kicked in).  I noticed that my
  pocket knife was missing, so I called the Bear&#39;s Den, and they had
  found it.  They very generously sent it on to me at a town that was
  down the trail.  I left Front Royal, and camped just a couple of
  miles before boundary of Shenandoah National Park.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  My experience in &quot;The Shennies&quot; was not great.  It rained nearly the
  whole time that I was there, and there is a road that the trail
  crosses something like 20 times in the park.  By the last day, I had
  determined that the rain jacket that I had was not really
  waterproof, and when it got really wet it just made me colder.  I
  had rain pants, but they were not breathable at all, so my legs
  would get nearly as wet from sweat as they would from rain.  On the
  last day, I procrastinated in the shelter as long as I could (I
  finished the book I was reading), and then went back out into the
  rain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I walked 20 miles that day without stopping on trails that were more
  like creeks.  I left Shenandoah and was very glad to do so.  Just
  past the boundary is another road, and I somewhat forced myself on a
  motorist to take me into Waynesboro, VA.  When I got to Waynesboro,
  the sun was coming out, and I was able to camp in town rather than
  paying for a hotel.  I took a shower at the YMCA, had a meal in a
  restaurant, and finally felt better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Central Virginia.  If I&#39;m feeling ambitious, also Southern
  Virginia.  Once I get there, the trail&#39;s almost done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/north-va/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/north-va/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Pennsylvania</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/pa/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/pa/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-28T02:08:50Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-28T01:58:19Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my last entry, Pennsylvania is many hikers&#39;
least-favorite state on the trail.  This comes down to one thing:
rocks.  All the states have some rocks, but in Pennsylvania, they are
relentless.  They tend to be small, firmly stuck into the earth, and
just the right shape for turning your ankle or at least moving your
foot in your shoe.  Since we were regularly doing 20-mile days by this
point in the trail, we saw a lot of rocks every day.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Delaware Water Gap to Palmerton&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Delaware Water Gap is named because it is a gap in the ridge caused
  by the Delaware River.  It has a quaint little town, and we stopped
  in to get some pie and do a little shopping (I needed to replace my
  water bag, which had sprung a leak in New York).  We didn&#39;t stay in
  town for the night, though, and went to a shelter with a nice view
  from the ridge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, we walked along the flat ridge all the way to the next
  gap, called Wind Gap, where we hitched into town for the night.
  Watching CNN, we learned that there were forest fires in Colorado,
  right near where Just Jill lived.  Since only about 90 houses were
  burned down, I thought the probability of her being affected was
  pretty small, but I hoped that she wasn&#39;t nonetheless.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Wind Gap was one of the least hiker-friendly towns that we stayed
  in.  As a hiker, you pretty much have to walk everywhere, so it is
  good if the town is very small and compact.  Wind Gap was not
  compact, and it also had no sidewalks.  When we went to get
  groceries, we had to cross a very large road, and people were
  honking their horns at us as if the lack of proper signals in the
  town was our fault.  All in all, it wasn&#39;t a great town, and I
  wouldn&#39;t recommend that other hikers stay there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We climbed up from the gap the next day and found Just Jill in a
  clearing at the top, putting away her tent.  Her house had indeed
  burned down in the fires.  Unfortunately, that meant the end of the
  trail for her.  Most importantly, her boyfriend and dog were okay,
  and she was flying out to Colorado to meet them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There was really nothing that we could do, so we kept on walking.
  Near the end of the day, we came to one of the most environmentally
  degraded areas of the trail: the Palmerton &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superfund&quot;&gt;Superfund&lt;/a&gt; site.  After
  months of mostly walking in forests, this was a completely bare
  ridge devoid of all trees.  The lack of trees was apparently a
  result of the zinc-smelting industry in the town poisoning the soil
  with its emissions.  It didn&#39;t bother me too much, but Picker
  especially thought it was creepy, and so we hustled through the
  deforested area.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, before we could make it completely past the deforestation,
  we needed to descend into Lehigh Gap.  This was one of the hardest
  descents we had since the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1&quot;&gt;White Mountains&lt;/a&gt;.  I was glad to get to the
  bottom of the descent, but it just meant that we had to up to the
  next ridge.  We saw two snakes at the shelter that we stayed at that
  night &amp;ndash; mice are attracted by the crumbs hikers leave behind and
  snakes are attracted by the mice &amp;ndash; so it was a bit hard to get to
  sleep, and I checked my shoes pretty carefully when I got out of my
  hammock the next night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Palmerton to Duncannon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The hiking in this section was honestly not that interesting.  The
  ridges were flat and rocky, and we simply tried to pass the time and
  make miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After Wind Gap, we stayed in Port Clinton, where we went to the
  world&#39;s largest &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cabelas.com/&quot;&gt;Cabela&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;.  They actually picked us up and drove us
  to the store.  It is supposed to be an outdoors store, but it is
  more of a hunting and fishing store, so we didn&#39;t find too much to
  interest us.  However, they did have an all-you-can-eat buffet, so
  we gorged ourselves a bit.  The next day was the first day of the
  NCAA football season, and Picker was a die-hard University of Miami
  fan, so we needed to get to town and find a hotel with ESPN.  The
  only town that we thought we could get to was Shartlesville, which
  is marked in the guide book, but which is only accessible from the
  trail via a dirt road.  Since there was no possibility of a hitch
  (and the football game was so crucial to see), we walked the nearly
  4 miles to town.  It turned out to be little more than a rest-stop
  on the interstate, but we found a hotel with cable and checked in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Miami lost, and the next day it was lightly raining.  So we decided
  to take a zero (my first since Vermont) and stay in the hotel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked back to the trail the next day (walking off-trail is never
  fun for me) and continued on.  I really don&#39;t remember much of the
  next few days.  I can guarantee you that there were rocks.
  Eventually, we crossed the Susquehanna River and walked into
  Duncannon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Duncannon is one of the most popular towns on the trail.  It has a
  cheap hole-in-the-wall hotel with decent food and good beer where
  all hikers stay.  I met up with my uncle there and we had a very
  nice supper.  The next day was drizzling again, and again we decided
  that we would rather not walk in the rain, so we took another zero.
  Since my uncle had paid for our rooms the previous night
  (unbeknownst to me), we felt that we would not be breaking the bank
  by doing this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, the next day, we felt that we had some miles to make up.
  We had planned to make it to Boiling Springs in two days from
  Duncannon, but we did it in one day instead.  Grinner wasn&#39;t too
  happy about going 26 miles, but the terrain was pretty flat and we
  crossed a road every mile or two, so it was pretty easy to keep
  track of how far we needed to go.  Plus, we had mostly gotten rid of
  the rocks that had been plaguing us, so we could walk a bit faster.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Midpoint to Border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Late the next day, we hit Pine Grove Furnace State Park.  It&#39;s a
  really nice State Park, but it has the feature of having the nearest
  convenience store to the midpoint of the trail.  There&#39;s a tradition
  known as the Half-Gallon Challenge that occurs there.  Since you&#39;ve
  come halfway, you must eat a half-gallon of ice cream in under an
  hour.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-6YpYvoAaNIg/TOXBEOMWPII/AAAAAAAAAy0/EvknY6GNZBY/s800/DSCF0231.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-6YpYvoAaNIg/TOXBEOMWPII/AAAAAAAAAy0/EvknY6GNZBY/s800/DSCF0231.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As you can see, I left a little bit in my beard, but I finished it
  with plenty of time to spare.  Picker finished his half-gallon a bit
  faster than me, but Grinner didn&#39;t quite make it &amp;ndash; she left about
  three bites.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  None of us felt wonderful after consuming that much ice cream, so we
  didn&#39;t go much farther that night.  The next morning, however, we
  hit the midpoint of the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-GVEBEnvJk30/TOXBEuKmZUI/AAAAAAAAAy8/v4wWFXvj6mU/s800/DSCF0232.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-GVEBEnvJk30/TOXBEuKmZUI/AAAAAAAAAy8/v4wWFXvj6mU/s800/DSCF0232.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Around this time, the oak trees were shedding their acorns, so as we
  walked, we would hear the acorns hitting the ground.  Occasionally
  someone would get hit by one.  They were pretty big acorns, so they
  would hurt and leave a bruise.  At our campsite for that night,
  there was a large group of birds in the trees above us.  They shook
  the branches even more than usual, so we had a veritable hailstorm
  of acorns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We went into Waynesboro, PA the next day and I bought new shoes (my
  previous pair lasting nearly 800 miles).  We also had a Chinese
  buffet.  Somewhere in the previous few days I had lost my trowel, so
  I went to a garden store and got a new one.  (I never used a trowel
  all that much because I usually stayed near a shelter and most
  shelters have privies, but it is important to have one for
  emergencies.)  We resupplied in town and walked on for a couple of
  miles to a campsite just before the border.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had a plan for a crazy amount of miles the next day, so it was to
  be my last day with Picker and Grinner.  We had walked with each
  other for nearly 1000 miles, so I was sorry to leave them.  I took a
  picture of our campsite, with them doing a fairly typical activity:
  playing rummy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vshGTrWxiFw/TOXBFTwUYII/AAAAAAAAAzE/L_Ia2O_1GAA/s800/DSCF0235.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vshGTrWxiFw/TOXBFTwUYII/AAAAAAAAAzE/L_Ia2O_1GAA/s800/DSCF0235.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The day with the crazy mileage, taking me into Virginia.  Since
  Virginia is the longest state on the trail (nearly a third of the
  miles), I&#39;m sure I won&#39;t be able to write the whole thing in one
  entry.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/pa/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/pa/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>New Jersey</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/nj/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/nj/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-13T20:00:15Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-13T18:46:16Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;New Jersey, or Joisey as the TV would have you say it, isn&#39;t really a
place that you think of when you think about hiking.  The stereotype
is one of chemical factories and Guidos on the Jersey Shore.  However,
it&#39;s called the Garden State for a reason.  There is a lot of beauty
in New Jersey, and I found it far away from the beach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On our first full day in New Jersey, we hiked 17 miles by lunch time.
It was a town day, so our packs were light and we were looking forward
to sleeping in a hostel.  The trail was also incredibly easy, with a
one-mile stretch of boardwalk at one point.  The last two miles were
also on a former railroad bed.  Since trains can only go up the most
gentle of hills, it is always nice to walk where they once were.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I was saying, we reached town by lunch time.  We had to go back
into New York to get to town, but it was worth it.  There was a small
pizzeria with great food (for once I could only eat half of a pizza),
and we made our way to the &quot;Mayor&#39;s House&quot; (aka the &quot;Outhouse&quot;).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Mayor (who wasn&#39;t really the mayor, but who had run at one point)
was a charming older guy with the gift of gab.  This is a guy who can
really talk.  One interesting feature of the house is that he had
requested that people mail him stones from every state of the trail,
and he had made a walkway from them in the back yard.  Since the trail
is government property for the most part, this had received the
attention of the authorities, who had sent the chief ranger to inspect
it.  One strange thing about this particular hostel is that one
requirement of hikers is that they must watch a motivational video in
order to stay there.  There was some eye-rolling about this at first,
but it was not a bad video.  It was about a Susan-Boyle-type singer on
the X Factor TV show, who had overcome looking plain to sing opera
well.  The message that the Mayor was trying to impart with the video
was encapsulated by the line that the singer sang: &quot;Vincero, Vincero,
Vincero&quot;, from Turandot.  (I will win, I will make it, I will finish
this hike.)  It sounds cheesy, but the story was nice, and it gave you
something to think about if you got down during the hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After a great breakfast, we headed out again.  We didn&#39;t go far, and
stopped at a shelter.  Every shelter in New Jersey has a bear box,
which is essentially a locker with a complicated handle that bears
can&#39;t figure out to store food in.  This is much more convenient than
hanging food from a tree branch, and it keeps the bears (which are all
over New Jersey) from getting too comfortable around shelters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day, we passed by the highest point in New Jersey, which has
its own monument:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-s8awWxSKIOU/TOXA4yklbTI/AAAAAAAAAw0/nnwa6hiwlcw/s800/DSCF0219.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-s8awWxSKIOU/TOXA4yklbTI/AAAAAAAAAw0/nnwa6hiwlcw/s800/DSCF0219.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Going down the hill from the high point, we saw our first bears of the
trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-X5MOSZiWs50/TOXA5hBqqLI/AAAAAAAAAw8/SUmfDKEbx-0/s800/DSCF0220.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-X5MOSZiWs50/TOXA5hBqqLI/AAAAAAAAAw8/SUmfDKEbx-0/s800/DSCF0220.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was a mother and her cub, but we were only close enough to get a
picture of the cub.  It seemed at first as if the cub was going to
climb a tree to get away from us, which would have been the worst
possible thing to happen.  In that case, the mother would have
defended the tree and we would have had to go far out of our way to
avoid them.  We were lucky, though, and the cub just kept going, as
did we.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day was less exciting, but we saw another bear the day after
that.  We were walking on a dirt road, and it was right ahead of us.
Grinner was so excited to see the bear that she started skipping down
the road.  Try skipping with twenty or thirty pounds of stuff in a
backpack, and you&#39;ll see that she must have been &lt;b&gt;really&lt;/b&gt; excited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We spent the night at the Mohican Outdoor Center.  We had to pay a
little bit to camp, but they had bear boxes, and considering the
amount of bears in the area, we thought they would be worth it.  It
turned out that it was good that the bear boxes were there, because a
bear apparently came into the camp and tried to get at food.  I&#39;m a
sound sleeper, which is why I can only say &quot;apparently&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day would be our last in the state.  We walked up onto a
ridge, from where I was able to take some nice sunrise pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3L8Q43a9C5o/TOXBBe0VxgI/AAAAAAAAAyQ/GSOewt5CxhM/s800/DSCF0228.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3L8Q43a9C5o/TOXBBe0VxgI/AAAAAAAAAyQ/GSOewt5CxhM/s800/DSCF0228.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After that, we went past the southernmost glacial lake on the trail,
named Sunfish Pond.  Finally, we began our descent into &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delaware_Water_Gap&quot;&gt;Delaware Water Gap&lt;/a&gt;, which marks the border between New Jersey and Pennsylvania.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Pennsylvania.  It&#39;s many hikers&#39; least-favorite state, but I had a
  nice time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/nj/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/nj/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>A bit of ikiwiki hackery</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/ikiwiki-hacking/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/ikiwiki-hacking/"/>






	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />


	<updated>2012-02-09T23:45:17Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-09T23:45:17Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Spurred on by the first comment by an actual user of my plugin today,
I tracked down one of the major bottlenecks for external ikiwiki
plugins.  My fix might not be the most elegant, but it works so far.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Ikiwiki plugins work by calling a function named &lt;code&gt;hook&lt;/code&gt; which lets
  them tell the ikiwiki compiler that they implement a certain
  subroutine.  Whenever that subroutine needs to be called, the
  ikiwiki compiler calls &lt;code&gt;run_hooks&lt;/code&gt;, and that runs all the registered
  functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  For most of these hooked functions (&lt;code&gt;htmlize&lt;/code&gt; is the only exception
  I can think of), all of the registered functions are called,
  regardless of file type.  This is normally not a problem, because
  the plugin can check the type of content that it is given and only
  operate on the types of content that it knows anything about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  For external plugins, however, there is a problem.  Ikiwiki
  communicates with external plugins via xml-rpc on &lt;code&gt;stdin&lt;/code&gt; and
  &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;.  Every function call that it makes involves writing the
  function&#39;s parameters on &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;.  When there is a file type that
  is unknown to the external plugin, all that effort (I/O is the main
  time sink I think, but the content must also be encoded correctly
  for xml-rpc) is wasted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I have added a parameter named &quot;exclusive&quot; to the optional arguments
  that are accepted by the &lt;code&gt;hook&lt;/code&gt; function.  When this argument exists
  (and is true), the registered function is only run when the type of
  file is the same as the type of file that the plugin accepts.  So
  far, it only works with the &lt;code&gt;scan&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;linkify&lt;/code&gt; hooks, which were
  the main areas that slowed my plugin down.  However, it is quite
  simple to get it to work with other hooks as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/ikiwiki-hacking/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/ikiwiki-hacking/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>New York State</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ny/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ny/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-04T01:54:36Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-04T01:50:44Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;New York State has the reputation of being one long jaunt from deli to
concession stand to food truck, but it seemed that by the time we were
there, they had all left.  What I remember most about hiking in New
York is that we were never very far from a road, and there are plenty
of motorcycles to remind you of the fact.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first two days in New York were largely flat and unmemorable.  We
did have one small problem when we wanted to get a resupply on our
second day.  Hitchhiking is illegal in New York, so we eventually had
to call a taxi to take us into a little town.  To leave town, we were
thinking about doing the same thing, until I noticed a pizza-delivery
car in the parking lot of the shopping centre that we were in.  I went
to the pizza place and ordered a delivery.  I would only buy the pizza
if they delivered it (and us) to the trail.  It was a double-score: a
great lunch, and a free ride back to the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the third day, we crossed the Bear Mountain Bridge over the Hudson
River.  At that point, the Hudson is nearly at sea level, so we were
nearly to the lowest point on the trail.  The bridge is a few hundred
feet above the river and has many signs urging people not to jump.
Naturally, these signs make me think of jumping, so I scooted across
the bridge as quickly as I could.  It&#39;s a bit strange to be a hiker
that&#39;s afraid of heights, but it&#39;s an issue that really doesn&#39;t come
up too much.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the bridge, we entered a zoo.  It&#39;s not a great zoo, but the
trail goes through it, so in we went.  I&#39;m not a big fan of zoos
anyway, and when the lowest point on the trail was right next to the
bear enclosure, it seemed apt.  Past the zoo, we entered &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bear_Mountain_State_Park&quot;&gt;Bear Mountain State Park&lt;/a&gt;.  It was awful too.  Full of people, nearly all paved over,
with rangers in golf carts.  We stopped at a concession stand and got
an overpriced soda.  The trail up the mountain had fewer people, but
just as much trash.  We even saw a pair of men&#39;s underwear right next
to the trail.  The higher we went, however, the more sparse the trash
became, and when we reached the summit, the trail had become mostly
clean once again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other side of the summit, we saw a couple of deer.  They
skittered away, but then we saw them five minutes later.  And five
minutes after that.  They were clearly habituated to humans, and
seemed to be playing coy with us.  We hiked over one more small
mountain but by the time we were going up Black Mountain, both Picker
and I were having heat-related chafing issues.  We stopped at the top
of Black Mountain and took some pictures of the sun reflecting off the
New York City skyline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-tmsoXjXxiv0/TOXA0yMh11I/AAAAAAAAAvs/HlPqqSVUyCk/s800/DSCF0210.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-tmsoXjXxiv0/TOXA0yMh11I/AAAAAAAAAvs/HlPqqSVUyCk/s800/DSCF0210.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sunset was pretty too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-etjpnUs9h58/TOXA1-vH4sI/AAAAAAAAAv0/CNg06w_N8IU/s800/DSCF0211.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-etjpnUs9h58/TOXA1-vH4sI/AAAAAAAAAv0/CNg06w_N8IU/s800/DSCF0211.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day was hot as well.  We went down to a lake with showers and
vending machines, but everything was locked up.  Nearing the end of
the day, we hit a water cache that had a note inside from the people
who had left it.  The note said to give them a call and they would
come and pick us up.  It turned out that they were busy when we
called, but we didn&#39;t have much to do, so we just hung out and waited
for them.  When they did come and pick us up, they were so nice.  They
practically forced us to eat with them and we slept in extremely
comfortable beds after a luxurious shower.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some sense, we had been lucky to get to the cache when we did,
because Just Jill and Day Tripper were right behind us and would have
taken the hospitality if we didn&#39;t beat them to it.  I&#39;ve introduced
Just Jill before, but Day Tripper is new.  My main memory of her is of
her mobile phone.  It was always on and she was always doing something
with it.  She was a bit behind a larger group of people and was
keeping in close contact with them.  The morning after our stay with
the people who had left the cache, we thought that she and Just Jill
must be ahead of us, because they would not need a ride to get to the
trail.  However, we soon heard Day Tripper talking on her phone as
she was walking up the mountain, right behind us.  It was a bit
strange for me, but she was a nice person, so I tried to not let it
get in the way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, the rest of the day was pretty flat, so the five us could
walk at a good pace and chat a bit.  We hit a hot-dog stand at lunch
time (not so great for a vegetarian: when I asked if he had veggie
dogs, he laughed at me), and before long, we crossed into New Jersey.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-k02LG0nkYp0/TOXA4n6sBGI/AAAAAAAAAws/pzQ5UqRdUYw/s800/DSCF0218.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-k02LG0nkYp0/TOXA4n6sBGI/AAAAAAAAAws/pzQ5UqRdUYw/s800/DSCF0218.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It might sound like we were going out of the frying pan and into the
  fire, but the trail in New Jersey is actually really beautiful.  It
  also has the highest concentration of bears of any state on the
  trail.  Foreshadowing!
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ny/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ny/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
