<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Hiking and Coding</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20120202">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-09-22T07:55:48Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Sierras and a little Oregon</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/sierras-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/sierras-01/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-09-22T07:55:48Z</updated>
	<published>2012-09-22T07:52:39Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I just got back from a few days in the mountains hiking with my mom
and sister, so I thought I would write a bit more of my rememberances
from last year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leaving Kennedy Meadows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After a couple of nights in Kennedy Meadows, I was ready to get back
  on the trail.  There was a group leaving a couple hours before I
  would be ready, so I checked and made sure that they would be okay
  with me tagging along.  I really didn&#39;t want to do the mountains
  alone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Before long, I left and hiked five or ten miles before I caught the
  group.  The group consisted of Buffalo, Pyrite, Chinchilla,
  Zombiefeet, Ryan, and Sue.  The first day, we didn&#39;t see any snow,
  but that would not last long.  Our packs were much heavier than
  usual, since we had bear canisters to keep our food safe, and ice
  axes to keep our bodies safe.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We made our way into the mountains.  The group was larger than I was
  used to, and so we hiked a bit slower than I normally did.  Getting
  consensus that we would start hiking againg after breaks was
  difficult.  I started to get antsy.  There were some upsides to the
  size of the group, though.  Pyrite knew how to use an ice axe and
  gave us all a quick lesson.  When we hit snow on the second day, we
  were able to find our way relatively quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  On the second day, our group got even bigger, as we were joined by
  the French Team, a husband and wife duo from &amp;ndash; you guessed it --
  France.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Snow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  My attitude toward snow upon leaving Kennedy Meadows was that I
  didn&#39;t think it would be much of a problem.  After all, as a
  Canadian, I walk on snow 4 or 5 months of the year.  I hadn&#39;t
  anticipated two things.  First, it is nearly impossible to find the
  trail when everything around is covered by snow, and second, a high
  amount of snow means a high amount of snowmelt.  The second
  consideration would come later, but by our third day in the Sierra,
  we were very glad that the French Team had a GPS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-L3fdCCRHUpY/TnvM2zbe8DI/AAAAAAAACe4/QhzidwV4CkY/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-L3fdCCRHUpY/TnvM2zbe8DI/AAAAAAAACe4/QhzidwV4CkY/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Early on the fourth day, we came to Chicken Spring Lake.  The maps
  list it as a water source.  This is what it looked like to us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-fklZyjFIKu0/TnvN_4Io-KI/AAAAAAAACfM/qrVE1Ax_Ppo/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-fklZyjFIKu0/TnvN_4Io-KI/AAAAAAAACfM/qrVE1Ax_Ppo/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We started to learn how to &quot;boot-ski&quot;.  On slopes that are steep
  enough, you can let your shoes slip and then you start sliding down
  the slope.  As long as the slope isn&#39;t too steep, you can go for
  quite a while and have a lot of fun.  It also broke up the hiking a
  little bit, which was becoming a bit of a trudge.  The snow was
  packed quite firm, but even the firmest snow is harder to walk on
  than dirt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the end of our fifth day, we got to Crabtree Meadows.  I had been
  hoping to climb Mount Whitney (the highest mountain in the contintal
  US), and to do so we would need to take a side-trail.  However, I
  had to balance that with my need to stay with a group.  I was quite
  liking the group that I was with, and one by one, they decided not
  to attempt the climb.  It was a hard decision, but I gave up on the
  idea of climbing Whitney as part of my PCT hike.  With the benefit
  of hindsight, I am pretty sure that it was the right decision.  The
  miles ahead were among the hardest I had ever hiked and I was nearly
  out of food.  If I had needed to hurry, things could have gone
  terribly wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-zR62ys-lIO4/TnvViJKFRAI/AAAAAAAAChE/wrVruqk3YPw/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-zR62ys-lIO4/TnvViJKFRAI/AAAAAAAAChE/wrVruqk3YPw/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-hE5MMyNeKgY/TnvUwKAWtoI/AAAAAAAACg8/8aPSHGeP910/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-hE5MMyNeKgY/TnvUwKAWtoI/AAAAAAAACg8/8aPSHGeP910/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Passes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was all about getting close to Forester Pass.  The
  consensus from hikers who had done the trail in previous years was
  that it was best to do the passes in the morning, before the snow
  got slushy.  So we wanted to get close to the pass (the highest
  point on the trail) in order to do that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The hiking was starting to get spectacular.  Everything was covered
  in snow and there were giant mountains all around.  We only made it
  about 8 miles that day, but they were 8 hard-fought miles.  Our
  large group found the last cluster of trees with snowless patches to
  camp in, and we ate a slightly early supper and turned in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The weather was great the next morning, and we started out with
  great moods.  This picture of Pyrite and Chinchilla walking toward
  Forester Pass is one of my favorites:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WncLk1Hvm0w/TnvalcifPSI/AAAAAAAACiY/vyyjVcOBK78/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WncLk1Hvm0w/TnvalcifPSI/AAAAAAAACiY/vyyjVcOBK78/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we got to the real climb before the pass.  Unfortunately,
  I don&#39;t have any pictures that do it justice.  It started off with a
  few hundred feet of what seemed like climbing straight up.  There
  were steps in the snow that someone had made the day before, so I
  used those.  I also had my ice axe out just in case I slipped or the
  snow gave way.  At the top of the steps were some rocks.  This was
  the actual trail, with switchbacks.  The rocks were icy because the
  snow had melted the day before and frozen during the night.  It was
  not fun climbing up them, but once I was up I was glad to be on the
  switchbacks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The gladness didn&#39;t last very long.  The switchbacks abruptly ended,
  crossed by a chute of icy snow.  It was even more vertical than the
  steps we had just climbed, and as a bonus there were jagged rocks at
  the bottom.  Any slip would give you almost no chance of saving
  yourself.  To top it off, the snow was so hard and icy that the ice
  axe wouldn&#39;t go in.  There were steps carved across the chute, but
  they seemed to have been carved by a giant.  To say that I was
  scared when I was crossing them would be a massive understatement.
  It&#39;s not something that I want to do again.  (It would have been
  much less scary if we had crossed in the afternoon when the snow was
  slushy, but that&#39;s something we didn&#39;t know at the time.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Once I crossed the chute of death, it was just a few more
  switchbacks on terra firma before I got to the top.  I had to sit
  down and hold my knees to get rid of the adrenaline that was
  flowing.  The rest of the group caught up about five minutes later,
  and we celebrated being at the highest point of the hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-mgfmDk7YQBQ/TnvcIuSwzeI/AAAAAAAACi8/QSmfhYen7hM/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-mgfmDk7YQBQ/TnvcIuSwzeI/AAAAAAAACi8/QSmfhYen7hM/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-F44I2j86_rM/TnvdqJ33EuI/AAAAAAAACjU/TLloMjX0BNQ/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-F44I2j86_rM/TnvdqJ33EuI/AAAAAAAACjU/TLloMjX0BNQ/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We started our descent from the pass and very soon got to do our
  first glissading.  Glissading is a fancy word for sitting on your
  bum and sliding.  It&#39;s a ton of fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-XAlZSZ7ihOI/TnveTYNPvQI/AAAAAAAADYE/EsdF9RxtzB0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-XAlZSZ7ihOI/TnveTYNPvQI/AAAAAAAADYE/EsdF9RxtzB0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We descended more than 3000 feet and then started climbing again.
  Our next day would take us into town, so we wanted to get as close
  as possible.  We camped near Bullfrog Lake, and because campsites
  were so scarce, I camped quite a distance from the rest of the
  group.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I awoke the next morning having decided that I was sick of the
  snow.  It was causing us to hike too slowly and get too tired.  I
  just wanted out.  I started hiking without the group and got a
  little off trail.  I did, however, get a picture of this fellow, who
  I think is a pine marten.  He was quite curious about me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-XKMvPHGFmbo/TnviJ59CFdI/AAAAAAAACkg/fc8nVttcjT0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-XKMvPHGFmbo/TnviJ59CFdI/AAAAAAAACkg/fc8nVttcjT0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I ended up a good distance above the trail and eventually saw the
  rest of the group pass below me.  It was somewhat embarassing to
  climb down and catch up with them, but I was still glad to see
  them.  We got to Kearsarge Pass without much incident, but the snow
  seemed treacherous again on the other side.  We had to descend a
  long way from the pass to get to the road, and it was after noon by
  the time we got there.  Eventually, we got a ride into the small
  town of Independence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Off to Oregon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  As I said, I had decided to get out of the snow.  My strategy was to
  get to Oregon, where my mom and sister would be vacationing and then
  have them drive me back to Independence after a couple of weeks.  I
  was joined on this road trip by Zombiefeet and Ryan, who had planned
  to end their hike at Independence and who needed to get to
  Washington for a wedding.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  Getting to Oregon was a bit difficult logistically.  The first thing
  we did was hitch up to Mammoth Lakes.  It wasn&#39;t an easy hitch, but
  eventually a BMW &lt;img src=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./smileys/idea.png&quot; alt=&quot;(!)&quot; /&gt; driven by a single lady &lt;img src=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./smileys/idea.png&quot; alt=&quot;(!)&quot; /&gt; pulled over and
  gave all three of us &lt;img src=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./smileys/idea.png&quot; alt=&quot;(!)&quot; /&gt; a ride.  It even turned out that we had
  grown up in the same city, so we had something to talk about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  From Mammoth, we were able to rent a car.  It&#39;s kind of strange
  driving after a month and a half of walking, but nevertheless I
  drove most of the way to Ashland, Oregon.  I said my goodbyes to
  Zombiefeet and Ryan, handed them the keys, and was on my own again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Oregon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Out of Ashland, I was happy to be on snow-free trail once more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OQzyBH7e-ck/TnvizEGvdhI/AAAAAAAACkw/d0t9-35bohU/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OQzyBH7e-ck/TnvizEGvdhI/AAAAAAAACkw/d0t9-35bohU/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was cursing my luck the same day when I came to a large patch of
  snow.  It was easily crossed, though, and then the path was bare for
  a while longer.  The next day had a climb, and the higher I went,
  the snowier it got.  When I finally got to the top, it was as snowy
  as it had been in California.  I was on my own without a GPS and I
  got lost.  By this time, I was pretty used to the sensation of being
  lost, and knew that as long as I went down the mountain in the
  correct general direction I would be fine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  And that was the case.  I slept on it, and found some snowmobile
  paths the next day.  I followed them to a larger road and came out
  nearly on the trail.  Later that day, I would come to so-called lava
  fields.  Obviously, this isn&#39;t the molten rock of the movies, but
  it&#39;s the rocks that formed after cooling off.  It&#39;s not too much fun
  to walk on because the rocks are awkwardly sized and shift
  constantly under your feet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r4xPytZ06xE/TnvmsNHmDCI/AAAAAAAACl0/7SjtldjLeZw/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r4xPytZ06xE/TnvmsNHmDCI/AAAAAAAACl0/7SjtldjLeZw/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As you can see from that picture, I was coming to another mountain
  with plenty of snow.  Since the whole point of coming to Oregon was
  to get out of the snow, I didn&#39;t feel like going into it.  I called
  off my plan to keep hiking in Oregon and took a week off at my
  grandparents&#39; house with my mom and sister.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  We drive back to Independence and I start hiking again.  The rivers
  become harder to cross and I get lost some more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/sierras-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/sierras-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>The End of Southern California</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-06/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-06/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-07-09T00:22:07Z</updated>
	<published>2012-07-09T00:22:07Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Tehachapi to Walker Pass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  We left Tehachapi fairly late in the morning and both Garby and I
  were tired, so we walked fairly slowly.  It was already pretty late
  by the time we got to the start of Section F.  Section F starts with
  a long climb, and I for one was really glad to get to the top.  Once
  we were at the top, the wind mostly stopped, which was another
  relief.  However, it was easy to see from the trees that the wind
  blew at the top too:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-GOpGag5worM/TnvDoAdKWpI/AAAAAAAACcQ/pHQm8vaQ-8Q/s144/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-GOpGag5worM/TnvDoAdKWpI/AAAAAAAACcQ/pHQm8vaQ-8Q/s144/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We didn&#39;t go much farther that day.  We found a saddle out of the
  wind and set up camp.  There was a freak snowstorm the next
  morning.  It created an interesting juxtaposition: snow and cacti:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/--k6BlHg_nyo/TnvD3WY0ISI/AAAAAAAACcU/3Nn-7Unb5S8/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/--k6BlHg_nyo/TnvD3WY0ISI/AAAAAAAACcU/3Nn-7Unb5S8/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The snow only lasted long enough to make things cold and wet.  Soon
  enough, the heat was back.  Unfortunately, I am somewhat blanking on
  the exact places that I camped during this time.  I seem to be
  missing a day.  Judging from the dates on my pictures, the snow day
  was May 29.  I forget where I camped that night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day must have been more interesting though.  The bulk of it
  was spent on a rather tedious trudge across a desert-y landscape,
  but toward the end of the day we had gained some elevation and found
  ourselves amongst the Joshua Trees.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-cdMF-02UuiM/TnvE9PZjg5I/AAAAAAAACcs/-SvpqRsgc5c/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-cdMF-02UuiM/TnvE9PZjg5I/AAAAAAAACcs/-SvpqRsgc5c/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I sat and ate supper in the shade of a couple at around 4:00 and
  then hiked in the dusk, when it got a little cooler.  When I got to
  my destination (Bird Spring Pass), there was a cache of cool water,
  but only Joshua Trees on which to hang my hammock.  It felt a little
  wrong to do so, but it was actually a decent base.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was one of my favorite kinds.  It began with a nice
  long climb, it was followed by a long mostly-flat section mostly in
  the woods, and ended with a descent.  At the end of the descent was
  Walker Pass, which has a campground and had trail magic that day.  I
  got some pizza and drinks and waited for Garby, who I had hiked past
  the previous day.  When he caught up, I asked whether he wanted to
  climb the next hill that evening or just stay at the campground.  I
  must admit that I was happy that he chose the latter.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Walker Pass to Kennedy Meadows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The following day also began with a climb, but was supposed to end
  with a climb as well.  Garby and I ate a longish lunch at a stream
  near the base of the climb and we discussed where we would camp.
  After lunch, I let him go ahead of me as I normally do, but when I
  got to the place that I thought would be the campsite, I saw neither
  hide nor hair of him.  Thinking that I had perhaps misread the map,
  I kept going.  After an hour, I was sure that I had gone too far,
  but there was no turning back at that point.  I found a thicket of
  brushy trees and hung my hammock for the night, hoping that Garby
  wouldn&#39;t think that I had ditched him.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The mountains were pulling me in the next day.  All my pictures from
  the day are terrible because they are of the mountains in the
  distance.  (Except maybe this one, which is terrible only because
  the snake is so unimpressive:)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-hvn7qZuSeXQ/TnvHKZRTViI/AAAAAAAADnY/Hsn80JIVTrE/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-hvn7qZuSeXQ/TnvHKZRTViI/AAAAAAAADnY/Hsn80JIVTrE/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a decent day of hiking.  There was a burned area, which
  wasn&#39;t so nice, but I also saw a huge golden eagle, and then walked
  along the Kern river for a while, both of which were very nice.  I
  made it to Kennedy Meadows &amp;ndash; mile 700 &amp;ndash; by late afternoon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Kennedy Meadows is the last stop for hikers before the big
  mountains: The Sierra Nevada.  I had known when I started my journey
  that I would be getting there somewhat early, considering that 2011
  had been one of the highest snow years on record.  I knew that I
  should take a few days and try to wait for it to melt.  I ended up
  taking one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Garby, Lovebird, and Raven all showed up on my zero-day.  Garby was
  worryingly late &amp;ndash; he had gotten sick again and was not able to keep
  food down very well.  In the end, he took a couple of weeks off from
  the trail and came back feeling better and made quite a name for
  himself in the Sierras.  Kennedy Meadows was the last place that I
  saw him on the trail.  It turned out that we passed somewhat close
  to each other a couple more times, but I found out later that he got
  off the trail near the California/Oregon border with foot problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The highlight of my zero-day was going to an alpaca farm with the
  rest of the gang.  I purchased an alpaca hat there that I wore for
  the rest of the trail (including some really cold nights in the
  mountains, where I was extremely glad to have it).  We hung out the
  rest of the day and even watched the movie Old School projected onto
  a big screen outdoors after it got dark.  It was a great day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Into the mountains, and more snow than I thought possible.  Hiking
  with a large group.  Defying death to get to the trail&#39;s highest
  point.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-06/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-06/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section E</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-05/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-05/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-07-04T22:17:21Z</updated>
	<published>2012-07-04T22:17:21Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;After my zero at Hiker Heaven, I started on my way into the fifth
section of the trail, which is notable for containing about twenty
miles of actual desert.  Before this, everything that had seemed like
a desert was actually chaparral.  The map, usually shaded with green
and brown, was completely white.  But I am getting ahead of myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Agua Dulce to the edge of the Mojave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It is customary for PCT hikers to leave Hiker Heaven and then hike
  directly to the Anderson&#39;s, which is about 23 miles away.  Having
  just spent a very nice zero day at Hiker Heaven, I didn&#39;t feel any
  need to do that.  I was walking by myself and feeling good.  I had
  let Garby leave a little earlier than me, and knowing his speed, I
  was fairly confident that he would be ahead of me all day.  Some
  days you just want to walk alone.  I reached the road to the
  Anderson&#39;s in the early afternoon and decided to keep going.  Just
  past the road, I found a dead horny toad and took a picture of it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8X3kmfL8y8E/Tnu9q5-AZKI/AAAAAAAACac/LeTdqQGpbpc/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8X3kmfL8y8E/Tnu9q5-AZKI/AAAAAAAACac/LeTdqQGpbpc/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I walked five or six more miles that evening before finding a nice
  grove of trees with a small clearing inside for my hammock.  There
  was even a nice little stream nearby.  I did not catch up to Garby
  and was not sure if I would catch him again on the hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was up early the next morning and walked about 100 yards when I
  came upon Garby packing up his campsite.  To me, it was a pretty
  good indication that we were really good hiking partners.  After
  nearly thirty miles of hiking, we had independently decided to call
  it a day within a distance that could be sprinted in 10 seconds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We passed the 500-mile marker that afternoon (though it was quite a
  distance past where the maps indicated that it should be).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-vo6fdjs5_uY/Tnu_b6GGilI/AAAAAAAACbA/ffFV4E3X-s4/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-vo6fdjs5_uY/Tnu_b6GGilI/AAAAAAAACbA/ffFV4E3X-s4/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The trail also became more wooded and shaded, which was nice because
  the weather was pretty hot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r_5XUEmDZ3A/Tnu_sF5KHvI/AAAAAAAACbE/dUUMgHrHCsM/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r_5XUEmDZ3A/Tnu_sF5KHvI/AAAAAAAACbE/dUUMgHrHCsM/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  And some of the trees had absolutely huge pine cones.  They were
  heavy too.  I kicked one, thinking that it would have the same
  papery weight that I am used to pine cones having, and nearly hurt
  my foot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually, though, we descended from the forested ridge toward the
  desert.  A few miles before the desert actually starts, there is
  some private property with no camping allowed.  Garby and I decided
  to camp as close to that property line as possible and to get an
  early start the next morning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The Mojave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  As we agreed, Garby and I got up at 3:30 in the morning and started
  walking toward the desert.  The moon was just past full, but it was
  not quite bright enough that we did not need our headlamps.  I had
  night-hiked &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/north-va&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and did not really like it.  This time was a
  little better, but I still stumbled more than I would have liked.
  However, I knew that this was the best way to beat the heat of the
  desert.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We got to the LA aqueduct just after daybreak.  We filled our water
  containers to their capacity there and then started walking in a
  straight line.  The trail follows the aqueduct (which is mostly
  buried after your first encounter with it) across most of the
  desert.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-o4F_F2AaOxY/TnvAnfsDv8I/AAAAAAAACbY/0pQAPGDwATs/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-o4F_F2AaOxY/TnvAnfsDv8I/AAAAAAAACbY/0pQAPGDwATs/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It has a round top, which is slightly annoying to walk on, but it is
  better than sand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It&#39;s fairly hard to describe walking in the desert and make it seem
  exciting.  Nothing happens suddenly, like it can in the mountains.
  It is all very gradual.  Eventually you notice that it&#39;s gotten
  really oppressively hot.  Your water gets hot.  You want to sit
  down, but there&#39;s no point, because there&#39;s no shade anywhere.  It&#39;d
  just be a waste of time.  So you keep walking.  Eventually we came
  to a bridge that was about 2 feet off the ground, and I sat for
  about ten minutes in the meager amount of shade that it offered.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Past the bridge, we walked on a road for a while.  We probably saw
  ten white trucks driving on the road, and no other vehicles.
  Clearly, this was a place where the only practical conveyance was a
  white truck.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was only noon by the time we reached our destination.  This was a
  small stream with a bridge over it, a spigot with cool water, and a
  small piece of corrugated tin on the other side of the bridge acting
  as a generator of shade.  We put down our mats and tried to get some
  sleep.  By this time, I was not feeling very well and did not eat
  much for supper that afternoon. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Tehachapi Wind Farm and Sickness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, we were up at 2:30 and repeated our night-hiking
  stunt from the morning before.  As we walked up the hill out of the
  desert, we hit an enormous head wind.  So we were walking up hill
  and into the wind &amp;ndash; not a pleasant experience.  On top of this, I
  was still not feeling well, so this part of the hike does not stick
  out as one of my favorite.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We got lost a couple of times in the dark.  The trail follows an
  ill-defined network of roads that aren&#39;t really roads, and it was
  quite easy to get on the wrong one.  Eventually we found a campsite
  (with people still sleeping in it), so we knew we were on the right
  path.  It was also hard not to feel a little smug, knowing that we
  had already walked about 10 miles and were passing people who were
  not yet awake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As we walked on, the wind was a near-constant annoyance.  However,
  we would see that it had a real use.  We walked straight into one of
  the largest wind farms in the world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZYF-QpSOFXo/TnvCMkzT_AI/AAAAAAAACb4/Ur-o8Mh4KzY/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZYF-QpSOFXo/TnvCMkzT_AI/AAAAAAAACb4/Ur-o8Mh4KzY/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By early afternoon, we had made it to a road, and I was beat.  It
  was not our destination, but the combination of not feeling well and
  the early rising of the previous days killed my energy.  Garby
  caught up with me, and together we decided to hitch into town.  We
  needed to go to the post office, and as soon as that business was
  taken care of, we got a hotel room and turned the air conditioner
  on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It turned out that Garby had caught whatever it was that I had.  It
  seemed like he still ate as much as usual, but he threw it up
  shortly thereafter.  I managed to moderate my eating so that I
  wouldn&#39;t throw up, but it was easy to decide that we needed to
  recuperate a little, so we took another zero.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Leaving Tehachapi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The nice lady who had given us a ride from the post office to the
  hotel had also given us her phone number and told us to call if we
  needed anything.  Neither of us felt like hitching out of town, so
  we took her up on it.  I think she was a bit surprised to hear from
  us again, but she was game.  On our way out of town, she took us
  past a friend&#39;s farm where a bison had just given birth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-fB3OXL1RI_k/TnvC0SftiCI/AAAAAAAACcA/NU7-CBFafo0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-fB3OXL1RI_k/TnvC0SftiCI/AAAAAAAACcA/NU7-CBFafo0/s800/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After plenty of ooh-ing and aah-ing, we got back to the trail and
  started hiking again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked through the remainder of the wind farm and across a
  highway, and we left the section.  Of all the hiking that I did,
  that might have been my least favorite section.  It was constantly
  hot (though I actually got somewhat lucky with the weather &amp;ndash; others
  had it much hotter than I did), and both I and my hiking partner got
  sick.  The first two days weren&#39;t bad, but the last two certainly
  made up for that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I may combine the next section with half of the following one so
  that I get to the start of the Sierras.  I&#39;m as excited to write
  about my experience in the Sierras as I was to get to them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-05/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-05/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section D</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-04/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-04/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-08-06T04:22:43Z</updated>
	<published>2012-05-27T21:35:03Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Section C ended with a couple of rainy days before a night at a Best
Western at Cajon Pass.  It was a restful night, and before long we
were on the trail again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Cajon Pass to Wrightwood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Most passes on the trail are higher than the trail around them, but
  Cajon Pass is the opposite.  So we had another day of climbing ahead
  of us.  This day was more than 5000 feet over about 22 miles.  So
  not very steep, but still a grind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As I went higher, the landscape changed from desert and chaparral to
  more of a forest.  It also became clear that we were reaching
  elevations where it could snow if there was any precipitation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-SZ19p5esr9U/Tdk5s92ISgI/AAAAAAAABf4/6uz_7f9FouU/s800/DSCF0572.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-SZ19p5esr9U/Tdk5s92ISgI/AAAAAAAABf4/6uz_7f9FouU/s800/DSCF0572.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Given that we had had bad weather over the past couple of days, this
  was a real concern.  The picture above has clouds in it, and I was
  monitoring them all day.  The plan for the day was to end near a
  trail going to the town of Wrightwood and then to spend the next day
  in Wrightwood.  If bad weather hit, we would go into Wrightwood that
  night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  What happened was a bit more complicated than that.  When we got to
  the top of the hill, the weather wasn&#39;t great.  The wind was blowing
  fiercely, and it was cold and cloudy, but there was no
  precipitation.  Morevover, we were at a campground with an outhouse
  that all the campers could pile into if the weather got truly
  awful.  Even though the outhouse didn&#39;t smell great, we would do it
  if we had to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We didn&#39;t have to, but I awoke the next morning to freezing rain.
  On the trail, I&#39;m generally an early riser, so I was out of camp
  before the others that were camping at the site with me.  Even
  though the trail to town was behind us, I decided to hike to the
  road that was about five miles ahead of us.  I guess I was in a bit
  of a masochistic mood.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As I walked down the trail, ice balls as big as cantaloupes fell
  from the trees around me.  The freezing rain was accompanied by a
  strong wind, and it felt like someone was sandblasting my face.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-njjbEhDW0l0/Tdk5_KJN01I/AAAAAAAABgE/ckXeQPMWtq4/s800/DSCF0574.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-njjbEhDW0l0/Tdk5_KJN01I/AAAAAAAABgE/ckXeQPMWtq4/s800/DSCF0574.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After a while, the trail was covered by snow and ice, and staying on
  it became more difficult.  At one point, I kept going straight after
  it had turned and ended up at a ski hill.  There was a nearby
  maintenance shed, and I stood in its wind shadow to warm up a bit
  and read my maps.  I was near the trail, so I got back on it.  After
  another half mile or so, I was still at the ski hill, but I found a
  warming shed.  The ski hill was closed for the season, but the
  heater in the shed still worked, so I had a chance to warm up for
  real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At that point, I knew I had two options.  I could either try to stay
  on the trail, or I could go down the ski run that I was sitting at
  the top of.  It is a truism that if you go down a ski run, you will
  eventually find a road at the end, so I knew that would work.  As I
  said, I was having trouble staying on trail, so it was an attractive
  option.  Looking back on it, going down the ski run would probably
  have been smarter, but I decided to try to stay on the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I did get slightly lost a couple more times, but eventually I found
  my way to the road.  As I descended, the weather got better (just
  rain and not freezing rain), but I was still pretty cold and wet by
  the time I got there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Unbeknownst to me, the road was closed in the direction that traffic
  would be coming towards town, so hitching was &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; hard.  Since
  I was cold and wet, I decided to keep moving, and walk towards
  town.  A few miles down the road there was an intersection which
  meant that finally there would be traffic in the correct direction
  on the road, so I got a hitch the rest of the way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had a nice time in Wrightwood, where I stayed in a room with Holden and
  (Head)Banger.  We went out for Mexican food at a place that
  advertised 5 cent margaritas with your meal.  Of course, only the
  first was 5 cents, but Holden didn&#39;t realize that.  Or perhaps he
  didn&#39;t want to realize it because it was his birthday.  In any case,
  he had quite a few of them, and it was a pretty fun night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Mount Baden-Powell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After a large pancake breakfast, I got a ride back to the trail.
  The first half of the day was flat and easy, and then I got to Mount
  Baden-Powell.  Initially, it was easy too, though steeper than most
  of the trail we had encountered so far, and then I got to the
  snow.  Even that didn&#39;t seem too bad &amp;ndash; someone had gone up it on
  skis, so the trail was easy to follow.  I met another hiker on the
  way up (I can&#39;t for the life of me remember his trail name), and we
  decided to stick together going up the mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-f0WndvmwhK8/Tdk6NjGRdRI/AAAAAAAADO4/H1NMH8DyaT4/s800/DSCF0576.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-f0WndvmwhK8/Tdk6NjGRdRI/AAAAAAAADO4/H1NMH8DyaT4/s800/DSCF0576.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Near the top of the mountain, the PCT turns and traverses the face
  of the mountain, and another trail keeps going to the top.
  Traverses are scarier to me than ridge walking, so we took the trail
  to the top.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-CBjbZoP7fWA/Tdk68VDz2DI/AAAAAAAABhQ/mwhBNd_L0rk/s800/DSCF0584.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-CBjbZoP7fWA/Tdk68VDz2DI/AAAAAAAABhQ/mwhBNd_L0rk/s800/DSCF0584.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Now here is where things get funny.  As you can see in the picture
  above, there was quite a fog that day.  So, following footsteps
  rather than our compasses, we went down the wrong ridge.  In the
  picture below, we were supposed to follow the red line, but we
  followed the orange one instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/mountainmishap.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/mountainmishap.png&quot; alt=&quot;mountainmishap.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  knew that we were lost.  What we didn&#39;t know was just how lost we
  were.  We started scouting around for the trail, going back to
  places where we had last seen footprints, and following animal paths
  to dead ends.  By the time we got our compasses out, we were off the
  map, but it didn&#39;t matter.  It was clear that we were going the
  wrong direction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Before we figured out exactly what had happened, Garby happened upon
  us.  He had gone down the path to Wrightwood rather than the road,
  so he had been a few hours behind us all day.  He had seen our
  footprints and assumed that we were going the right way.  So now
  there were three of us that were lost.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Once Garby showed up, though, we figured out what had happened
  pretty quickly.  It was clear that we would have to walk all the way
  back up Mount Baden-Powell, and go down the correct ridge.  By this
  time, however, the sun was setting, so we needed to camp.  It was a
  new experience for me, camping while lost.  It was not particularly
  pleasant.  I remember getting up during the night and seeing that
  the fog had cleared.  The moon was bright, and I could see the ridge
  that we needed to walk down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We were all up early the next morning, partly because we wanted to
  be back on the trail and officially un-lost, and partly because we
  were all almost out of water.  We hiked back up the mountain and
  down the correct ridge to a beautiful spring, with water coming out
  of the side of the mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Let me take a quick diversion here to talk about the process of
  hiking, rather than the journey.  On the AT I resisted technology
  for a long time.  On the PCT, however, I started the trail with an
  mp3 player.  I would charge and refill it with podcasts every chance
  that I got.  Some people hate any technology on the trail (except
  all the technologically-advanced stuff that they carry on their
  back, but I digress even further), but I think that listening to
  podcasts really helped me cement the experience in my brain.  I have
  trail memories triggered by my favorite podcasts all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I can picture exactly where I was when I was listening to the guys
  on &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebuglepodcast.com/&quot;&gt;The Bugle&lt;/a&gt; make fun of the hype surrounding the royal wedding.
  And now, whenever they mention it, I picture that place.  When I was
  going up the hill out of Cajon Pass, I was listening to an interview
  on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/programs/fresh-air/&quot;&gt;Fresh Air&lt;/a&gt; with a couple who filmed lions.  On the way down Mount
  Baden-Powell, I was listening to Tig Notaro on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.maximumfun.org/shows/jordan-jesse-go&quot;&gt;Jordan, Jesse, Go&lt;/a&gt;.  I
  heard Tig on another podcast the other day and immediately thought
  of the whole experience.  Even more than a year later, these are
  completely vivid memories, and I think the fact that I was making
  mental connections between what I was listening to and the place
  that I was hiking through helped that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So anyway to distill it to two words: podcasts good.  Just always
  have one earbud out if you are walking in a place that could have
  snakes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Frog Detour and Station Fire Burn area&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The next couple of days are a bit of a blur (though I could tell you
  what I listened to).  It was a beautiful area, but perhaps the
  slightly traumatic experience of getting so lost pushed the memories
  out of my head.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  One thing that does stick out is a long road walk to detour around
  the habitat of an endangered species of frog.  I later heard that
  horseback riders are likely more damaging to the frogs&#39; habitat than
  hikers, so I would have been fine going through the detour, but I
  did the detour in any case.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The day after the frog-detour day, the trail went through the burn
  zone of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Station_Fire_(2009)#Los_Angeles_County&quot;&gt;Station Fire&lt;/a&gt;.  An act of arson, this fire had been so
  bad that it burned down the ranger station.  They were rebuilding
  at the time that we were there, which is a good thing to see, but a
  burn zone is a pretty sad thing for me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-4-1&quot;&gt;Boris&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-4-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/socal-03&quot;&gt;last section&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned that there was a funny story with
   Boris and LoL.  Around the frog detour, just past Mount
   Baden-Powell, LoL went into the bushes to go to the bathroom and
   Boris passed him without LoL knowing it.  Boris was in the zone,
   moving fast, and even though he and LoL had been hiking together,
   he didn&#39;t wait around for LoL.  With his head down, he even missed
   a turn and went a little way on a wrong path before realizing it
   and bushwhacking down to the correct path.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   After half a day of not seeing his buddy, LoL got concerned.
   Assuming that Boris was behind him, LoL decided to wait for Boris.
   When he got word from hikers behind him that they had seen a place
   where a hillside had been torn up and it looked like someone had
   fallen down the mountain, LoL had all the reason he needed to panic
   and call in search and rescue.  They sent a team to the place where
   the possible fall had been seen, but found no Boris.  They had
   sheriffs go to all the campgrounds in the area and yell his name
   (one of them woke me up).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Boris was at the same campground as Garby, about 10 miles ahead of
   me, and had no idea that so much was going on in his honor.  When
   he found out, he was mightily embarrassed, and that&#39;s how he got
   his trail name of Overdrive.  My theory is that he didn&#39;t want to
   be associated with the name that the sheriffs had been yelling.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Vasquez Rocks and Hiker Heaven&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It had been an eventful section, and there were two last treats.
  The first was the Vasquez Rocks.  Huge weather-worn rocks sticking
  out of the desert, they epitomize what I think of as a western
  scene.  For good reason, it turns out.  They have been used in
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_productions_using_the_Vasquez_Rocks_as_a_filming_location&quot;&gt;quite a lot of movies and TV shows&lt;/a&gt; that want to have a &quot;Western&quot;
  location.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Z88b0OU1DKE/Tdk8D_-Gn5I/AAAAAAAABiI/wBHthUwP2j0/s800/DSCF0595.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Z88b0OU1DKE/Tdk8D_-Gn5I/AAAAAAAABiI/wBHthUwP2j0/s800/DSCF0595.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It is quite a touristy location, to the extent that they even have
  placards along the path identifying the flora.  I was a bit
  surprised to see that they even had one identifying poison oak.  I
  would think that it would be easier to remove the poison oak than to
  put up a sign saying what it is, but I guess that shows what I know.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-5-1&quot;&gt;Hiker Heaven&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-5-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Just past the Vasquez Rocks is a hostel appropriately named Hiker
   Heaven.  It&#39;s run by the Saufleys, who are a great couple who
   happen to have a large yard and love hikers.  I took a zero there,
   and got a ride to an outfitter near LA where I got a couple of
   things that I had been needing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Into the real desert.  Night-hiking to avoid the sun.  Going by
  another wind farm.  Feeling sick.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-04/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-04/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section C</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-03/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-03/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-05-24T05:49:41Z</updated>
	<published>2012-05-24T05:49:41Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;A bit of news&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This blog has been pretty quiet lately, because I recently moved
  from Calgary to sunny California.  I took a job with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.starviewinc.com/&quot;&gt;Starview&lt;/a&gt; in San
  Jose, and I&#39;m living nearby in Sunnyvale.  Things are going really
  well with the job, and I&#39;ve been working hard so that I can make an
  impact right out of the gate.  Of course, that cuts down on the time
  that I have for writing blogs.  So that&#39;s what I&#39;ve been up to.  On
  with the story of the hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Cabazon to Big Bear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Section B ends in an ugly way under an interstate highway overpass.
  It&#39;s sandy, and that&#39;s hard to walk on.  By the time we got there,
  it was already after noon, and mighty hot.  A wall of clouds loomed,
  but it was easy to disregard them, considering that we were still in
  what could easily be considered desert.  The clouds were to one side
  and Palm Springs was on the other.  We were moving closer to Palm
  Springs, so there was no way it was going to rain.  (Have you
  guessed that it&#39;s going to rain yet?)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As we walked, we came nearer to a wind farm, the first of two that
  we would walk past on our hike.  It is a little hard to imagine how
  large the turbines are when you just see them fleetingly as you
  drive past, but when you walk near them, you get the full
  experience.  They aren&#39;t messing around.  There is a little man-made
  oasis near a maintenance truck by the wind farm where there is shade
  and refreshments, so we took a break and tended to our feet for a
  while before we started moving again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vQn_UOPq5WE/Tdk4j0aSxaI/AAAAAAAABeo/uA1H-sRNowg/s800/DSCF0561.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vQn_UOPq5WE/Tdk4j0aSxaI/AAAAAAAABeo/uA1H-sRNowg/s800/DSCF0561.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  A little after we left, it started raining.  At first it was a
  relief.  We had been walking under completely blue skies in Southern
  California for around two weeks, and the variety was nice.  However,
  I had been expecting the blue skies and had not packed any rain gear
  for this part of the journey (I sent it all to the beginning of the
  Sierras).  So after a while, even my fleece was getting
  waterlogged.  Our plan upon leaving the oasis had been to try to get
  to a fish hatchery that was about a half a mile off-trail.  Since it
  would clearly be the only shelter for miles, it became a must.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had been hiking in the vicinity of Garby, Raven, and Lovebird all
  day, and we met up near where we thought the junction with the
  fish-hatchery trail would be.  In fact, I thought that we were at
  the junction because I was misreading the map.  In my defense, it&#39;s
  pretty hard to read a map through a plastic bag in a hard rain, but
  that doesn&#39;t change the fact that I was misreading the map.  I was
  lucky that Raven was more persuasive than me, and convinced us to go
  on until we actually found the junction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we made it to the fish hatchery, where there was shelter
  (a gazebo-like structure for tourists to picnic under).  We had gone
  over 27 miles on the day &amp;ndash; more than 1% of the trail.  I quickly
  set up my hammock between two beams of the gazebo, but the setup
  wasn&#39;t optimal, and the wind kept waking me up throughout the night
  by flapping the tarp.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was almost completely uphill.  The rain was gone and it
  was hot once again.  I got an early start, but that only gets you so
  much.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-uXHQpSRVdnY/Tdk4tpTOZJI/AAAAAAAABes/Zg3tvddCOsE/s800/DSCF0562.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-uXHQpSRVdnY/Tdk4tpTOZJI/AAAAAAAABes/Zg3tvddCOsE/s800/DSCF0562.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked up the basin formed by a creek for almost the whole day.
  By the end of the day, we had climbed around 5000 feet.  It was cold
  at night at that altitude and there were pine trees.  We ran into
  some fun people at the camp site, most notably Love it or Leave it
  (abbreviated LoL) and Hercules.  Hercules will show up again much
  later in the story, but we will meet LoL and his friend Boris (aka
  Overdrive) again much sooner.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After our long climb, Garby and I kept the next day nice and easy,
  setting ourselves up for a nearo into the town of Big Bear.  We
  found a nice camp at around 3 and then just rested for the remainder
  of the day.  We even made a camp fire.  Unfortunately, Lovebird had
  shin splints, so he and Raven hitched in to Big Bear by an alternate
  road before our camp.  We would see them in town, but it was the
  last I would hike with them for quite a while.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  On the Appalachian Trail, you can tell that you are having a good
  day if you can do &quot;12 by 12&quot;.  That is, 12 miles by noon.  Garby and
  I had 9 miles to go to get to the road into Big Bear the next day
  and we made it by 9 o&#39;clock.  9 by 9 is so much better than 12 by
  12 that I was pretty impressed, but perhaps it&#39;s one of those things
  that doesn&#39;t really translate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, we spent the day in Big Bear.  It&#39;s a very spread-out town,
  which makes it bad for hikers, so I won&#39;t say too much about it.
  (Other than to note that it has the smallest ski hill I think I&#39;ve
  ever seen.  Seriously, there must be sand dunes that are bigger.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Big Bear to Cajon Pass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Following our day in Big Bear, we must have walked for a while, but
  I don&#39;t remember it at all.  So I&#39;ll skip it.  The day after that,
  we made one of our biggest mistakes on the trail.  A section of the
  trail was closed due to a rock slide, and an alternate route was
  given.  We took the alternate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At first, it didn&#39;t look too bad. It was mostly on dirt roads, but
  there wasn&#39;t any traffic.  However, we soon turned off the dirt road
  onto off-road-vehicle roads.  It was a Friday, and the off-roaders
  were out in force.  There were vehicles of all shapes and sizes from
  dirt bikes to Hummers.  Every 20 minutes or so, there would be a
  procession of them.  The passengers would hold up their fingers
  indicating how many more were coming, which is thoughtful, but also
  disheartening.  &quot;Really, there are 7 more of you jerks disrupting my
  day?&quot;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We ate lunch by a little creek and I got some water out of it,
  upstream of its crossing with the road.  It was a good thing that I
  did, because as we were eating lunch, three Jeeps came to the
  creek.  We sat and watched as they crossed and re-crossed the creek
  4 or 5 times, a different passenger getting out and taking video of
  the crossing each time.  It was maddening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We later heard that if we had not taken the alternate, the trail
  would have been beautiful and the rock slide not too bad.  Also,
  Deep Creek, which is where the trail went, is a natural hot spring
  that is clothing-optional.  The day that we missed it, there was a
  rumored nude photo shoot there.  Now of course this is a only trail
  rumor, so who knows if it&#39;s true, but it sure sounds like the kind
  of thing that I would have liked to have verified for myself.  For
  science, of course.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, by the end of the long day, we finished the alternate route
  and were back on the trail.  We met an older lady, and being a bit
  dumb, I didn&#39;t realize who she was until she was already gone.  Her
  name is Mother Goose, and she is an a true trail legend.  She is
  still going strong &amp;ndash; according to her &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.postholer.com/mothergoose&quot;&gt;trail journal&lt;/a&gt;, she is hiking
  the PCT again this year.  I set up my hammock in some scrubby trees
  on a hillside and it rained again at night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It kept raining the next morning, and I got as colder as the day
  went on.  My strategy in situations like that is generally to push
  on and keep moving so that I generate body heat.  That day, however,
  it was really bad.  It just never let up.  Eventually I met up with
  Garby at an underpass where we found some shelter from the rain.  I
  tried to tear open a pack of crackers, but my fingers were so cold
  that they had lost the strength required even for that.  Out of the
  rain, we warmed up again, and eventually found the courage to hike
  on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It didn&#39;t rain much longer that day, and before long we were drying
  our tarps in the sun.  The terrain also became more deserty again,
  which was heartening.  I was really tired of rain by that point.  I
  had not expected it or packed for it.  Even when you&#39;re ready for
  it, cold rain isn&#39;t much fun, but when you&#39;re not ready for it, it&#39;s
  downright awful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, in the afternoon, we walked by some very windy cliffs to
  Cajon Pass.  It sounds nice, but it&#39;s really a McDonald&#39;s and a Best
  Western at a highway rest stop.  I got my customary chocolate shake,
  and a room at the Best Western.  I was tired from the long days
  and walking in the rain, so I slept deeply.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Snow and ice.  Getting really lost.  Finally getting back to normal
  weather and having to take a &quot;frog detour&quot;.  Boris and LoL get up to
  some shenanigans that keep people up at night.  Finally, we meet
  some of the nicest trail angels around.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-03/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-03/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section B</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-02/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-02/"/>






	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="pct" />


	<updated>2012-04-23T00:33:42Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-22T23:04:48Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Warner Springs to Idyllwild&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Leaving Warner Springs, my feet were getting tired.  I had started
  with shoes that had almost no padding (the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004IHNHQK/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004IHNHQK&quot;&gt;Merrell Trail Glove&lt;/a&gt;), and
  it was turning out that they were too minimal for the task at hand.
  They were fine for forests, but the rocky desert that I was walking
  on was not forgiving enough.  I had ordered some of my favorite
  trail runners to be sent to a cafe that was a couple of days away,
  though, so I was keen to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first day out of Warner Springs, I met up with the group of
  three ladies that I met the day before Warner Springs.  We made it
  to a water tank by the early afternoon and then sat and shot the
  breeze during the really hot part of the day.  Annie&#39;s blisters were
  still really bad, but she had gotten epsom salts in town, and she
  spent quite a while soaking her feet in a plastic bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We eventually hiked on, but it was starting to get dark quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-2OWhQv6J7RU/Tdk1sPcwPXI/AAAAAAAABcE/tiQCf5BoyCQ/s640/DSCF0533.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-2OWhQv6J7RU/Tdk1sPcwPXI/AAAAAAAABcE/tiQCf5BoyCQ/s640/DSCF0533.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we got to a spot with some flat areas where tents could
  be set up.  Unfortunately for me, there were no trees where I could
  hang my hammock, so I had to &quot;cowboy camp&quot;.  It&#39;s a pretty common
  thing to do, especially on the PCT, where there is very little
  rain.  Basically, it is camping without any shelter.  I put the tarp
  of my hammock down and my mat and sleeping back on top of it.  The
  bugs were pretty bad (I kept Annie awake by slapping at mosquitoes),
  and the ground was a lot less comfortable than my hammock, but I
  made it through the night.  Thankfully, it was one of the very few
  times that I was forced to sleep on the ground during the whole
  trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was, for me, a big day.  I wanted to get to the cafe as
  quickly as possible to get my shoes.  We started early, but before
  long it was hot again.  Raven, Lovebird, and Garby, who had all left
  Warner Springs a bit after I had, caught and passed me.  Eventually
  we all met at a water cache and again tried to wait out the sun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I found that I couldn&#39;t wait.  New shoes were just too close and too
  tantalizing.  It was really hot, but they would have cold drinks at
  the cafe.  I walked on, up and down hills, and across dirt roads
  with no trail magic until I finally got to the top of a hill where I
  could see the road with the cafe.  I could see Annie ahead of me, and
  I knew that she would have no trouble getting a ride.  I was also
  really excited about the cafe.  So I started running down the hill
  towards the road.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Annie really had no trouble getting the ride &amp;ndash; I think someone
  stopped before she had enough put out her thumb, so I was on my
  own.  Before long Raven and Lovebird showed up and the three of us
  got a ride together.  After a short ride, we were at Paradise Valley
  Cafe. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Paradise Valley Cafe really is a paradise, especially for
  thru-hikers.  First, it has one of the best waitresses I have ever
  seen.  She was a marvel of efficiency, giving us ice water as soon
  as we came in and refilling our drinks well before they ran dry.
  She was even reading hiking books in an effort to connect better
  with her clientele.  It also has really good burgers (of course I
  got the veggie patty), and is in a really beautiful location.  What
  made me the happiest, though, was my new shoes.  After 150 miles of
  shoes with no padding at all, they felt like walking on cushions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we had to leave paradise.  It was late, and there was a
  little trail behind the cafe back to the PCT, so I walked down that
  until I found a couple of trees where I could hang my hammock.  All
  the trees were too big or too far apart until I got nearly all the
  way to the trail.  Even then, I had to be very creative to make the
  hammock work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was up early the next day and moving a lot faster.  We were
  heading into the San Jacinto mountains, and the elevation gain meant
  that we would get some respite from the heat.  Down below was the
  desert and Palm Springs, and I was glad not to be there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pM9l-VDxsJs/Tdk20nApc3I/AAAAAAAABdI/xgHbg9636UM/s800/DSCF0544.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pM9l-VDxsJs/Tdk20nApc3I/AAAAAAAABdI/xgHbg9636UM/s800/DSCF0544.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ycRPfwUCUxk/Tdk2gFfAcQI/AAAAAAAABc8/UMgJkDT8O-U/s800/DSCF0541.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ycRPfwUCUxk/Tdk2gFfAcQI/AAAAAAAABc8/UMgJkDT8O-U/s800/DSCF0541.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3G_8V1I7vcg/Tdk3S3oDeqI/AAAAAAAABdg/1RSwB_PPTPU/s800/DSCF0549.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3G_8V1I7vcg/Tdk3S3oDeqI/AAAAAAAABdg/1RSwB_PPTPU/s800/DSCF0549.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I slept on the side of a mountain that night, and the next morning
  came to some snow-covered trail.  At that point, it was still enough
  of a novelty that I took a picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Q7sN1vpeiXg/Tdk39Isin5I/AAAAAAAABeA/piFJkqioW0U/s800/DSCF0555.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Q7sN1vpeiXg/Tdk39Isin5I/AAAAAAAABeA/piFJkqioW0U/s800/DSCF0555.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LXdf2CTd3m8/Tdk4QqnTBLI/AAAAAAAABeY/folE9Emn3AE/s800/DSCF0558.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LXdf2CTd3m8/Tdk4QqnTBLI/AAAAAAAABeY/folE9Emn3AE/s800/DSCF0558.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Later that day I made it down a steep side trail to Idyllwild, and
  met up with the rest of the crew.  We had a Mexican feast and
  listened to some really good live music until &quot;hiker midnight&quot; (9
  PM).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Fuller Ridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Up early the next day to hike back up the side trail.  We had more
  snow ahead of us, and the dreaded Fuller Ridge.  People had been
  hyping Fuller Ridge for at least 50 miles, and as with most things
  in life, it didn&#39;t live up to the hype.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Though I&#39;m writing about it now with some bravado, I must admit that
  I was glad to be with a group.  Even better was having Lovebird and
  Raven in the group, who are from the Yukon and have a lot of
  experience hiking on snow.  Garby showed me how to shorten one
  hiking pole while walking on the side of a ridge, but all in all
  Fuller Ridge really wasn&#39;t that bad.  The most difficult thing was
  navigating on the snow.  We had a good idea of where we were on the
  map, and using some intuition and my altimeter watch, we were able
  to stay at the right elevation.  When we walked over the wilderness
  sign that was buried almost to its top in the snow, we knew we were
  at the right place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We ended the day at a trailhead whose elevation was not much
  different from the top of the ridge.  It had already been raining a
  bit during the day, and it continued into the night.  Because of the
  elevation, it froze over night and I awoke to find a thin layer of
  ice covering my hammock&#39;s tarp.  Since my new shoes were frozen, I
  wore my old ones for a while that morning as we started our
  descent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The descent from Fuller Ridge is kind of amazing.  The factoid on
  the map states that it&#39;s 4.3 miles in a straight line but 15.2 miles
  on the trail.  It&#39;s just one switchback after another.  It&#39;s a
  little boring, but we made quick work of it.  We got to the bottom
  by noon.  We had lost about 7000 feet of elevation in the morning
  and were in the boiling heat of the sun once more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Some editing will be in order if I ever want to finish writing about
  this hike.  I remember it all so vividly, though, and I enjoy
  reliving the details.  Anyway, we will go past a wind farm and get
  caught in the rain.  We will miss some of the best sights on the
  trail because we stupidly followed the law and took a marked
  detour.  And a Best Western will never have seemed so good after a
  tough day with some more rain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-02/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-02/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>More Clojurescript Macros</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros-02/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros-02/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="macros" />


	<updated>2012-04-20T23:18:48Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-20T22:47:21Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Most of my time this week was spent traveling and in meetings, but I
did have a chance to work on the Clojurescript macro system that I
have been working on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Things didn&#39;t start too well for the system, since it would not run
  the simplest of tests written for it in the Clojurescript testing
  system.  My test was a macro that would take a positive integer,
  recursively decrease it until it was zero, and then output the
  zero.  (Clearly not the smartest macro in the world &amp;ndash; it was just
  meant to test recursion.)  However, I kept getting errors saying
  that the system didn&#39;t know how to test equality among numbers.
  This seemed strange until I realized that the &lt;code&gt;extend-type&lt;/code&gt; call for
  numbers wasn&#39;t getting executed because it wasn&#39;t expanded into a
  &lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt;.  (I had been executing all &lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; calls, which defined all
  functions and variables, but nothing else.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I briefly flirted with executing a bunch of other special forms,
  including &lt;code&gt;set!&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt;, but I could see that this would make
  things pretty unwieldy, and that the compiler would be doing a lot
  of confusing things, for example trying to execute a &lt;code&gt;set!&lt;/code&gt; that was
  buried deep inside a function without being able to know anything
  about the locals that it was being set to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That was clearly the way of madness, so I eventually decided to
  execute every special form that was at the top level.  This worked
  really well, and the tests started passing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I also added tests to make sure that the namespaces work as
  expected.  You can &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; macros from other namespaces
  just like other functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;What&#39;s not there (yet)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So far I have not added the &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;env&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;form&lt;/code&gt; variables to macros.
  I expect that it will be necessary to add them at some point (and
  honestly not too hard).  I know they are extremely useful in some
  projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clojure/core.match&quot;&gt;core.match&lt;/a&gt;, but that project has already been ported
  to Clojurescript (via Clojure macros), so it might make more sense
  to leave the large macros that need those facilities to Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Backquoted forms don&#39;t work as nicely as in Clojure.  The reason is
  that we are using Clojure&#39;s reader, which qualifies backquoted
  symbols with their full namespace.  Unfortunately, it doesn&#39;t know
  anything about Clojurescript namespaces, so expect to need to
  qualify symbols inside backquotes.  This is an area where true
  reader macros inside Clojure would be really helpful, but we have to
  live with what we have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;One step closer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  &amp;hellip; to Clojure in Clojure.  Clojurescript already has a reader and a
  compiler that can compile most of itself.  The reader isn&#39;t totally
  complete &amp;ndash; it doesn&#39;t have backquote working yet for example &amp;ndash; but
  it is close.  It recently got persistent vectors and persistent
  hash-maps.  With macros added, all that&#39;s left for Clojure in
  Clojure is to finish up the reader and get rid of the calls to
  Java.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros-02/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros-02/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section A</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/"/>






	<category term="PCT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-04-15T19:21:52Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-15T19:16:46Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Here we go on the first post of my recap of my experience on the
Pacific Crest Trail.  It&#39;s been nearly a year since I started, and I
didn&#39;t keep records of where I stayed as well as on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./tags/AT&quot;&gt;AT&lt;/a&gt;, so this
recap will probably be a bit less detailed than that one (which might
be a good thing).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s the obligatory &quot;before&quot; photo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Across the wall behind me is Mexico.  My shirt is clean, my pack&#39;s
color is vivid, and my face is clean-shaven.  None of those things
would be true for very long on this hike.  I had arrived at the border
at around 6:30 PM, so I didn&#39;t plan to go very far that evening.  I
passed the first mile-marker on my way to the small town near the
trailhead:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had food with me, but no water.  The store owner (because the town
was little more than a convenience store) made me buy water.  Since
Southern California is mostly a desert, I felt it was the best idea to
go along with it.  I walked a bit longer (I made maybe about three
miles on the first evening), found a place to set up my hammock, made
supper and went to bed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day really showed the rigors of desert hiking.  With the sun
beating down and hardly any shade, it wasn&#39;t long before things got
really hot.  I heard my first rattlesnake in bushes nearby, but I just
kept trudging on.  At lunchtime, though, I found a bit of shade at the
bottom of a hill near a flowing stream.  There was another hiker there
with the trail name Hikeaholic.  He had hiked the PCT before and had
even been a maintainer of the trail in Washington, and he was quite
encouraging about my chances.  After lunch, we parted ways, and I went
on to the Lake Morena campsite for the first day of what is known as
the Kickoff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://adzpctko.org&quot;&gt;Kickoff&lt;/a&gt; is an annual event where many of the northbound hikers
(which is just about everyone on the PCT) get together.  Gear
companies show up along with trail &quot;alumni&quot; who want to re-live the
fun and scare the newbies.  There were a few hundred tents set up in
the campsite by the evening, and the next morning I thought that I had
seen enough.  I go hiking to avoid crowds of that size, so I started
down the trail in the cool of the morning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was on my own for most of the day, but I met two couples that I
would later hike with for long distances: Raven and Lovebird, and
Funyan and Meow-Meow.  Of course, they didn&#39;t have their trail names
at that point, but after a while it becomes more natural to refer to
people by their trail names than their actual names.  At the end of
the day, I set up camp just above a dry creek bed with another person
with whom I would hike most of Southern California: a tall guy who got
the trail name Garby from his ability to clean everyone&#39;s plates
like a garbage disposal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day actually had some pine forest, which was a bit of a
surprise.  I enjoyed the shade, but it didn&#39;t last long, and
eventually I was back in the sun.  I ended the day in a campsite that
was the last bit of green on the map for many miles.  I had gotten
there minutes after Lovebird, Raven, and Garby.  There was another
person that I hadn&#39;t met before, who introduced himself as Swope.  I
told the group that my intention was to stay at the campsite so that I
could be sure to find a place to hang my hammock.  I very quickly
regretted it as Swope announced that that made us hiking buddies,
because he was staying there as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could tell that Swope was a little off, and as the evening went on,
it became even more clear.  He talked a mile a minute about some very
strange topics, he clearly hadn&#39;t been long-distance hiking before,
and he had a massive pack (around 50 pounds) whose weight he had
reduced from about 80 pounds the day before.  He even had a satellite
phone with him &amp;ndash; pretty strange for someone who wanted to get away
from civilization.  Eventually, I had all that I could take and
escaped to my hammock for some shuteye.  (Sorry Swope if you ever read
this.  Some people are just not natural hiking companions.)  Swope got
out of camp ahead of me the next morning, but given his huge pack, I
had no trouble passing him very quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The hiking was turning out to be slightly different than I had
expected.  When I think of the desert, I imagine really sandy areas
with almost no vegetation.  This was fairly rocky with shrubs and
brushy trees.  Desert is actually a misnomer: the ecosystem is known
as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaparral&quot;&gt;chaparral&lt;/a&gt;.  It was still hot, though, and when I got to a water
tank at around noon, I decided to wait out the sun for a while.  While
I was waiting, I met Skinny D.  We talked for a while, and then she
went on ahead of me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We met again at Scissors Crossing &amp;ndash; an awkward intersection of roads
&amp;ndash; where trail angels had left water, energy drinks, beer, and even a
pie.  It was supper time, so we ate supper and then had the pie for
desert.  Skinny D went a bit farther, but I found some trees near a
dried creek bed, and hung out there.  It was surprisingly cold over
night &amp;ndash; the lack of moisture in the air causes that to happen &amp;ndash; and
I was glad to get moving the next morning so that I could get warm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That day highlighted another big difference between the PCT and the
AT.  The whole day was spent going over one big hill.  On the AT, the
hills come thick and fast, but on the PCT they are much more gradual.
The net effect is that you spend a long time going up and then a long
time going down.  We finished the day just past mile 100, where I met
up with many of the people I had met earlier as well as two new ones:
Liz and Annie.  Annie had terrible blisters, but she was pushing
through the pain, which eventually led to her trail name &quot;Push&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was only about 7 miles to the first trail town &amp;ndash; Warner Springs.
There&#39;s really not much more to the town than a small resort and a
gas-station convenience store, where I picked up my first resupply.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After getting to Warner Springs nice and early, I got a room at the
resort with Garby, and we had a lot of fun there with Raven and
Lovebird as well.  While we were eating at the pub, a
bedraggled-looking Swope walked in.  He was clearly the worse for
wear, and had only hiked as far as Scissors Crossing (meaning that he
had somehow gotten a day behind me despite starting at the same time
two days earlier).  He then hitchhiked to Warner Springs and was
intending to get a ride back to Scissors Crossing and return to Warner
Springs by running.  It was, as always, an unconventional approach.
It was the last I would see of him, but I did hear that he made it
farther than I had expected (though I don&#39;t know if he finished).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later that night, the four of us went for a dip in the hot pool that
is fed by the hot springs.  It&#39;s debatable whether it hurt or helped
our hiking, but it was nice and relaxing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There will be fewer characters to introduce, so hopefully I can
  write about more than one section.  The trail goes from chaparral to
  mountains and back, and we have a snow storm in the mountains and a
  rain storm in the desert.  Hopefully I&#39;ll be able to get to the part
  where I get massively lost by walking down the wrong mountain
  ridge.  That was fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Clojurescript Macros</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="macros" />


	<updated>2012-04-11T06:33:51Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-11T05:36:33Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Today I wrote a proof-of-concept implementation of a macro system for
Clojurescript.  The code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/clojurescript/tree/defmacro&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clojurescript already had a sort of macro system in the form of
Clojure macros, but this is different &amp;ndash; the macros are written in
Clojurescript, get compiled to JavaScript, and are evaluated by a
JavaScript interpreter.  They can be mixed in with Clojurescript code
and call Clojurescript functions.  In theory, they should work with
any Clojurescript backend that implements the REPL-related protocols
(but who knows if that&#39;s true).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&#39;s the big announcement.  What follows are some implementation
details and other notes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Implementation details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The macros are defined by passing strings back and forth between the
  Clojurescript compiler and the Rhino JavaScript interpreter.  The
  strings from Rhino are read by Clojure using &lt;code&gt;read-string&lt;/code&gt;, so
  macros are limited to things that can be printed by Clojurescript in
  a form that Clojure can read.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Macros are not yet put into the correct namespaces.  I don&#39;t think
  it will be too hard to do that correctly though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Rhino is a slow beast.  It adds multiple seconds to the startup time
  of the compiler.  It might be smart to scan the file for calls to
  &lt;code&gt;defmacro&lt;/code&gt; before including the macro-interpreting code.  However,
  since macro expansion requires that all functions are defined in the
  interpreter, once a &lt;code&gt;defmacro&lt;/code&gt; is hit, all the functions in the file
  preceding it (and in all &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt;&#39;d files) must be re-parsed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Existing Clojure macros should still work.  If two macros have the
  same name, the Clojurescript one will take precedence, but of course
  getting namespaces working should eliminate most conflicts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It should go without saying that this is completely experimental at
  this point.  Things seem like they work to me, but they might yet
  blow up in unexpected ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;An example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Here is a simple Clojurescript file which implements the &lt;code&gt;unless&lt;/code&gt;
  macro (also known as &lt;code&gt;when-not&lt;/code&gt; in Clojure, but I think giving it a
  different name shows better that it is really not using the Clojure
  macros).
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot;&gt;(defmacro unless
  [pred &amp;amp; body]
  `(if (not ~pred)
     (do ~@body)
     nil))

(let [a (unless true (/ 1 0) (+ 1 1))]
  a)
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  And here is its output:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot;&gt;var a__5799 = (cljs.core.truth_(cljs.core.not.call(null,true))?(function (){(1 / 0);
return (1 + 1);
})():null);

a__5799;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It&#39;s a bit ugly, but it should be obvious what&#39;s going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m pretty happy with the progress so far.  It really shows how
  flexible the Clojurescript compiler is that a macro system could be
  added in under 75 lines of code, with nearly half of that being very
  lightly modified from the compiler itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Clojure Data Structures</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-data-structures/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-data-structures/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />


	<updated>2012-04-01T01:27:15Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-01T01:27:15Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;This past week, I&#39;ve been knee-deep in Clojure data structures --
mostly persistent vector and hash-map.  The goal has been to provide
replacements written in pure Clojure that can be ported to
ClojureScript, but it has also been a great way to learn about how
these structures work.  So in this post, I&#39;ll try to summarize what I
learned, and give some the results of my hacking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Vector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I started this project inspired by a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/swannodette&quot;&gt;David Nolen&lt;/a&gt;.  I can&#39;t
  find it any more, but he mentioned that he had ported the
  persistent-vector data structure to JavaScript and that he was
  hoping to use it in ClojureScript.  That made me think: since
  the ClojureScript compiler now supports languages other than
  JavaScript as its backends, wouldn&#39;t it be helpful, at least for
  those backends, to port the data structure to pure Clojure, so that
  any ClojureScript backend could use it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I did.  The result is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/persistent-data-structures/blob/master/src/persistent_data_structures/vector.clj&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Instead of merely mechanically
  porting the Java into Clojure, I tried to really understand what was
  going on.  The gist is really simple (and has been talked about
  before): the vector is actually a tree with branching-factor 32, and
  a buffer of size 32.  When you add to the vector, you really add to
  the buffer if you can, copying the buffer before writing to it.
  When the buffer fills up, it is put in the tree, and again nodes are
  copied rather than simply written-to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  This procedure means that adding an element is a \(O(\log n)\)
  operation, but the constants are really good: for one thing, the
  base of the \(\log\) is 32, so the influence of the \(\log n\) in
  the overall running time is pretty small even for very large \(n\).
  For another thing, the \(\log n\) penalty is only incurred on every
  thirty-second insert.  Most inserts are constant-time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another cool feature is the way that the tree is structured.  Each
  node has its children in an array of length 32.  This means that the
  subtree that contains a given element can be found very quickly by
  simple bit operations.  To find the subtree containing element \(i\)
  in tree level \(k\), you shift \(i\) to the right by \(5k\) places
  and take the rightmost 5 bits.  This procedure would work with
  arrays that are of length of any power of 2, where you replace 5 by
  the \(\log_2\) of the length.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, Lszl Trk had pretty much the same idea as I did (and the
  author of gvec.clj, which is in the core distribution, had the same
  idea before either of us), and his code was better-tuned than mine,
  so it is what went into the new release of ClojureScript.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-1&quot;&gt;An aside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   When vectors are created in Clojure (but not yet in ClojureScript),
   they are created by way of a transient vector.  The idea behind this
   is that the transient vector is only around for the creation of the
   vector, so it does not need to be persistent.  Thus, it does not
   need to use the copy-on-write policy that persistent vectors use.
   In order to build a larger vector, it simply adds to an empty vector
   using the same procedure that I outlined above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Theoretically at least, that is not the optimal algorithm.  The
   trees can be built from the bottom-up (much like &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/clojure-sorting&quot;&gt;heaps&lt;/a&gt;), giving a
   \(O(n)\) algorithm, which also has very good constants.  I haven&#39;t
   computed the constant, but it should be less than \(1 {1 \over
   16}\).  I implemented this algorithm in Clojure, but the difference
   in constants between Clojure code and pure Java code, and the fact
   that the constants in the Java implementation are &lt;b&gt;so&lt;/b&gt; low meant
   that my implementation was slower even for very large \(n\).  I may
   one day try to port my bottom-up algorithm back to Java, but I kind
   of doubt it would make much difference.  Sometimes the
   theoretically better solution just isn&#39;t better in the real world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Hash Maps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I also had a look at hash maps.  The basic idea behind any hash-map
  is to store a key-value pair by first computing the &lt;i&gt;hash&lt;/i&gt; of the
  key to something much smaller &amp;ndash; in Clojure&#39;s case a 32-bit integer
  &amp;ndash; and then storing the pair in a location based on that hash.
  There are many ways that this could be done, and I had a look at the
  Java implementation used in Clojure and decided that I didn&#39;t really
  want to do much more porting.  So I came up with a couple of ideas
  that are related to Clojure&#39;s way of doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first idea was to make the same tree as used in the vector
  implementation, but to fill it in only as needed.  In essence, this
  was a sparse vector.  The Clojure implementation does something
  similar to this, but goes one step further by using a bit-map to
  signify which branches of the tree are actually used.  In this way,
  it can avoid copying arrays that are mostly full of placeholders.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next idea was a bit more radical.  It involved making a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patricia_trie&quot;&gt;radix tree&lt;/a&gt; of the input data.  Of all my experiments, this might have been
  the most successful.  In Clojure, its performance is very close to
  the built-in data structure.  In ClojureScript, for some reason it
  is much faster at storing new data than the built-in data structure
  but somewhat slower at retrieving data.  I am thinking that there
  must be some JavaScript-specific reason for this, but I haven&#39;t
  found it yet.  It could just be that the ClojureScript data
  structure is asymmetric in the opposite way (I haven&#39;t yet looked
  very deeply at it).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In all cases, the theoretical running times are pretty much what
  you&#39;d expect.  To either insert a new key-value pair or to find a
  key, it&#39;s basically the sum of the time needed to hash the key, a
  constant to find the place where the key is stored, and then
  something proportional to the number of other keys that have the
  same hash value that have been inserted so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In practice, large collections must be hashed each time they&#39;re
  inserted or searched for, so using them as keys is probably not a
  great idea.  In Clojure, negative numbers hash to one less than
  their absolute value, so there will probably be collisions if you
  use a large number of positive and negative numbers as keys, but
  it&#39;s not that big of a deal, since the number of collisions
  generated by this is at most two.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  At the very least, this was a good way to learn what&#39;s really going
  on under the hood.  I also did a lot of tuning &amp;ndash; not only adding
  typehints, but re-implementing some lazy functions to be non-lazy --
  which is certainly good experience.  I never made a data structure
  that was faster than one of the ones implemented in Java, but I got
  pretty close in both cases.  In order to get meaningful tests, I had
  to do things in a very big way: putting millions of things in
  vectors, and querying hash-maps hundreds of thousands of times.
  Most programs will not do these operations at such scales, and most
  of the tests still took less than a second on my underpowered
  laptop.  That makes me think pretty highly of the existing data
  structures in Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-data-structures/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-data-structures/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
