<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Hiking and Coding</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111107">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-04-20T23:18:48Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>More Clojurescript Macros</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros-02/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros-02/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="macros" />


	<updated>2012-04-20T23:18:48Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-20T22:47:21Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Most of my time this week was spent traveling and in meetings, but I
did have a chance to work on the Clojurescript macro system that I
have been working on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Things didn&#39;t start too well for the system, since it would not run
  the simplest of tests written for it in the Clojurescript testing
  system.  My test was a macro that would take a positive integer,
  recursively decrease it until it was zero, and then output the
  zero.  (Clearly not the smartest macro in the world &amp;ndash; it was just
  meant to test recursion.)  However, I kept getting errors saying
  that the system didn&#39;t know how to test equality among numbers.
  This seemed strange until I realized that the &lt;code&gt;extend-type&lt;/code&gt; call for
  numbers wasn&#39;t getting executed because it wasn&#39;t expanded into a
  &lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt;.  (I had been executing all &lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; calls, which defined all
  functions and variables, but nothing else.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I briefly flirted with executing a bunch of other special forms,
  including &lt;code&gt;set!&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt;, but I could see that this would make
  things pretty unwieldy, and that the compiler would be doing a lot
  of confusing things, for example trying to execute a &lt;code&gt;set!&lt;/code&gt; that was
  buried deep inside a function without being able to know anything
  about the locals that it was being set to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That was clearly the way of madness, so I eventually decided to
  execute every special form that was at the top level.  This worked
  really well, and the tests started passing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I also added tests to make sure that the namespaces work as
  expected.  You can &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; macros from other namespaces
  just like other functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;What&#39;s not there (yet)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So far I have not added the &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;env&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;form&lt;/code&gt; variables to macros.
  I expect that it will be necessary to add them at some point (and
  honestly not too hard).  I know they are extremely useful in some
  projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clojure/core.match&quot;&gt;core.match&lt;/a&gt;, but that project has already been ported
  to Clojurescript (via Clojure macros), so it might make more sense
  to leave the large macros that need those facilities to Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Backquoted forms don&#39;t work as nicely as in Clojure.  The reason is
  that we are using Clojure&#39;s reader, which qualifies backquoted
  symbols with their full namespace.  Unfortunately, it doesn&#39;t know
  anything about Clojurescript namespaces, so expect to need to
  qualify symbols inside backquotes.  This is an area where true
  reader macros inside Clojure would be really helpful, but we have to
  live with what we have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;One step closer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  &amp;hellip; to Clojure in Clojure.  Clojurescript already has a reader and a
  compiler that can compile most of itself.  The reader isn&#39;t totally
  complete &amp;ndash; it doesn&#39;t have backquote working yet for example &amp;ndash; but
  it is close.  It recently got persistent vectors and persistent
  hash-maps.  With macros added, all that&#39;s left for Clojure in
  Clojure is to finish up the reader and get rid of the calls to
  Java.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros-02/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros-02/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>California Section A</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/"/>






	<category term="PCT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-04-15T19:21:52Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-15T19:16:46Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Here we go on the first post of my recap of my experience on the
Pacific Crest Trail.  It&#39;s been nearly a year since I started, and I
didn&#39;t keep records of where I stayed as well as on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./tags/AT&quot;&gt;AT&lt;/a&gt;, so this
recap will probably be a bit less detailed than that one (which might
be a good thing).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s the obligatory &quot;before&quot; photo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Across the wall behind me is Mexico.  My shirt is clean, my pack&#39;s
color is vivid, and my face is clean-shaven.  None of those things
would be true for very long on this hike.  I had arrived at the border
at around 6:30 PM, so I didn&#39;t plan to go very far that evening.  I
passed the first mile-marker on my way to the small town near the
trailhead:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had food with me, but no water.  The store owner (because the town
was little more than a convenience store) made me buy water.  Since
Southern California is mostly a desert, I felt it was the best idea to
go along with it.  I walked a bit longer (I made maybe about three
miles on the first evening), found a place to set up my hammock, made
supper and went to bed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day really showed the rigors of desert hiking.  With the sun
beating down and hardly any shade, it wasn&#39;t long before things got
really hot.  I heard my first rattlesnake in bushes nearby, but I just
kept trudging on.  At lunchtime, though, I found a bit of shade at the
bottom of a hill near a flowing stream.  There was another hiker there
with the trail name Hikeaholic.  He had hiked the PCT before and had
even been a maintainer of the trail in Washington, and he was quite
encouraging about my chances.  After lunch, we parted ways, and I went
on to the Lake Morena campsite for the first day of what is known as
the Kickoff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://adzpctko.org&quot;&gt;Kickoff&lt;/a&gt; is an annual event where many of the northbound hikers
(which is just about everyone on the PCT) get together.  Gear
companies show up along with trail &quot;alumni&quot; who want to re-live the
fun and scare the newbies.  There were a few hundred tents set up in
the campsite by the evening, and the next morning I thought that I had
seen enough.  I go hiking to avoid crowds of that size, so I started
down the trail in the cool of the morning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was on my own for most of the day, but I met two couples that I
would later hike with for long distances: Raven and Lovebird, and
Funyan and Meow-Meow.  Of course, they didn&#39;t have their trail names
at that point, but after a while it becomes more natural to refer to
people by their trail names than their actual names.  At the end of
the day, I set up camp just above a dry creek bed with another person
with whom I would hike most of Southern California: a tall guy who got
the trail name Garby from his ability to clean everyone&#39;s plates
like a garbage disposal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day actually had some pine forest, which was a bit of a
surprise.  I enjoyed the shade, but it didn&#39;t last long, and
eventually I was back in the sun.  I ended the day in a campsite that
was the last bit of green on the map for many miles.  I had gotten
there minutes after Lovebird, Raven, and Garby.  There was another
person that I hadn&#39;t met before, who introduced himself as Swope.  I
told the group that my intention was to stay at the campsite so that I
could be sure to find a place to hang my hammock.  I very quickly
regretted it as Swope announced that that made us hiking buddies,
because he was staying there as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could tell that Swope was a little off, and as the evening went on,
it became even more clear.  He talked a mile a minute about some very
strange topics, he clearly hadn&#39;t been long-distance hiking before,
and he had a massive pack (around 50 pounds) whose weight he had
reduced from about 80 pounds the day before.  He even had a satellite
phone with him &amp;ndash; pretty strange for someone who wanted to get away
from civilization.  Eventually, I had all that I could take and
escaped to my hammock for some shuteye.  (Sorry Swope if you ever read
this.  Some people are just not natural hiking companions.)  Swope got
out of camp ahead of me the next morning, but given his huge pack, I
had no trouble passing him very quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The hiking was turning out to be slightly different than I had
expected.  When I think of the desert, I imagine really sandy areas
with almost no vegetation.  This was fairly rocky with shrubs and
brushy trees.  Desert is actually a misnomer: the ecosystem is known
as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaparral&quot;&gt;chaparral&lt;/a&gt;.  It was still hot, though, and when I got to a water
tank at around noon, I decided to wait out the sun for a while.  While
I was waiting, I met Skinny D.  We talked for a while, and then she
went on ahead of me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We met again at Scissors Crossing &amp;ndash; an awkward intersection of roads
&amp;ndash; where trail angels had left water, energy drinks, beer, and even a
pie.  It was supper time, so we ate supper and then had the pie for
desert.  Skinny D went a bit farther, but I found some trees near a
dried creek bed, and hung out there.  It was surprisingly cold over
night &amp;ndash; the lack of moisture in the air causes that to happen &amp;ndash; and
I was glad to get moving the next morning so that I could get warm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That day highlighted another big difference between the PCT and the
AT.  The whole day was spent going over one big hill.  On the AT, the
hills come thick and fast, but on the PCT they are much more gradual.
The net effect is that you spend a long time going up and then a long
time going down.  We finished the day just past mile 100, where I met
up with many of the people I had met earlier as well as two new ones:
Liz and Annie.  Annie had terrible blisters, but she was pushing
through the pain, which eventually led to her trail name &quot;Push&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was only about 7 miles to the first trail town &amp;ndash; Warner Springs.
There&#39;s really not much more to the town than a small resort and a
gas-station convenience store, where I picked up my first resupply.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After getting to Warner Springs nice and early, I got a room at the
resort with Garby, and we had a lot of fun there with Raven and
Lovebird as well.  While we were eating at the pub, a
bedraggled-looking Swope walked in.  He was clearly the worse for
wear, and had only hiked as far as Scissors Crossing (meaning that he
had somehow gotten a day behind me despite starting at the same time
two days earlier).  He then hitchhiked to Warner Springs and was
intending to get a ride back to Scissors Crossing and return to Warner
Springs by running.  It was, as always, an unconventional approach.
It was the last I would see of him, but I did hear that he made it
farther than I had expected (though I don&#39;t know if he finished).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later that night, the four of us went for a dip in the hot pool that
is fed by the hot springs.  It&#39;s debatable whether it hurt or helped
our hiking, but it was nice and relaxing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There will be fewer characters to introduce, so hopefully I can
  write about more than one section.  The trail goes from chaparral to
  mountains and back, and we have a snow storm in the mountains and a
  rain storm in the desert.  Hopefully I&#39;ll be able to get to the part
  where I get massively lost by walking down the wrong mountain
  ridge.  That was fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/socal-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Clojurescript Macros</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-macros/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="macros" />


	<updated>2012-04-11T06:33:51Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-11T05:36:33Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Today I wrote a proof-of-concept implementation of a macro system for
Clojurescript.  The code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/clojurescript/tree/defmacro&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clojurescript already had a sort of macro system in the form of
Clojure macros, but this is different &amp;ndash; the macros are written in
Clojurescript, get compiled to JavaScript, and are evaluated by a
JavaScript interpreter.  They can be mixed in with Clojurescript code
and call Clojurescript functions.  In theory, they should work with
any Clojurescript backend that implements the REPL-related protocols
(but who knows if that&#39;s true).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&#39;s the big announcement.  What follows are some implementation
details and other notes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Implementation details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The macros are defined by passing strings back and forth between the
  Clojurescript compiler and the Rhino JavaScript interpreter.  The
  strings from Rhino are read by Clojure using &lt;code&gt;read-string&lt;/code&gt;, so
  macros are limited to things that can be printed by Clojurescript in
  a form that Clojure can read.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Macros are not yet put into the correct namespaces.  I don&#39;t think
  it will be too hard to do that correctly though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Rhino is a slow beast.  It adds multiple seconds to the startup time
  of the compiler.  It might be smart to scan the file for calls to
  &lt;code&gt;defmacro&lt;/code&gt; before including the macro-interpreting code.  However,
  since macro expansion requires that all functions are defined in the
  interpreter, once a &lt;code&gt;defmacro&lt;/code&gt; is hit, all the functions in the file
  preceding it (and in all &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt;&#39;d files) must be re-parsed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Existing Clojure macros should still work.  If two macros have the
  same name, the Clojurescript one will take precedence, but of course
  getting namespaces working should eliminate most conflicts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It should go without saying that this is completely experimental at
  this point.  Things seem like they work to me, but they might yet
  blow up in unexpected ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;An example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Here is a simple Clojurescript file which implements the &lt;code&gt;unless&lt;/code&gt;
  macro (also known as &lt;code&gt;when-not&lt;/code&gt; in Clojure, but I think giving it a
  different name shows better that it is really not using the Clojure
  macros).
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defmacro&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt;
  [pred &amp;amp; body]
  `(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; ~pred)
     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; ~@body)
     nil))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; [a (unless true (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; 1 0) (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 1 1))]
  a)
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  And here is its output:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;a__5799&lt;/span&gt; = (cljs.core.truth_(cljs.core.not.call(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;))?(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; (){(1 / 0);
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; (1 + 1);
})():&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;);

a__5799;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It&#39;s a bit ugly, but it should be obvious what&#39;s going on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m pretty happy with the progress so far.  It really shows how
  flexible the Clojurescript compiler is that a macro system could be
  added in under 75 lines of code, with nearly half of that being very
  lightly modified from the compiler itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/cljs-macros/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Clojure Data Structures</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-data-structures/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-data-structures/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />


	<updated>2012-04-01T01:27:15Z</updated>
	<published>2012-04-01T01:27:15Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;This past week, I&#39;ve been knee-deep in Clojure data structures --
mostly persistent vector and hash-map.  The goal has been to provide
replacements written in pure Clojure that can be ported to
ClojureScript, but it has also been a great way to learn about how
these structures work.  So in this post, I&#39;ll try to summarize what I
learned, and give some the results of my hacking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Vector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I started this project inspired by a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/swannodette&quot;&gt;David Nolen&lt;/a&gt;.  I can&#39;t
  find it any more, but he mentioned that he had ported the
  persistent-vector data structure to JavaScript and that he was
  hoping to use it in ClojureScript.  That made me think: since
  the ClojureScript compiler now supports languages other than
  JavaScript as its backends, wouldn&#39;t it be helpful, at least for
  those backends, to port the data structure to pure Clojure, so that
  any ClojureScript backend could use it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I did.  The result is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/persistent-data-structures/blob/master/src/persistent_data_structures/vector.clj&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Instead of merely mechanically
  porting the Java into Clojure, I tried to really understand what was
  going on.  The gist is really simple (and has been talked about
  before): the vector is actually a tree with branching-factor 32, and
  a buffer of size 32.  When you add to the vector, you really add to
  the buffer if you can, copying the buffer before writing to it.
  When the buffer fills up, it is put in the tree, and again nodes are
  copied rather than simply written-to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  This procedure means that adding an element is a \(O(\log n)\)
  operation, but the constants are really good: for one thing, the
  base of the \(\log\) is 32, so the influence of the \(\log n\) in
  the overall running time is pretty small even for very large \(n\).
  For another thing, the \(\log n\) penalty is only incurred on every
  thirty-second insert.  Most inserts are constant-time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another cool feature is the way that the tree is structured.  Each
  node has its children in an array of length 32.  This means that the
  subtree that contains a given element can be found very quickly by
  simple bit operations.  To find the subtree containing element \(i\)
  in tree level \(k\), you shift \(i\) to the right by \(5k\) places
  and take the rightmost 5 bits.  This procedure would work with
  arrays that are of length of any power of 2, where you replace 5 by
  the \(\log_2\) of the length.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, László Török had pretty much the same idea as I did (and the
  author of gvec.clj, which is in the core distribution, had the same
  idea before either of us), and his code was better-tuned than mine,
  so it is what went into the new release of ClojureScript.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-1&quot;&gt;An aside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   When vectors are created in Clojure (but not yet in ClojureScript),
   they are created by way of a transient vector.  The idea behind this
   is that the transient vector is only around for the creation of the
   vector, so it does not need to be persistent.  Thus, it does not
   need to use the copy-on-write policy that persistent vectors use.
   In order to build a larger vector, it simply adds to an empty vector
   using the same procedure that I outlined above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Theoretically at least, that is not the optimal algorithm.  The
   trees can be built from the bottom-up (much like &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/clojure-sorting&quot;&gt;heaps&lt;/a&gt;), giving a
   \(O(n)\) algorithm, which also has very good constants.  I haven&#39;t
   computed the constant, but it should be less than \(1 {1 \over
   16}\).  I implemented this algorithm in Clojure, but the difference
   in constants between Clojure code and pure Java code, and the fact
   that the constants in the Java implementation are &lt;b&gt;so&lt;/b&gt; low meant
   that my implementation was slower even for very large \(n\).  I may
   one day try to port my bottom-up algorithm back to Java, but I kind
   of doubt it would make much difference.  Sometimes the
   theoretically better solution just isn&#39;t better in the real world.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Hash Maps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I also had a look at hash maps.  The basic idea behind any hash-map
  is to store a key-value pair by first computing the &lt;i&gt;hash&lt;/i&gt; of the
  key to something much smaller &amp;ndash; in Clojure&#39;s case a 32-bit integer
  &amp;ndash; and then storing the pair in a location based on that hash.
  There are many ways that this could be done, and I had a look at the
  Java implementation used in Clojure and decided that I didn&#39;t really
  want to do much more porting.  So I came up with a couple of ideas
  that are related to Clojure&#39;s way of doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first idea was to make the same tree as used in the vector
  implementation, but to fill it in only as needed.  In essence, this
  was a sparse vector.  The Clojure implementation does something
  similar to this, but goes one step further by using a bit-map to
  signify which branches of the tree are actually used.  In this way,
  it can avoid copying arrays that are mostly full of placeholders.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next idea was a bit more radical.  It involved making a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patricia_trie&quot;&gt;radix tree&lt;/a&gt; of the input data.  Of all my experiments, this might have been
  the most successful.  In Clojure, its performance is very close to
  the built-in data structure.  In ClojureScript, for some reason it
  is much faster at storing new data than the built-in data structure
  but somewhat slower at retrieving data.  I am thinking that there
  must be some JavaScript-specific reason for this, but I haven&#39;t
  found it yet.  It could just be that the ClojureScript data
  structure is asymmetric in the opposite way (I haven&#39;t yet looked
  very deeply at it).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In all cases, the theoretical running times are pretty much what
  you&#39;d expect.  To either insert a new key-value pair or to find a
  key, it&#39;s basically the sum of the time needed to hash the key, a
  constant to find the place where the key is stored, and then
  something proportional to the number of other keys that have the
  same hash value that have been inserted so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In practice, large collections must be hashed each time they&#39;re
  inserted or searched for, so using them as keys is probably not a
  great idea.  In Clojure, negative numbers hash to one less than
  their absolute value, so there will probably be collisions if you
  use a large number of positive and negative numbers as keys, but
  it&#39;s not that big of a deal, since the number of collisions
  generated by this is at most two.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  At the very least, this was a good way to learn what&#39;s really going
  on under the hood.  I also did a lot of tuning &amp;ndash; not only adding
  typehints, but re-implementing some lazy functions to be non-lazy --
  which is certainly good experience.  I never made a data structure
  that was faster than one of the ones implemented in Java, but I got
  pretty close in both cases.  In order to get meaningful tests, I had
  to do things in a very big way: putting millions of things in
  vectors, and querying hash-maps hundreds of thousands of times.
  Most programs will not do these operations at such scales, and most
  of the tests still took less than a second on my underpowered
  laptop.  That makes me think pretty highly of the existing data
  structures in Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-data-structures/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-data-structures/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Org Plugin Rethink</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2012-03-14T15:47:03Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-14T15:47:03Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I am glad to announce a new version of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/ikiwiki-org-plugin&quot;&gt;ikiwiki org plugin&lt;/a&gt;.  This is
a major change to the way things had worked previously, and is much
faster than previous versions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The installation procedure has changed, so please read the
&lt;code&gt;README.org&lt;/code&gt; file in the repository for information about how to
install the plugin.  Also, if you have installed a previous version,
please remove that since it may conflict.  Also be sure that you kill
any daemonized versions of emacs that are running.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This version of the plugin is no longer what ikiwiki calls an
  &quot;external plugin&quot;.  The overhead associated with XML-RPC was simply
  too high (at least on the emacs side of things).  I tried
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/ikiwiki-hacking&quot;&gt;working around&lt;/a&gt; it by having less communication between the compiler
  and the plugin, but the ikiwiki developers &lt;a href=&quot;http://ikiwiki.info/todo/be_more_selective_about_running_hooks/&quot;&gt;didn&#39;t really think it was a great idea&lt;/a&gt;.  So I have basically scrapped the idea of the
  plugin being external.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The nice thing about that is that it allowed me to remove a lot of
  code on the emacs side.  Instead of communication via XML-RPC, the
  new plugin can put the content to be interpreted in a file and call
  emacsclient directly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I note in &lt;code&gt;README.org&lt;/code&gt; that there is a concern about security.  This
  is because any program that calls another program with
  user-generated arguments should be concerned about security.  As far
  as I can tell, the only way that something bad can happen is if
  someone creates a filename with an unmatched double-quote and
  convinces ikiwiki to accept it.  Since ikiwiki doesn&#39;t accept
  filenames with double-quotes anyway, there really shouldn&#39;t be a
  problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, I would recommend that this plugin not be used in
  situations where untrusted people can create files (such as from the
  CGI interface), unless you personally verify that nothing bad can
  happen.  As always, this is free software and comes with no
  warranty.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Remaining todos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I would like to get rid of the potential security hole so that
  people could feel safe running this plugin from the CGI interface.
  I would also like to get rid of the hardcoded org configuration and
  let that be stored in the user&#39;s setup file.  I have a branch that
  does that using the old architecture, so it should not be too
  difficult to port to the new architecture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-5/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Hiking Philosophy</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="PCT" />

	<category term="gear" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-15T17:24:18Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-13T19:50:44Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have written an account of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./tags/AT&quot;&gt;AT hike&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I would
write down some things that I think are true about hiking before
writing about the next hike.  The first thing to note is that I
subscribe completely to the hike-your-own-hike (HYOH) philosophy, so
this should be read as descriptive more than prescriptive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, I lied.  This is the one prescription.  Read the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lnt.org/programs/principles.php&quot;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;
  and follow them.  Also follow any other rules that are in place for
  the area that you&#39;re in.  If it says not to make camp fires, then
  don&#39;t.  It&#39;s a pity to need to say this, but I&#39;ve seen experienced
  hikers break the rules (and I&#39;m not perfect either, but I do my
  best).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So much of the conversation about hiking with non-hikers or
  inexperienced hikers is about dangerous animals.  I probably saw
  less than one bear for every month of hiking that I did, and they
  were all running away from me.  I never hiked in grizzy country, and
  if I ever do, I&#39;ll think about maybe carrying bear spray, though I
  doubt I will in the end.  Wilderness is vast and bears and other
  dangerous animals are sparse.  They generally don&#39;t want anything to
  do with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most scared I was of an animal on the AT was the time I saw a
  skunk on the trail in the Shenandoahs.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m generally not an ultralighter, though I&#39;m moving more in that
  direction.  This is the gear that I used.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-1&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I love my hammock.  It&#39;s lighter than many tents, far more
   comfortable than sleeping on the ground, and you don&#39;t need to find
   a flat spot to set it up.  On the other hand, you do need to find
   suitable trees.  This is easy in a pine forest and is probably
   impossible in the plains.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-2&quot;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Not boots.  I grew to be very happy with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004C0ZOEG/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004C0ZOEG&quot;&gt;North Face Singletrack&lt;/a&gt;
   trail-running shoe.  It is a bit more rugged than a normal running
   shoe, but far less stiff and heavy than a boot.  I like my shoes to
   last at least 10 miles per dollar.  The Singletrack normally costs
   about $100 and lasts about 1000 miles, so that works out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-3&quot;&gt;Pack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I wore the same pack for both of my thru-hikes: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0034NUZ8M/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0034NUZ8M&quot;&gt;Black Diamond Infinity 60&lt;/a&gt;.  It worked well, though I came to feel that it was
   heavier than it needed to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-4&quot;&gt;Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   All synthetic.  For the AT hike, I wore the same shirt and shorts
   most of the way.  I got a new pair of shorts in Damascus, just
   because I was getting tired of the pair that I was wearing.  I
   started my AT hike with three pairs of socks and they lasted me the
   whole way.  I would generally change socks only as needed because
   they were wet or once per week during dry sections.  I carried the
   following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One short-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One long-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two pairs of underwear
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of shorts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of long pants
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three pairs of socks
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One fleece
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One rain jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One down jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;     
   On sections that I knew would be very cold, I carried a hat and
   gloves.  In the Sierras I carried wool tights as well, and there
   were nights where I wore everything that I was carrying.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-5&quot;&gt;Sleeping Bag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have a fairly generic down sleeping bag from &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt;.  Since it&#39;s
   down, I must be very careful to keep it dry.  To do this, I keep it
   in a trash bag inside its stuff sack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-6&quot;&gt;Bear canister&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   It&#39;s the law that you must carry one in the Sierras, so I did.
   They are the worst &amp;ndash; heavy and bulky, and they still don&#39;t fit as
   much food as a normal food bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-7&quot;&gt;Hiking poles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   As far as I can tell, simpler is better.  A strap is good and
   telescoping is good so that they fit in cars when hitching.  I&#39;ve
   never used poles with shock absorbers, but I really don&#39;t see how
   they would help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-8&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-8&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-8&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The main change between my hikes was my stove.  On my AT hike, I
   used a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004P78F88/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004P78F88&quot;&gt;MSR Whisperlite&lt;/a&gt; stove.  It&#39;s a great stove &amp;ndash; it puts out
   varying levels of heat and is very fuel efficient &amp;ndash; but I thought
   it was a bit heavy for one person.  So on my PCT hike, I took a
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003LDCVBY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B003LDCVBY&quot;&gt;Vargo&lt;/a&gt; titanium alcohol stove.  It was lighter, but only had one
   temperature, was more prone to accidents, was a pain to fill, and
   required more fuel.  I know that if I was going on a hike with more
   than one person, I would take the Whisperlite, but I don&#39;t know
   what I&#39;d do on another solo hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-9&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-9&quot;&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-9&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   For some hikes, they are necessary, for others emphatically not.  I
   took the &lt;a href=&quot;http://theatguide.com/&quot;&gt;AWOL guide&lt;/a&gt; on my AT hike and printed out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pctmap.net/&quot;&gt;Halfmile maps&lt;/a&gt;
   for my PCT hike.  Since the AT is so well marked, only an elevation
   profile is necessary so that you know how difficult the next
   stretch of trail will be.  On the other hand, it is important to
   have maps on the PCT because there are places where the trail is
   not obvious.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-10&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-10&quot;&gt;Bear Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-10&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have about 50 feet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parachute_cord&quot;&gt;parachute cord&lt;/a&gt; that I attach the lightest
   possible carabiner to.  I then use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qgBLDMuPuvE&quot;&gt;PCT Method&lt;/a&gt; to hang the food
   bag from the tree (with varying degrees of success).  As I noted
   earlier, I&#39;m generally not too concerned about actual bears, but
   hanging food is always a good thing, especially near established
   campsites where there is a high probability of rodents.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Packing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m a firm believer that you should always pack in a consistent
  manner.  This saves you time rooting around in your pack.  The only
  tip that I have is that the sleeping bag should go on the bottom.
  You won&#39;t need it all day, and it&#39;s nice to have something soft on
  the bottom of your pack if you put it down quickly or fall down
  backwards.  Other than that, I don&#39;t think the order matters too
  much as long as it&#39;s consistent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Both of my long hikes have been solo hikes in the sense that I made
  no explicit arrangement with anyone else to hike together.  In both
  hikes, I have had periods of being truly alone and periods where I
  would regularly meet up with the same people nearly every night.  I
  probably enjoyed myself the most when I was in groups of three or
  four, but I also think that it would be nearly impossible for me to
  stay with one single group for an entire hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The community aspect of hiking is one of its strongest
  selling-points.  You meet all kinds of people who are all doing the
  same thing as you.  So that gives you something to talk about right
  away.  Nothing bonds like shared misery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is also a strong sense that everyone is looking out for each
  other.  This was put into the starkest relief for me when I was
  hiking in the Sierras on the PCT, so I&#39;ll go into it in more detail
  when I get around to writing about that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I might write another of these more general posts about hiking later.
  I still haven&#39;t touched on things like a daily schedule or what town
  stops are like.  For now, however, I think this post has gotten long
  enough.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Georgia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ga/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/ga/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-06T18:24:58Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-06T18:24:58Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;I entered Georgia with one goal: get to Springer Mountain by my
birthday.  It&#39;s about 75 miles from the border to Springer, and I had
three and a half days, so I thought that I had a pretty good chance of
getting there on time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I needed to make one final stop in town before I got to the end for my
last resupply.  I got to the highway at about 5:00 and soon got a
hitch into Hiawassee.  67.5 miles to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Hiawassee to Springer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, back on the trail with three days of food, I took
  an early break.  I went to put my pack on, and the buckle for the
  hip belt broke!  Some people with ultralight packs can hike without
  a hip belt, but I am not one of them (though I wish I was).  For
  me, the hip belt is the thing that bears most of the weight of the
  pack and the shoulder straps are more for stabilization.  In short,
  this almost rose to the level of an emergency.  Had it been earlier
  in the trip, or if I had not set a self-imposed deadline for the end
  of the hike, I might have turned around and hiked back to the road.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There was no way I was going to do that though.  I tried hiking
  without the hip belt for a little while, but it quickly became
  obvious that that wouldn&#39;t work.  It was time for some
  out-of-the-box thinking.  I seriously considered just leaving the
  pack behind and running the rest of the way to Springer.  I know
  that people run that far in less than 24 hours all the time, and
  considering the shape I was in, I probably could have done it.
  However, leaving all my stuff in the back woods of Georgia seemed
  like something to do only as a last resort, and spending a night
  without my pack would be too awful to risk.  Finally, I realized
  that I had my rope that I used to hang my bear bag.  I cut about a
  foot from that and tied the straps of my hip belt together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Thankfully, it worked.  I soon got just as good at tying the hip
  belt together as I had been at buckling it.  It looked a little
  funny, like a person with a rope for a belt, but in the woods
  there&#39;s really no one to judge that sort of thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The terrain was hilly that day, and between that and my hip-belt
  disaster, I didn&#39;t make it that far.  I ended up on the top of Rocky
  Mountain with 52.2 miles to go and two full days of hiking left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Fortunately, the hills were less steep the next day, the weather was
  great, and I was on a roll.  With each mile that I got closer to the
  end of my journey, the better I felt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OBun7vrnzl4/TOXC8p5RC1I/AAAAAAAABPI/gWK7F1WvMdY/s800/DSCF0429.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OBun7vrnzl4/TOXC8p5RC1I/AAAAAAAABPI/gWK7F1WvMdY/s800/DSCF0429.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Near the end of the day, I came to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_Mountain&quot;&gt;Blood Mountain&lt;/a&gt;.  There is a
  shelter near the top, but it is 28.3 miles from Springer, so I kept
  on going.  I walked for about two more hours to get to a small
  campsite near a stream 22.3 miles from the finish line.  One day
  left, and within striking distance.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The final day was much like the previous 131.  I got up early, had
  breakfast and walked.  I did see a small family of wild pigs in the
  morning, but it was otherwise a day pretty much like any other.  As
  I got closer to the end, my pace picked up, and I flew past some
  day-hikers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Springer Mountain is nothing compared to &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness&quot;&gt;Katahdin&lt;/a&gt;.  I am willing to
  stipulate that much.  Some will say that makes finishing a
  southbound AT hike anticlimactic, and that is one step too far for
  me.  I had walked nearly 2200 miles in the wilderness to get there;
  it was pretty damn climactic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vasthhIyDsw/TOXDBoTkJqI/AAAAAAAABQg/2XvPPR9mj_Q/s640/DSCF0437.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vasthhIyDsw/TOXDBoTkJqI/AAAAAAAABQg/2XvPPR9mj_Q/s640/DSCF0437.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I finished on my birthday, just as I had hoped.  It really was a
  great way to spend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-oucyoSno3wE/TOXDFWGUSkI/AAAAAAAABRc/yJsPJxobONY/s800/DSCF0450.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-oucyoSno3wE/TOXDFWGUSkI/AAAAAAAABRc/yJsPJxobONY/s800/DSCF0450.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Coda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The terminus of the trail is the top of a mountain.  There is no
  road up to there &amp;ndash; to get home you must take another trail.  I
  walked about a mile down that after finishing the AT, and camped one
  last time.  I was out of fuel, so I made my only campfire of the
  entire hike and made supper over that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I hiked out the next day past &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amicalola_Falls&quot;&gt;Amicalola Falls&lt;/a&gt;.  At the end, there is
  a visitor&#39;s center, where I made sure to sign the final log book,
  and then I had to think about getting home.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-MHSIhlA5HjA/TOXDMRbU5kI/AAAAAAAAAYY/R50fqbApYss/s800/DSCF0466.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-MHSIhlA5HjA/TOXDMRbU5kI/AAAAAAAAAYY/R50fqbApYss/s800/DSCF0466.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Hitching in a tourist area is never easy, so in the end I resorted
  to asking for rides from people who wanted to talk about my hike.  A
  nice older couple gave another hiker and me a ride into Atlanta, and
  just like that I was back in civilization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  That&#39;s it for the AT, but it&#39;s less than half of my long hikes.
  Depending on my mood, I might start right in on the PCT, or I might
  go a little deeper into the gear I used and other more general
  thoughts that I have about hiking.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ga/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/ga/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Tennessee and North Carolina</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/tn-nc/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/tn-nc/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-05T21:19:25Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-05T21:19:25Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Damascus to Erwin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I had a great time in Damascus with the little crew that I had met
  up with a few days earlier, but they wanted to stay in town a little
  longer than I did, so I went on without them.  The first day out of
  town, I had a certain shelter in mind to end at, but it got dark
  before I got there and, having no desire to night-hike, I simply
  stopped in the middle of a hill and set up my hammock.  I&#39;m fairly
  sure that was one of my most random campsites.  I didn&#39;t think it
  looked any good as a campsite, but I was tired and wanted to stop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8fZ-ti3dcz4/TOXCLpKx74I/AAAAAAAABEs/hkBzRoF-np0/s800/DSCF0357.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8fZ-ti3dcz4/TOXCLpKx74I/AAAAAAAABEs/hkBzRoF-np0/s800/DSCF0357.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laurel Fork Falls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Maybe my thinking was skewed by the fact that I knew that if I could
  hike 25 miles per day for the next four days, I could stay at a
  hostel for each of them.   The first of these days took me to the
  Kincora hostel, home of Bob Peoples.  Bob is a trail maintainer in
  addition to being a hostel-keeper, and is a trail fixture.  Most of
  the graffiti in the shelters leading to his hostel consists of Chuck
  Norris-style jokes about him (all complimentary of course).  He has
  been running the hostel for over 20 years and still only charges $4
  per night.  While I was there, we sat and chatted a bit.  He told me
  about his previous hike in Europe and his plan for the next summer
  to work on the International AT in Canada, adding cairns so people
  can find their way in Newfoundland.  For an older guy (he must be
  nearly 70), he sure gets his kicks on the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-lBicNB2_kco/TOXCKDcoHUI/AAAAAAAABEY/rAERWP-mCKo/s800/DSCF0355.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-lBicNB2_kco/TOXCKDcoHUI/AAAAAAAABEY/rAERWP-mCKo/s800/DSCF0355.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The leaves by this point had all turned, and most of them were
  brown.  There were a few patches of color left, though.  For the
  most part, I was still in the &quot;tunnel&quot; of trees and branches, but
  the falling leaves gave some more opportunities to see outside it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WZ8VczQj33M/TOXCMx27zhI/AAAAAAAABFE/cLmrOJSzRwg/s800/DSCF0359.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-WZ8VczQj33M/TOXCMx27zhI/AAAAAAAABFE/cLmrOJSzRwg/s800/DSCF0359.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next night I made it to the next hostel.  This was the Mountain
  Harbour Hostel.  They have a room above a barn that is really nice,
  but unfortunately it was booked by the time that I got there.  I did
  use it to shower in and watched City Slickers (a great trail movie
  by the way) before going to bed in an RV.  It was comfortable, but
  not as neat as the barn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day started with a big climb up Hump Mountain.  It is the
  first of the &quot;balds&quot; that a southbound hiker hits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-S1hfxMHYxhA/TOXCPGGVckI/AAAAAAAABFw/-xlAKwyqRBc/s800/DSCF0366.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-S1hfxMHYxhA/TOXCPGGVckI/AAAAAAAABFw/-xlAKwyqRBc/s800/DSCF0366.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As you can see, there are no trees &amp;ndash; it is just long grass.  After
  nearly 1800 miles of nearly consistent tree cover (and alpine
  terrain on the tops of mountains), this is a welcome change.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xv4qN3hMZf0/TOXCQy1_0lI/AAAAAAAABGQ/Uu7uw2GRvfQ/s800/DSCF0370.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xv4qN3hMZf0/TOXCQy1_0lI/AAAAAAAABGQ/Uu7uw2GRvfQ/s800/DSCF0370.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually the trail goes over 6000 feet elevation at Roan High
  Knob.  There is a shelter at the top, where I am sure it gets quite
  cold at night, but I wouldn&#39;t know because I wanted to get to the
  next hostel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next hostel was not a hostel but a &quot;friendly&quot; (get it?
  hostel&amp;hellip; hostile&amp;hellip; friendly (it&#39;s not a great joke)).  The
  proprietress, who was quirky but nice, wasn&#39;t there when I arrived,
  but she left a key so that I could get situated and watch a little
  TV.  She cooked me a great breakfast the next morning and I was on
  my way to the next one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The weather that day was rainy, and I got to use the rain jacket
  that I had purchased in Virginia for the first time.  Going up some
  rather high mountains in a thunderstorm wasn&#39;t so fun, but I was on
  a mission.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-18-yC2TThzA/TOXCUUsDYDI/AAAAAAAABHE/RlzjBWtuZEA/s800/DSCF0376.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-18-yC2TThzA/TOXCUUsDYDI/AAAAAAAABHE/RlzjBWtuZEA/s800/DSCF0376.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Luckily, the rain didn&#39;t last long, and soon it was a mere memory.
  I kept pushing on and made it to Erwin, TN by mid-afternoon.  The
  hostel in Erwin had a bunch of old guys just hanging around.  I
  might have found them amusing under other circumstances, but as it
  was I just found them (and Erwin by extension) a little sad.
  I got a resupply that evening and was out early the next morning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-bNeMS0NsS-0/TOXCU1n69JI/AAAAAAAABHM/qHUwMddoRbQ/s800/DSCF0377.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-bNeMS0NsS-0/TOXCU1n69JI/AAAAAAAABHM/qHUwMddoRbQ/s800/DSCF0377.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Erwin to Gatlinburg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Out of Erwin, there is some significant climbing, and that combined
  with the threat of rain conspired to stop me after only 16 miles.
  I was glad to have stopped, because it did rain that evening and
  some the next morning as well.  Once again, the rain cleared up by
  the afternoon, and by the end of the day I was happy to be walking
  down the trail.  At the end of the day I came upon Hot Springs, NC.
  It was dark by the time I found the hostel that I had heard about.
  It is run by a Buddhist monk who makes gourmet vegetarian food.
  Naturally, I took a zero there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By this time, I had done the math and determined that I could finish
  on my birthday if I kept a decent pace.  The zero set me back a
  little bit, so from then on I needed to really push: the only thing
  in my way was the Great Smoky Mountain National Park.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I met up with Skittles again the day after I left Hot Springs.  He
  had a bit of a falling-out with the rest of the group (as I
  understood it) and had hiked ahead of them.  It was nice to be
  around someone that I knew again, but we had such radically
  different paces during the day that we were never around each other
  for very long.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day ended just inside the national park at a shelter that
  had a chain-link fence enclosing it to keep the bears out.  There
  was a group there, and after a while it became clear to me that they
  were a church group.  Skittles showed up late and he never got the
  memo.  The next morning, he went with them to the top of a mountain
  off-trail (there were a couple of pretty young ladies in the group,
  and he thought he had a chance) and only found out then.  As he told
  me, he was pretty mad when he found out and spent a couple of hours
  arguing with them about the existence of God.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I, on the other hand, went to a shelter half a mile off the trail
  and spent the night alone at a mile high.  There were bear warnings
  all over, but I didn&#39;t see one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-oSiqXRADocw/TOXCfollvCI/AAAAAAAABJc/jmQjhW8uoE0/s800/DSCF0391.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-oSiqXRADocw/TOXCfollvCI/AAAAAAAABJc/jmQjhW8uoE0/s800/DSCF0391.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I love views where the mountains seem to be stacked one behind the
  other.  The Smokies had that in abundance, and the haze in these
  photos really shows where they got their name.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-USFWqkYdXng/TOXCgu51wWI/AAAAAAAABJ0/CkG9EF1uqOo/s800/DSCF0394.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-USFWqkYdXng/TOXCgu51wWI/AAAAAAAABJ0/CkG9EF1uqOo/s800/DSCF0394.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was only about 10 miles from the road Gatlinburg, and got there
  easily by noon.  Despite the throngs of tourists, I wasn&#39;t able to
  get a hitch for over an hour (and even that was in the back of a
  pickup truck &amp;ndash; not fun for 15 miles at 60 miles per hour).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Gatlinburg is a strange place.  It&#39;s now overshadowed by Dollywood,
  but it was once the premier tourist destination in the area.  As
  such, it has everything you wouldn&#39;t expect: a Ripley&#39;s Believe it
  or Not, cable cars, a wax museum.  The only thing that isn&#39;t
  accessible in town is a grocery store.  I had to wait for a bus to
  take me out of town and back in order to resupply.  By the time I
  had gotten everything that I needed, it was getting pretty late, so
  I decided to stay in town.  The one advantage of it being such a
  touristy town is that there are many motels, and they&#39;re all pretty
  cheap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gatlinburg to the border&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I got picked up by a guy going back to the trail to do some trail
  maintenance the next day.  Soon after getting dropped off, I hit the
  highest point on the trail &amp;ndash; Clingman&#39;s Dome.  For some reason
  unknown to man, there is a completely ugly structure on top.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DoWWt_id7ug/TOXCqBMQf_I/AAAAAAAABLU/C2ebU9qnbQQ/s800/DSCF0404.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DoWWt_id7ug/TOXCqBMQf_I/AAAAAAAABLU/C2ebU9qnbQQ/s800/DSCF0404.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The hike was all relatively downhill from there&lt;a href=&quot;http://instantrimshot.com/&quot;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;  The next morning
  it snowed for the first time on the hike.  At first, this seemed
  exciting and fun, but it really was just a colder version of rain.
  I stayed at a shelter called the &quot;Fontana Hilton&quot; that night, so
  called because it&#39;s a large shelter near the Fontana Dam.  It&#39;s
  nowhere near as comfortable as a Hilton hotel, though, and it was
  packed for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was even snowier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-q0DG66O-4Fw/TOXCvSy-B6I/AAAAAAAABMg/dd4ADNAEevY/s800/DSCF0411.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-q0DG66O-4Fw/TOXCvSy-B6I/AAAAAAAABMg/dd4ADNAEevY/s800/DSCF0411.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The snow didn&#39;t slow me down too much, because I was on a mission to
  get to the Nantahala Outdoor Center.  I hit a shelter full of people
  at about 5 pm with about 7 miles left to go before I got there.  I
  didn&#39;t even hesitate about staying at the shelter.  I knew that if I
  was going to make it to the end by my birthday, I would have to do
  the miles that night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I eventually did make it to the outdoor center, after a little bit
  of night-hiking.  I am almost always against the idea of
  night-hiking, but it really is magical in the snow: everywhere that
  your headlamp hits just sparkles.  I was really glad to be inside
  that night &amp;ndash; it snowed more and got quite cold outside and I was
  snug inside.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning was still cold, so I went and bought a cap at the
  outfitter.  It was a good thing that I did too, because I was cold
  almost all of that day.  That night it got the coldest that it ever
  was on the trail.  My sleeping bag, rated at 0 C (meaning that
  I should be comfortable all the way down to that temperature) was
  really not warm enough.  I slept in all my clothes and had just my
  nose poking out the top.  It was cold.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Thankfully, that was the coldest night that I spent on the trail.
  The sun came out the next day and never went away again.  I passed
  the point where I only had 100 miles left and at that point I was
  pretty certain that I would make it.  I had 4 days left until my
  birthday, and I was also pretty certain that I would make it by
  then.  Thinking back to the beginning of my hike, that would have
  been hubris, but now that I had gotten near the end, it really was
  justified confidence.  That said, there were some tests to come, but
  no more in North Carolina, because I was almost out of there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Acn7auhOXgQ/TOXC3T_cAcI/AAAAAAAABN4/k6GNwAfjk-s/s800/DSCF0419.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Acn7auhOXgQ/TOXC3T_cAcI/AAAAAAAABN4/k6GNwAfjk-s/s800/DSCF0419.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--e9fCfWHt4E/TOXC7Gn8PBI/AAAAAAAABO4/EZwr8ffhoWw/s800/DSCF0427.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--e9fCfWHt4E/TOXC7Gn8PBI/AAAAAAAABO4/EZwr8ffhoWw/s800/DSCF0427.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final state line&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Georgia.  The last state on the trail, containing the final
  challenge for my hike.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/tn-nc/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/tn-nc/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Central and Southern Virginia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/central-va/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/central-va/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-29T19:10:24Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-29T19:10:24Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Waynesboro to Daleville&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//./posts/hiking/north-va&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned what a hard time I had in the
  Shenandoah National Park because of the rain.  In Waynesboro, I
  decided to do something about that.  I mailed my rain jacket home
  and went to an outfitters to get a new one.  I got a nice compact
  down jacket while I was at it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is a diner in town that has all-you-can-eat pancakes, so
  breakfast and lunch were taken care of.  I couldn&#39;t walk very fast
  with so much food in my stomach, though, so I didn&#39;t go far past
  Waynesboro.  At the shelter, I met Farm-a-sea, whose trail name had
  a double meaning.  He was training to become a fish farmer when he
  wasn&#39;t hiking, and he also had a sizable cache of medicinal herbs.
  He was an interesting guy though.  He would pack a dozen eggs and a
  large hunk of bacon out of town.  He had a skillet for frying them
  in, and would build a fire at every shelter and cook his supper in
  the skillet.  Really old-school stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The terrain in Virginia became hilly once again.  After the flatness
  of Pennsylvania, this took some getting used to.  Also, since
  Southern Pennsylvania, the leaves had been falling, and by Central
  Virginia, they were falling in earnest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/---71aZGG9Pw/TOXBaqs19sI/AAAAAAAAA5A/yMiEIbVmITA/s800/DSCF0279.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/---71aZGG9Pw/TOXBaqs19sI/AAAAAAAAA5A/yMiEIbVmITA/s800/DSCF0279.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was in this section that I realized that I had not packed enough
  food for the number of days that I would need if I was going to
  continue at the same average speed.  Thus, I needed to pick up my
  average mileage considerably.  I did two 30-mile days and two
  25-mile days into Daleville.  There was some interesting scenery on
  the way, including this rock formation, rather ominously named &quot;The
  Guillotine&quot;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5QG7ZkAwCsw/TOXBkYjN3vI/AAAAAAAAA7w/ToGxgOOKRSo/s800/DSCF0298.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5QG7ZkAwCsw/TOXBkYjN3vI/AAAAAAAAA7w/ToGxgOOKRSo/s800/DSCF0298.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the time I got to Daleville, I was in a pretty serious calorie
  deficit.  I went and had a big supper at a crappy Mexican
  restaurant, followed by two beers from the store in my motel room.
  I could tell midway through the second beer that it wasn&#39;t a good
  idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Daleville to Damascus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I was hung over all the next day.  However, following my experience
  from the previous week, I tried to make miles and not allow it to
  slow me down.  I didn&#39;t want to be stuck without food once again.
  Hiking with a hangover is really terrible, though, and it seemed
  like every 10 minutes I needed to sit down or bend over and try to
  vomit.  I didn&#39;t get anything out all day, but I didn&#39;t eat anything
  either, so by the end of the day I was getting hungry.  I took this
  as a good sign and ate some Teriyaki Noodles.  I couldn&#39;t keep them
  down through the night, but after I had gone into the woods to
  deposit them on the ground, I finally felt better.  However, the
  memory of that day has been enough to keep me from drinking alcohol
  ever since.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/4/4c/McAfee_Knob.jpg/1024px-McAfee_Knob.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/4/4c/McAfee_Knob.jpg/1024px-McAfee_Knob.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  
  The next days were better, though marred by bad trail maintenance
  and ragweed.  One highlight was the second-largest oak tree on the
  trail:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6sYDOs4YlL4/TOXBsVEoBOI/AAAAAAAAA9w/uI7VlAy6UmY/s800/DSCF0312.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6sYDOs4YlL4/TOXBsVEoBOI/AAAAAAAAA9w/uI7VlAy6UmY/s800/DSCF0312.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The day after that picture was taken, I ended up at The Captain&#39;s
  place, a small hostel with tenting in the yard.  The really
  interesting feature of it was that you needed to take a cable car
  across the creek to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The following day, I ended up at Pearisburg.  It is another
  spread-out town, and I had to walk a couple of miles to get to the
  store.  However, I had had a sleeping bag sent there because mine
  had been leaking feathers for quite a while, and I was able to pick
  it up, so that was nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I went to the Woods Hole hostel the next day, which was a greatly
  relaxing day.  One of the hostel-keepers teaches yoga and the other
  is a masseur (though the massages weren&#39;t free, and I didn&#39;t feel
  like getting one).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-as7GEIfL9gY/TOXB5mbZT9I/AAAAAAAABA0/VeqESiZRKfc/s800/DSCF0332.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-as7GEIfL9gY/TOXB5mbZT9I/AAAAAAAABA0/VeqESiZRKfc/s800/DSCF0332.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After Woods Hole, I really started rolling.  I did a 20-mile day the
  next day and a 34-mile day the day after that.  This took me to the
  Chestnut Knob shelter, which is a completely enclosed shelter on the
  top of a mountain.  It was windy all night, but I slept fairly
  comfortably after my long day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next two days weren&#39;t too special.  I stayed in a motel near the
  interstate and a shelter that was reportedly haunted (though I saw
  no evidence of a haunting).  The day after that, though I entered
  the Grayson Highlands State Park.  This is a park that is famous for
  the wild ponies that roam it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pi9paLjIp4w/TOXCC-zwgTI/AAAAAAAABCw/2s80vuVgMmk/s800/DSCF0345.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pi9paLjIp4w/TOXCC-zwgTI/AAAAAAAABCw/2s80vuVgMmk/s800/DSCF0345.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got a picture with me near them that shows how small they really
  are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-W6OOfZuUnlM/TOXCD941S_I/AAAAAAAABDE/I7ZbXLwWgY4/s800/DSCF0347.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-W6OOfZuUnlM/TOXCD941S_I/AAAAAAAABDE/I7ZbXLwWgY4/s800/DSCF0347.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I had heard that they will come up to you and lick or chew your pack
  in order to get the salt from your sweat, but that didn&#39;t happen to
  me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Just before I got to the Grayson Highlands, I met up with another
  group of hikers: Skittles, Flora, Abear, and Coyote.  I had been
  following most of them in the shelter logs for months, so it was
  like meeting old friends.  Flora in particular signed her name with
  a large flower (her hiking partner Fauna had left near Washington,
  DC), so her entries were hard to miss.  We hiked together off and on
  for a few days, and it was nice to be hiking with people once again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We all stopped together in Damascus, VA and found cheap
  accommodation in a building run by a local church.  It was empty,
  but it had strict rules (no cooking in the rooms was the one they
  seemed most concerned with) and a person came during the night to
  make sure that we were following them.  I found a new pair of shoes
  on sale in Damascus, so I got them and got rid of my previous pair
  which were falling apart.  They had only lasted about 500 miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I left Damascus early the next day, leaving the group behind.
  Skittles would catch up with me and we would hike together a bit
  longer, but I didn&#39;t see the rest again.  Just past Damascus, I left
  Virginia for Tennessee.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hwZeFpMUAJk/TOXCIxbQ-3I/AAAAAAAABEI/DC0DPcb6umI/s800/DSCF0353.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hwZeFpMUAJk/TOXCIxbQ-3I/AAAAAAAABEI/DC0DPcb6umI/s800/DSCF0353.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Tennessee and North Carolina.  A run of four straight hostels, and
  the weather finally turning cold.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/central-va/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/central-va/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>4-State and Northern Virginia</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/north-va/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/north-va/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-02-29T03:08:36Z</updated>
	<published>2012-02-29T03:08:36Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/north-va/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/north-va/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
