<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged thrush</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/thrush/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/thrush/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/thrush/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-11-15T22:18:05Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>luhnybin</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/luhnybin/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/luhnybin/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="programming-challenge" />

	<category term="thrush" />


	<updated>2011-11-15T22:18:05Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-15T20:22:19Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Another programming challenge &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I woke up with another programming challenge in my inbox this
  morning.  This one is from &lt;a href=&quot;http://squareup.com&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/a&gt;.  They are a company that gives
  you a little device so that you can accept credit cards using a
  smart phone.  The challenge is &lt;a href=&quot;http://corner.squareup.com/2011/11/luhny-bin.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; basically it&#39;s about removing
  credit cards numbers from logs.  There are some details about what
  constitutes a credit card number, and how they are distinct from
  other numbers.  I won&#39;t repeat that here, but you should read it to
  understand what&#39;s coming up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As usual, I implemented my solution in Clojure.  I particularly
  liked the function I called &lt;code&gt;luhn-check&lt;/code&gt;.  Here it is:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defn luhn-check
  &lt;span&gt;&quot;Takes a sequence of digits and determines whether they pass the Luhn test.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;   The sequence must be in order from right to left.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  [digits]
  (-&amp;gt;&amp;gt; digits
       (partition 2 2 (repeat 0))
       (mapcat #(vector (first %) (* 2 (second %))))
       (reduce #(+ %1 (int (/ %2 10)) (int (mod %2 10))))
       (#(mod % 10))
       (= 0)))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  I think this is a good illustration of the &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; operator in
  Clojure, which is also called the &quot;thrush&quot; operator.  Basically,
  this operator can be thought of as taking the result from one
  expression and putting it at the end of the next expression.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In this case, we start out with a list of digits.  We then partition
  them into pairs, padding with a zero if necessary.  We then take the
  pairs and double the second number in the pair, concatenating all
  the pairs back into a single list.  We then sum up all the digits in
  the list, using the &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; function.  This leaves us with a
  number.  We get its value \(\mod 10\) and test whether it is equal
  to zero.  If it is, we return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, otherwise we return &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  All of this could be written with nested expressions (and the thrush
  operator is simply a macro that rewrites what you see as nested
  expressions), but I think the way it is written nicely shows what
  the data is doing in the function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, I don&#39;t know if this solution will get me a job, but it was
  a bit of fun coding and didn&#39;t take too long.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/luhnybin/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/luhnybin/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
