<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" >
<channel>
<title>pages tagged processing</title>
<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/processing/</link>
<description>Hiking and Coding</description>
<item>

	<title>Processing</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/processing/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/processing/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>processing</category>

	<category>visibility-polygon</category>


	<pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 12:29:29 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-12-01T07:45:19Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Viewing visibility polygons &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I mentioned yesterday that it would be nice to see the output of my
  visibility polygon solution.  To that end, I created an extremely
  simple drawing editor using &lt;a href=&quot;http://processing.org/&quot;&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt;.  I have to say, I loved it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most important feature to me is the extreme interactivity.  I
  can change functions extremely quickly with my tools &amp;ndash; redefining a
  Clojure function is either one or two keystrokes in emacs, depending
  how I choose to do it &amp;ndash; so I like a graphics environment that
  changes just as quickly.  This is what Processing, and in particular
  &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;, offers.  I was able to define a function that
  draws the various objects (in this case, the polygon, the point
  where the mouse is, and the visibility polygon of the mouse point
  inside the polygon).  If I wanted to make any changes to this
  function &amp;ndash; for example, changing the color of the point where the
  mouse is &amp;ndash; I can simply redefine the function using my emacs tools
  and the change shows up immediately on the drawing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was able to use this to find a couple of minor bugs in my
  visibility-polygon-finding code, but in general, it worked really
  well on the first try.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-1&quot;&gt;Shortcomings &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   There were a couple of things that slightly bothered me about
   &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;.  First, it used quite a lot of CPU just to
   display a simple polygon without too many points.  I am probably
   using it rather naïvely, so it is possible that this is my problem
   and not the problem of &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;.  However, the second
   problem is just that &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt; is showing its age.  I think
   it was probably one of the first Clojure libraries out there and
   much of the coding style hasn&#39;t evolved with the Clojure best
   practices that people use.  For example, some of the features do
   not work if you only &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; the library &amp;ndash; you must &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; it.  I
   try to only &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; libraries, to avoid my namespace becoming
   overly populated, so it is frustrating when that doesn&#39;t work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Going forward &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I need to clean up the code a bit before I can put it up on github,
  but it should be there soon.  It currently needs me to explicitly
  call the function in order to find the visibility polygon.  I would
  really like it to find the visibility polygon of any point where the
  mouse is inside the polygon.  However, determining if a point is
  inside a non-convex polygon tends to be a bit harder than it
  sounds.  You can shoot a ray in one direction from a point, and
  count the number of polygon edges that it crosses &amp;ndash; if it&#39;s even
  you are outside and if it&#39;s odd you are inside &amp;ndash; but what happens
  if the ray crosses a vertex?  There was a good experimental paper on
  this problem at a recent EuroCG.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So that&#39;s a slightly non-trivial problem.  I also coded an
  implementation of the Voronoi Diagram problem recently.  I should
  add a Processing UI to that as well.  I have a feeling that would be
  the easier task to do next, and I would surely discover some bugs in
  it while I did.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/processing/#comments</comments>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
