<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged gear</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/gear/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/gear/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/gear/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111107">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-03-14T04:52:20Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Hiking Philosophy</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="PCT" />

	<category term="gear" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-03-14T04:52:20Z</updated>
	<published>2012-03-13T19:50:44Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have written an account of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/gear/./../AT&quot;&gt;AT hike&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I would
write down some things that I think are true about hiking before
writing about the next hike.  The first thing to note is that I
subscribe completely to the hike-your-own-hike (HYOH) philosophy, so
this should be read as descriptive more than prescriptive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, I lied.  This is the one prescription.  Read the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lnt.org/programs/principles.php&quot;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;
  and follow them.  Also follow any other rules that are in place for
  the area that you&#39;re in.  If it says not to make camp fires, then
  don&#39;t.  It&#39;s a pity to need to say this, but I&#39;ve seen experienced
  hikers break the rules (and I&#39;m not perfect either, but I do my
  best).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So much of the conversation about hiking with non-hikers or
  inexperienced hikers is about dangerous animals.  I probably saw
  less than one bear for every month of hiking that I did, and they
  were all running away from me.  I never hiked in grizzy country, and
  if I ever do, I&#39;ll think about maybe carrying bear spray, though I
  doubt I will in the end.  Wilderness is vast and bears and other
  dangerous animals are sparse.  They generally don&#39;t want anything to
  do with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most scared I was of an animal on the AT was the time I saw a
  skunk on the trail in the Shenandoahs.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m generally not an ultralighter, though I&#39;m moving more in that
  direction.  This is the gear that I used.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-1&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I love my hammock.  It&#39;s lighter than many tents, far more
   comfortable than sleeping on the ground, and you don&#39;t need to find
   a flat spot to set it up.  On the other hand, you do need to find
   suitable trees.  This is easy in a pine forest and is probably
   impossible in the plains.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-2&quot;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Not boots.  I grew to be very happy with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004C0ZOEG/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004C0ZOEG&quot;&gt;North Face Singletrack&lt;/a&gt;
   trail-running shoe.  It is a bit more rugged than a normal running
   shoe, but far less stiff and heavy than a boot.  I like my shoes to
   last at least 10 miles per dollar.  The Singletrack normally costs
   about $100 and lasts about 1000 miles, so that works out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-3&quot;&gt;Pack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I wore the same pack for both of my thru-hikes: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0034NUZ8M/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0034NUZ8M&quot;&gt;Black Diamond Infinity 60&lt;/a&gt;.  It worked well, though I came to feel that it was
   heavier than it needed to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-4&quot;&gt;Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   All synthetic.  For the AT hike, I wore the same shirt and shorts
   most of the way.  I got a new pair of shorts in Damascus, just
   because I was getting tired of the pair that I was wearing.  I
   started my AT hike with three pairs of socks and they lasted me the
   whole way.  I would generally change socks only as needed because
   they were wet or once per week during dry sections.  I carried the
   following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One short-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One long-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two pairs of underwear
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of shorts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of long pants
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three pairs of socks
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One fleece
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One rain jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One down jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;     
   On sections that I knew would be very cold, I carried a hat and
   gloves.  In the Sierras I carried wool tights as well, and there
   were nights where I wore everything that I was carrying.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-5&quot;&gt;Sleeping Bag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have a fairly generic down sleeping bag from &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt;.  Since it&#39;s
   down, I must be very careful to keep it dry.  To do this, I keep it
   in a trash bag inside its stuff sack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-6&quot;&gt;Bear canister&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   It&#39;s the law that you must carry one in the Sierras, so I did.
   They are the worst &amp;ndash; heavy and bulky, and they still don&#39;t fit as
   much food as a normal food bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-7&quot;&gt;Hiking poles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   As far as I can tell, simpler is better.  A strap is good and
   telescoping is good so that they fit in cars when hitching.  I&#39;ve
   never used poles with shock absorbers, but I really don&#39;t see how
   they would help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-8&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-8&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-8&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The main change between my hikes was my stove.  On my AT hike, I
   used a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004P78F88/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004P78F88&quot;&gt;MSR Whisperlite&lt;/a&gt; stove.  It&#39;s a great stove &amp;ndash; it puts out
   varying levels of heat and is very fuel efficient &amp;ndash; but I thought
   it was a bit heavy for one person.  So on my PCT hike, I took a
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003LDCVBY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B003LDCVBY&quot;&gt;Vargo&lt;/a&gt; titanium alcohol stove.  It was lighter, but only had one
   temperature, was more prone to accidents, was a pain to fill, and
   required more fuel.  I know that if I was going on a hike with more
   than one person, I would take the Whisperlite, but I don&#39;t know
   what I&#39;d do on another solo hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-9&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-9&quot;&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-9&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   For some hikes, they are necessary, for others emphatically not.  I
   took the &lt;a href=&quot;http://theatguide.com/&quot;&gt;AWOL guide&lt;/a&gt; on my AT hike and printed out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pctmap.net/&quot;&gt;Halfmile maps&lt;/a&gt;
   for my PCT hike.  Since the AT is so well marked, only an elevation
   profile is necessary so that you know how difficult the next
   stretch of trail will be.  On the other hand, it is important to
   have maps on the PCT because there are places where the trail is
   not obvious.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-10&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-10&quot;&gt;Bear Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-10&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have about 50 feet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parachute_cord&quot;&gt;parachute cord&lt;/a&gt; that I attach the lightest
   possible carabiner to.  I then use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qgBLDMuPuvE&quot;&gt;PCT Method&lt;/a&gt; to hang the food
   bag from the tree (with varying degrees of success).  As I noted
   earlier, I&#39;m generally not too concerned about actual bears, but
   hanging food is always a good thing, especially near established
   campsites where there is a high probability of rodents.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Packing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m a firm believer that you should always pack in a consistent
  manner.  This saves you time rooting around in your pack.  The only
  tip that I have is that the sleeping bag should go on the bottom.
  You won&#39;t need it all day, and it&#39;s nice to have something soft on
  the bottom of your pack if you put it down quickly or fall down
  backwards.  Other than that, I don&#39;t think the order matters too
  much as long as it&#39;s consistent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Both of my long hikes have been solo hikes in the sense that I made
  no explicit arrangement with anyone else to hike together.  In both
  hikes, I have had periods of being truly alone and periods where I
  would regularly meet up with the same people nearly every night.  I
  probably enjoyed myself the most when I was in groups of three or
  four, but I also think that it would be nearly impossible for me to
  stay with one single group for an entire hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The community aspect of hiking is one of its strongest
  selling-points.  You meet all kinds of people who are all doing the
  same thing as you.  So that gives you something to talk about right
  away.  Nothing bonds like shared misery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is also a strong sense that everyone is looking out for each
  other.  This was put into the starkest relief for me when I was
  hiking in the Sierras on the PCT, so I&#39;ll go into it in more detail
  when I get around to writing about that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I might write another of these more general posts about hiking later.
  I still haven&#39;t touched on things like a daily schedule or what town
  stops are like.  For now, however, I think this post has gotten long
  enough.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/philosophy/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
