<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged AT</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111107">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2012-01-07T18:00:54Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Vermont</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/vermont/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/vermont/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-07T18:00:54Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-07T18:00:54Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Hanover to Rutland &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After an enjoyable two days in Hanover, it was time to hit the road
  again.  Unfortunately, the first few miles of the trail in Vermont
  are actually on road.  Road walks are bad for a hiker for a few
  reasons.  For one thing, you are taken out of the wilderness
  experience whenever you see the road.  For another, the hard surface
  tends to hurt your feet far more quickly than trail.  While there
  were times during the hike that I was glad to be walking on road
  (mainly after hiking the rocky trails of Pennsylvania), a good trail
  is almost always preferable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Rain started around lunch time, and by the time I arrived at the
  shelter, it was a downpour.  I was still not comfortable sleeping in
  shelters at this point of the hike, so I set up my hammock anyway.
  However, I went to the shelter to cook supper and found that
  sleeping there would not have been an option anyway.  It was full of
  northbounders &amp;ndash; roughly the end of the wave of northbounders that
  happens every year on the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The rain brought out some red efts from their hiding places.  These
  are juvenile newts that look somewhat like plastic toys.  I was
  never able to get a great photo of them, but this is one of the
  better ones:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6OUn7JW_nvg/TOXAji1HJ3I/AAAAAAAAAro/kQFlcuIKLdo/s800/DSCF0156.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6OUn7JW_nvg/TOXAji1HJ3I/AAAAAAAAAro/kQFlcuIKLdo/s800/DSCF0156.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The weather was better the next day, and I made good time.  During
  the day, I met up with Just Jill, who had been staying at the same
  shelter as me.  (Just X is a common trail name for people named X
  who can&#39;t decide on a trail name.)  She had started the trail much
  earlier than me, but had family near Hanover and was just getting
  back on the trail.  We chatted a bit about people that I only knew
  from reading log books at shelters and then went on.  Late in the
  day, I got some pretty bad chafing from the previous day&#39;s moisture
  and had to knock off before I got to my intended destination.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The following day was only notable because it marked the junction of
  the AT with the Long Trail, the oldest long-distance hiking trail in
  the US.  I caught up with Just Jill again at the end of the day, at
  a shelter near the top of Mount Killington.  We agreed that we would
  get up early the next day to go to the top and take pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I did get up early the next morning, but didn&#39;t wake Just Jill.
  However, I did get some very nice pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jGaLyra_81k/TOXAkAmvm5I/AAAAAAAAArw/BfmkXk7lStw/s800/DSCF0157.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jGaLyra_81k/TOXAkAmvm5I/AAAAAAAAArw/BfmkXk7lStw/s800/DSCF0157.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ZPfRLM6pUFI/TOXAk8yLnLI/AAAAAAAAAsI/KPbC3EpHhRk/s800/DSCF0159.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ZPfRLM6pUFI/TOXAk8yLnLI/AAAAAAAAAsI/KPbC3EpHhRk/s800/DSCF0159.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-X17lFoOGdco/TOXAmAaKhOI/AAAAAAAAAsc/rj7vIirb0CQ/s800/DSCF0161.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-X17lFoOGdco/TOXAmAaKhOI/AAAAAAAAAsc/rj7vIirb0CQ/s800/DSCF0161.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-HzKRZl8eawk/TOXAnuCWEvI/AAAAAAAAAsk/C1dk_d9CMKY/s800/DSCF0162.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-HzKRZl8eawk/TOXAnuCWEvI/AAAAAAAAAsk/C1dk_d9CMKY/s800/DSCF0162.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  From there, the day was all downhill (literally, not
  metaphorically).  I crossed 500 miles and saw an owl.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-snHnV4Ge7vs/TOXAtm7sfuI/AAAAAAAAAJ8/xK14j7xlUHI/s640/DSCF0178.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-snHnV4Ge7vs/TOXAtm7sfuI/AAAAAAAAAJ8/xK14j7xlUHI/s640/DSCF0178.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That night, I got to a road and decided to go to Rutland, VT.  My
  sister was playing in a musical competition that weekend, and I was
  able to take the train up to Montreal to see her.  But not before I
  stayed at a hostel run by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twelvetribes.com/&quot;&gt;Twelve Tribes&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; a sort of religious
  commune that some characterize as a cult, but who were very nice to
  me.  And they had great food and smoothies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Rutland to the Massachusetts border &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After the trip to Montreal, I was back to Rutland to start where I
  left off.  Since I got back to the trail late in the evening, I only
  walked to the first shelter a couple of miles down the trail.  I saw
  in the log book that Picker and Grinner had been there the day
  before, meaning that they were now ahead of me (I had been ahead of
  them since we split up at the beginning of the Whites).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was so excited at the prospect of catching back up with Picker and
  Grinner that I woke up at about 3:30 the next morning and, since I
  couldn&#39;t get back to sleep, I packed up and started walking.  I was
  undeterred by darkness, hills, rain, lightning, and trail re-routes
  and just kept walking all day.  Later in the day, after I had walked
  at least 20 miles, I started hearing about &quot;the best hostel on the
  trail&quot;.  I decided to make that my destination, even though it was
  another 10 miles or so.  I borrowed a mobile phone and called ahead
  to reserve a bunk.  I asked whether Picker and Grinner were there,
  and was given even more motivation to keep going when I found out
  that they were.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The last few miles of the day were down a ski run, and when I got to
  the bottom I was just about as tired as I&#39;d ever been.  However, I
  did my shopping and waited to get picked up by the guy who runs the
  hostel.  When I got to the hostel, it was as nice as it had been
  hyped to be.  It was clean and had trail memorabilia decorating the
  whole place.  On top of that, you get a pint of Ben &amp;amp; Jerry&#39;s ice
  cream as part of the low fee for staying there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Besides Picker and Grinner, there were two other couples staying at
  the hostel &amp;ndash; Lucky and Charm as well as Sherpa and Boss Lady. One
  fun way we passed the time that evening was to have everyone weigh
  their packs.  As you might expect, Sherpa&#39;s pack weight more than
  Boss Lady&#39;s, but Charm was a bit miffed to find out that her pack
  weighed at least 10 pounds more than Lucky&#39;s.  Plus, she was
  carrying a big camera, as she was (is?) an aspiring photographer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, I was rather sore, but after the effort that I had put
  in to catch Picker and Grinner, I was not going to sit around and
  let them get ahead of me again.  Thankfully, they didn&#39;t want to go
  too far either, so we found a nice river about ten miles down the
  trail and set up an early camp.  I hung up a bear bag comically low
  to the ground, and people took pictures standing next to it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t remember much from the next day, but the day after that we
  went to Bennington, VT to resupply.  It was there where we had our
  easiest hitch &amp;ndash; before we even stuck our thumbs out, an old gent
  pulled over and offered us a ride back to the trail.  He was an
  entertaining guy &amp;ndash; a veteran from the Korean War who was going
  skydiving for his eightieth birthday the following week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We slept near a shelter that night where there was a gaggle of
  northbounders, some of whom were roasting marshmallows over a camp
  fire (neither of which is a common occurrence for me &amp;ndash; I&#39;m usually
  too tired to have a camp fire at the end of the day, and
  marshmallows just waste space in the pack, but they sure were tasty
  that night), and I joined them for a little while.  One of them had
  a violin and was trying to learn to play as she was on her hike, so
  I borrowed it and played a little.  All in all, it was a great day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  That night, it rained, and a dead branch fell near Picker and
  Grinner&#39;s tent &amp;ndash; a good reminder that Mother Nature doesn&#39;t care if
  you just had a great day; she&#39;ll still try to mess it up for you.
  Luckily, though, no one was hurt.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning, we made it to the border and completed our third
  state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XLsTa1Hkwh0/TOXAvzWt-gI/AAAAAAAAAuk/4_CndnzBvV8/s800/DSCF0195.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XLsTa1Hkwh0/TOXAvzWt-gI/AAAAAAAAAuk/4_CndnzBvV8/s800/DSCF0195.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Massachusetts, flat and short.  Also large parties of college kids
  on orientation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/vermont/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/vermont/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Southern New Hampshire</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-05T18:32:06Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-05T18:28:43Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, my Disqus commenting system isn&#39;t letting me reply to
comments, so I&#39;ll start by answering the question that Björn asked
yesterday.  The question was about how the hut croos know if you&#39;re a
thru-hiker (or at least aspiring thru-hiker).  The answer is that they
must take your word for it.  There are some obvious signs, though.
First, thru-hikers have much larger packs than most other hikers in
the Whites, and are generally bearded by the time they get there.  The
vast majority have a trail guide sticking out of their pack, and their
pack will be really well-organized; they will know where everything is
inside it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But that does bring up a bigger question: what &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a thru-hiker?  Bar
Man, who I introduced yesterday, probably wouldn&#39;t fit any definition
(though he did get work-for-stay at every hut in the Whites), since he
was not actually hiking the length of the trail that year.  The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.appalachiantrail.org/hiking/thru-section-hiking&quot;&gt;ATC&lt;/a&gt;
defines a thru-hiker as someone who walks or is attempting to walk the
entire AT in one uninterrupted journey.  This seems reasonable to me:
it doesn&#39;t exclude people who hike the entire trail in sections as
long as their hike is uninterrupted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Ethan Pond to Mt. Moosilauke &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  From Ethan Pond, it was a relatively easy jaunt to Zealand Falls
  hut, where I once again went in to take a rest.  I tried to
  emphasize that I was a real thru-hiker in hopes of getting some
  leftovers, but the croo were busy and paid no attention.  I noticed
  a small boy with thick glasses at the hut.  He was awkwardly trying
  to walk with an unscrewed Camelbak full of water between his legs,
  and I immediately pegged him as a city kid who probably shouldn&#39;t be
  in the mountains.  Sure enough, I hadn&#39;t gone more than a quarter of
  a mile from the hut before I saw his dad consoling him after he had
  taken a hard fall.  As I walked on, I heard him yell, &quot;I hate stupid
  hiking!&quot; at the top of his lungs.  Whenever I was having a rough
  day, I would think back to this kid and know I had had it a lot
  better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The rest of the day was not too eventful.  I was lucky to see a few
  groups of Boy Scouts just before I would have gone to the shelter
  that was my destination for the day, so I stopped just before the
  shelter and set up camp.  Even though I was more than a quarter mile
  from the shelter, I could still hear them late into the night, but
  at least they were a bit more quiet than if I had been right there
  with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was up and over Mt. Garfield, another extremely steep
  mountain.  Thankfully, the trail up Garfield is just beside a
  waterfall and the waterfall is not the same as the trail, as it
  would be in Southern Maine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  From the next mountain, Mt. Lafayette, it is possible to see
  Greenleaf Hut, but since it is over a mile away, I did not go down
  to it.  Mt. Lafayette also had the most &quot;false summits&quot; of any
  mountain on the trail that I can remember.  I would think that I was
  getting to the top, and then there would be more climbing.  It&#39;s
  quite a frustrating thing.  However, the clouds that day made the
  view quite nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xnIhPV2GV34/TOXAZ41C5lI/AAAAAAAAApY/wxHoxT8l1QM/s800/DSCF0137.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xnIhPV2GV34/TOXAZ41C5lI/AAAAAAAAApY/wxHoxT8l1QM/s800/DSCF0137.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Mt. Lafayette is also the last mountain over 5000 feet for quite a
  while.  The knowledge of this probably made the descent down to
  Franconia Notch a little easier.  When I got there, I was presented
  with a confusing set of roads.  It was here that I almost got
  arrested.  I was trying to hitchhike into town, but somehow I walked
  to the interstate rather than the state highway.  I had my thumb out
  for a while and was disappointed that everyone was driving so fast,
  when I saw a car slow down coming my direction.  Too late did I see
  the lights on the top of the car.  It was a state trooper, and he
  simply yelled out the window &quot;I WILL ARREST YOU.&quot;  Needless to say,
  I got off the road pretty quickly.  However, I was so shaken up by
  the experience that I walked the wrong direction down the trail for
  about a half an hour before I realized my mistake, and had to turn
  around to get back to the state highway.  Finally I got a hitch, and
  was able to resupply in Lincoln, NH.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was back on the trail the next day, but didn&#39;t go far.  I stayed
  at the Kinsman Pond campsite, and I even had to pay for the
  privilege.  I&#39;m pretty sure that was the only time I paid to camp.
  I woke up the next day knowing that there were only two more real
  mountains in the Whites.  The first, Kinsman Mountain, was pretty
  tough in the morning, but it had this nice stream at the base of the
  other side.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-g1bvbE4YSvg/TOXAbjXiOWI/AAAAAAAAAps/FUYWTjxeJx8/s800/DSCF0141.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-g1bvbE4YSvg/TOXAbjXiOWI/AAAAAAAAAps/FUYWTjxeJx8/s800/DSCF0141.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YNuo_AGTX-s/TOXAe-aKNOI/AAAAAAAAAqU/Q_FdR84Ap3s/s800/DSCF0146.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YNuo_AGTX-s/TOXAe-aKNOI/AAAAAAAAAqU/Q_FdR84Ap3s/s800/DSCF0146.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After I was past the shelter on the other side, where I had a snack,
  I pushed pretty hard toward the next mountain: Mt. Moosilauke.
  There is a long flattish section between the two mountains, so I
  thought I might be able to make it up that night.  Unfortunately,
  Mt. Moosilauke is so steep (there are long sections where iron bars
  are embedded into the rock so that you have hand- and foot-holds)
  that I just didn&#39;t feel safe doing it.  I set up my hammock and
  waited for night to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-e6b-KBq6z7Q/TOXAfy9N68I/AAAAAAAADW4/V4JrX0b67M4/s800/DSCF0149.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-e6b-KBq6z7Q/TOXAfy9N68I/AAAAAAAADW4/V4JrX0b67M4/s800/DSCF0149.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  You can&#39;t really tell from that picture, but my hammock is nearly
  above a cliff.  I had to be extra-careful where I put my shoes that
  night so that they wouldn&#39;t roll down the mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I awoke the next morning and made quick work of the rest of the
  mountain.  I was so glad to get to the top, because it really meant
  the end of the hard stuff.  The Whites don&#39;t officially end for
  another 15 miles or so, but Moosilauke is the end of any really
  tough hiking in them.  I flew down the other side of the mountain --
  even running in places &amp;ndash; I was just so glad that the hard hiking
  was done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-OiOES6B_0YY/TOXAgN2icuI/AAAAAAAAAqo/93YDEfPdwNM/s640/DSCF0150.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-OiOES6B_0YY/TOXAgN2icuI/AAAAAAAAAqo/93YDEfPdwNM/s640/DSCF0150.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I stopped in at a small hostel in Glencliff, NH, but decided it
  didn&#39;t look very nice, so I kept going.  By the time the day was
  over, I was nearly out of the Whites.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The trail to Hanover &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After the hard hiking in the Whites, I started focusing on getting
  my mileage up.  After all, I had been hiking for over a month, and
  was only done about 20% of the trail.  At this rate, it would take
  nearly half a year.  So the first day out, I did over twenty miles.
  There were a few mountains, but I remember thinking they were
  nothing.  When I met northbounders, I was the one who could afford
  to be a bit smug.  They may have walked farther than me, but I had
  been through the hard mountains and survived.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, however, I got to Hanover, NH.  It&#39;s a beautiful
  university town, with Dartmouth University as its centerpiece.  I
  needed to resupply and get cleaned up, so I decided to stay.
  Unfortunately, I arrived on a Saturday and did not get my cleaning
  done.  The next day, the only public laundry was closed, so I had to
  stay another day as well.  It slowed me down a bit, but I was able
  to meet up with some other hikers, and we had a great time.
  Dartmouth was having some sort of orientation for new students, and
  we snuck into some of their barbecues.  There was even a fraternity
  which let me sleep in their basement for free, although they did
  have a big party the night that I slept there, which kept me up
  until far too late.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Vermont is just across the river from Hanover.  I don&#39;t remember too
  much about it.  Will I be able to recap it in one post?  Probably not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-2/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>North New Hampshire</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2012-01-05T01:02:45Z</updated>
	<published>2012-01-05T01:02:45Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;The Whites &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  As a southbound hiker on the Appalachian Trail, you hear about the
  White Mountains from nearly the first day.  They are reputed to be
  the Real Test &amp;ndash; if you can make it past them, you can do anything.
  However, once you get to them, you have made it past &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/./../../posts/hiking/southern-maine&quot;&gt;Southern Maine&lt;/a&gt;,
  and you know you can do anything anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  To be honest, though, the Whites are a real challenge, and present a
  few peculiarities when compared with the rest of the trail.  First,
  there are real buildings (unlike the shelters on the rest of the
  trail which generally only have 3 walls).  These are known as
  &quot;huts&quot;, but they&#39;re pretty nice.  Thru-hikers are allowed to stay at
  them if they do a night&#39;s work, but they cost about $100 per night
  for everyone else.  Also, there are many areas where camping is
  strictly forbidden, or where there is a fee to camp.  This seemed a
  bit of a hassle, given the fact that I had been sleeping pretty much
  wherever I wanted for the past month.  However, it&#39;s a high-use
  area, so I can understand the reasons behind the restrictions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Leaving Gorham &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Picker, Grinner, and I spent a nice day-and-a-half in Gorham despite
  a rather funny meal at a Mexican (perhaps that needs scare quotes)
  restaurant.  &quot;What kind of beers do you have?&quot;  &quot;Oh lots, just name
  one.&quot;  &quot;Okay, I&#39;ll have a Long Trail.&quot;  &quot;I don&#39;t think we have
  that.&quot;  &quot;How about a Dos Equis?&quot; &quot;Nope.&quot; &quot;Maybe you should tell us
  what you have.&quot;  &quot;We have Bud, Miller, and Miller Light.&quot;  &quot;I think
  I&#39;ll stick with water.&quot;  And it went downhill from there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first two miles out of Gorham have beautiful pine trees and a
  really easy grade.  They are probably the easiest two miles in New
  Hampshire.  After this, we started going straight up again until we
  finally got over Mount Moriah.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-fcAHof8WGPI/TOXAA_XLE2I/AAAAAAAAAlA/RlqDwELfFW0/s800/DSCF0109.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-fcAHof8WGPI/TOXAA_XLE2I/AAAAAAAAAlA/RlqDwELfFW0/s800/DSCF0109.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We got to a really nice shelter right at lunch time, and to my
  surprise Grinner wanted to stop for the day.  I really wanted to go
  on, so after an hour of discussing the situation, I decided to go on
  by myself.  I was a little scared because I had been with Picker and
  Grinner the whole way to that point, but I also knew that it might
  be a good idea, since I could be sure that I was going my own pace
  and not hurrying to stay up with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I walked about 5 more miles, not finding a camp spot (which was the
  reason that Grinner had wanted to stop), before finding a place to
  camp that was just outside the first big no-camping zone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next morning was up and over Carter Dome and then down to Carter
  Notch Hut.  This was the first hut that I encountered, and gave me a
  good first impression of the huts.  The croo (as the workers at the
  hut are known) was extremely welcoming and when they found out that
  I was a thru-hiker gave me some left-overs from the morning&#39;s
  breakfast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After my short stop, I pushed on, up the Wildcat Ridge.  This is a
  short mountain range with a ski area on one of the mountains.  I
  stopped at a gondola and did a little people-watching while I ate
  lunch.  After lunch, it was time for a knee-busting descent down to
  Pinkham Notch, which has a nice little interpretive center, where I
  think I got an ice-cream sandwich.  (Thinking back on this, I guess
  I was getting plenty of food in this section of the hike).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next four miles after Pinkham Notch were not too hard, but it
  was getting a bit late by the time I got to my final destination of
  the day &amp;ndash; Osgood Tent Site.  Bears are apparently a problem at this
  particular camp spot, so it was nice that they provided bear boxes
  to store our food.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Mounts Madison and Washington &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The climb from Osgood Tent Site the next morning is one of the
  longest and steepest on the trail.  The trail climbs 2866 feet over
  2.8 miles &amp;ndash; a 20% grade that just goes on and on.  Normally, when I
  got above tree line I was really happy because that meant that the
  climb was nearly over.  On this climb, it lasted for at least
  another hour.  I was lucky with the weather, though, and got some
  nice pictures.  Here is one of Mt. Washington, as seen from
  Mt. Madison.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-WWUwef9kwv8/TOXABgBmiII/AAAAAAAAAlM/h8NTmohWZ_E/s800/DSCF0110.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-WWUwef9kwv8/TOXABgBmiII/AAAAAAAAAlM/h8NTmohWZ_E/s800/DSCF0110.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  You can see the cloud on top of Mt. Washington (as well as the road
  up it).  That is a nearly-permanent feature of the place that
  advertises itself as having the worst weather on Earth.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Here is a picture that is a bit more representative of the trail
  going up Mt. Madison: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Iur5kQyy8yo/TOXAFEFvQvI/AAAAAAAAAmA/9owJuOEwmh0/s800/DSCF0115.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Iur5kQyy8yo/TOXAFEFvQvI/AAAAAAAAAmA/9owJuOEwmh0/s800/DSCF0115.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It is all large granite rocks, and the trail is marked by cairns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the time I had gotten to the top, I was really pretty tired, and
  I&#39;d only been going for a couple of hours.  Plus, the wind was
  beating fairly fiercely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-a6mx1BhBkcM/TOXAHkMGwnI/AAAAAAAAAmo/SK1dESLoYSU/s800/DSCF0119.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-a6mx1BhBkcM/TOXAHkMGwnI/AAAAAAAAAmo/SK1dESLoYSU/s800/DSCF0119.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I descended to the hut and warmed myself up a bit, but was soon out
  the door, because I had a goal that was on the other side of
  Mt. Washington.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  My afternoon that day was spent navigating large rocks and asking
  northbounders about the best method for getting work-for-stay at the
  hut that was just past Washington.  The majority opinion was that
  the best method would be to hang out at the top of Mt. Washington
  until an hour before dark because the croo would not turn away a
  hiker into the dark.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Before I got to Mt. Washington, I had to cross the railroad (for
  tourists only) that goes to the top.  You can just see it in this
  picture:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uLJy3SMRqPs/TOXAKk9oLhI/AAAAAAAAAnI/h3r4zQThVtg/s800/DSCF0123.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uLJy3SMRqPs/TOXAKk9oLhI/AAAAAAAAAnI/h3r4zQThVtg/s800/DSCF0123.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But I eventually made it to the top.  There were plenty of people
  who had ridden up in cars or the aforementioned railroad who would
  take my picture with the summit sign.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-m_h-mr1VN-8/TOXAMP1DYnI/AAAAAAAAAnU/57AVGS9d5XQ/s144/DSCF0124.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-m_h-mr1VN-8/TOXAMP1DYnI/AAAAAAAAAnU/57AVGS9d5XQ/s144/DSCF0124.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The top of Mt. Washington is a fairly strange place.  It is a major
  tourist attraction, and has a large snack bar, gift shop, and post
  office, but it also has a major weather station measuring just how
  bad the weather can get.  Every now and then, someone dies because
  they venture out on a hike without the proper gear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, I was safe and sound at the top and hanging out at the gift
  shop until it was late enough to go to the hut.  I met up with a guy
  I had seen in Gorham, who had the trail name Bar Man.  He was a bit
  out of place in the hiking community &amp;ndash; older than the average hiker
  and far less outdoorsy.  In the time that we were talking, it
  emerged that he had only hiked from Osgood Tent Site to Madison hut
  the day before.  Since I had done that hike in the morning, I was
  less than impressed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We walked down to the hut, with the lyrical name &quot;Lakes of the
  Clouds&quot; just before sunset.  There were many other hikers that had
  already arrived, but as predicted, they took us in since darkness
  was falling.  That evening, Bar Man made a nearly complete ass of
  himself.  He was completely rude during supper, complaining about
  everything, despite the fact that we were staying and eating for
  free at a place where others were paying quite good money to stay.
  He did as little work as possible, and relentlessly hit on the
  pretty northbound hikers.  I made up my mind to get up early and
  leave him behind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After sleeping on the dinner tables of the hut, I was very glad to
  get up early.  It turned out to be a lucky decision, because clouds
  had dropped beneath us, and the views were great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZgtPpRYJ_d0/TOXANgbnvpI/AAAAAAAAAns/-u3qVQn_Bxo/s800/DSCF0126.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZgtPpRYJ_d0/TOXANgbnvpI/AAAAAAAAAns/-u3qVQn_Bxo/s800/DSCF0126.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-yqKtaisyjqc/TOXASps4RrI/AAAAAAAAAoM/gBwx095WTrc/s800/DSCF0130.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The path from Mt. Washington was relatively easy &amp;ndash; I could have
  easily made it to the next hut the day before &amp;ndash; but before long, it
  got hard again.  During a moment of lack of focus between
  Mt. Jackson and Mt. Webster, I had my trekking pole slip on a rock,
  and I fell flat on face.  It was a good reminder to keep my
  concentration up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After a descent into another notch, I ascended back to nearly the
  same elevation, and made my way to Ethan Pond.  The caretaker at the
  campsite was a really nice guy and waived the fee for me as a
  thru-hiker.  He also told me that the camp site where I had set up
  my hammock was a favorite place for a local moose.  I didn&#39;t see the
  moose, but I did get a nice picture of the lake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-K-U4fnWnc0g/TOXAUy2PzlI/AAAAAAAAAos/9hmdqsxNM6g/s800/DSCF0133.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-K-U4fnWnc0g/TOXAUy2PzlI/AAAAAAAAAos/9hmdqsxNM6g/s800/DSCF0133.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Wrapup &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This post is getting a bit long, so I&#39;ll save the southern half of
  New Hampshire until next the next post.  In it, I nearly get
  arrested, finally finish with the Whites, and rub shoulders with the
  blue-bloods at Dartmouth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/new-hampshire-1/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Southern Maine</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/southern-maine/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/southern-maine/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-12-19T01:07:04Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-19T00:44:34Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;When I last &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/./../../posts/hiking/mid-maine&quot;&gt;left off&lt;/a&gt; the story of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/./../AT&quot;&gt;Appalachian Trail&lt;/a&gt; hike, I was in
Stratton with Picker and Grinner.  We left Stratton and almost
immediately I could tell that my new hiking shoes were going to bother
me.  They had a harder sole than I was accustomed to, and so my calf
muscles were feeling some pressure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We made it to the top of North Crocker Mountain and met up with
Wounded Knee again.  He was as socially awkward as ever, and I don&#39;t
remember much of the rest of the day until we met him again at the
end.  I was limping because of the pain in my calves, and Wounded Knee
made some remark about how fast a hiker he was, considering that he
had beaten me to the camp site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day, my calves were even more sore.  It was also raining for
much of the day.  We stopped for a long break about 10 miles into the
day so that we could dry off and avoid the rain for a while.
After the rain had stopped, we climbed Saddleback Junior and went on
to a brand new campsite just past the summit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Saddleback &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Some of the nicest views in Southern Maine came on the next day.
  Rather early in the morning, I caught this photo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xpDuqdqRE-o/TOW_u4MaR6I/AAAAAAAAAg8/Gfq875Iod00/s400/DSCF0078.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xpDuqdqRE-o/TOW_u4MaR6I/AAAAAAAAAg8/Gfq875Iod00/s400/DSCF0078.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We were glad that we had waited until after the rain had stopped to
  climb Saddleback, which I think is the mountain that can be seen
  here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8NpeydalE_Q/TOW_wE3rm4I/AAAAAAAAAhY/4TUvkKZ6pgU/s400/DSCF0081.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-8NpeydalE_Q/TOW_wE3rm4I/AAAAAAAAAhY/4TUvkKZ6pgU/s400/DSCF0081.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  First of all, it would have been cold and unpleasant if it had been
  raining, but more than that, we got some great views.  Here is the
  view from the top of Saddleback:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-678OhdNhOfg/TOW_zrmxFjI/AAAAAAAAAic/eX-WFora4js/s400/DSCF0087.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-678OhdNhOfg/TOW_zrmxFjI/AAAAAAAAAic/eX-WFora4js/s400/DSCF0087.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After descending Saddleback, we got to a road crossing near
  Rangeley, Maine.  We got a ride to the store from a person who had
  completed his hike a little earlier and was helping hikers on his
  way back south.  After we had gotten back on the trail, Grinner
  realized that she had left her hiking poles in the trail angel&#39;s
  car.  This was a cause for some consternation, but we had to keep
  pushing on.  Picker simply lent Grinner one of his poles, and we
  kept on hiking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Our hike that evening led us to a pond with a canoe docked on it for
  hikers to use.  We took the canoe for a spin and filtered some water
  from the pond (though pond water is generally not very good).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Bemis mountain &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After our little paddle, we had a nice weather for most of the next
  day.  It was a good thing, too, because after a fairly easy morning,
  we had a highly treacherous descent followed by a steep ascent.  By
  the time we had reached the shelter, it was raining again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When I awoke the next day, the clouds had dropped and fog had set
  in.  Luckily, Bemis mountain doesn&#39;t have any views to speak of
  anyway.  However, it does have one feature of the mountains in
  Southern Maine: trail that is a fairly sheer slab of rock, often
  with a stream running down it.  This is, needless to say, difficult
  to walk on.  I slipped multiple times before lunch, and was not
  having a great day.  On top of that, after lunch, there were two
  big, steep climbs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the end of the day, we got to a lean-to which contained a hiker
  who said that he had simply stayed there all day.  He had some
  rather depressing stories about how hard Southern Maine had been,
  but in a way, it cheered me up.  I could really see that others
  (even Northbounders, who had already come more than 1900 miles) were
  having trouble too.  As long as I wasn&#39;t alone, I knew I could make
  it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Notches &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Our plan the next day was to make it to Baldpate Lean-to, just short
  of Grafton Notch (which contains the southernmost road that the
  trail crosses in Maine).  However, as we were nearing the shelter,
  we came across a group of teenagers.  We went to the shelter and
  found an even larger group of teens.  They had completely taken over
  the shelter and were engaged in several loud games, completely
  disturbing the peace of the outdoors.  In fact, the object of one of
  the games was to scream for the longest.  It was terrible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Luckily for me, I had been lobbying to go on to Grafton Notch for
  most of the day anyway, so I was pleased when Picker and Grinner got
  fed up with the teens and decided to go on.  We made it to Grafton
  Notch and found some trail magic.  I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve described what
  trail magic is yet.  Sometimes people who live near the trail will
  leave food or drink on the trail for hikers.  In this case, a kind
  trail angel had driven his truck to Grafton Notch and was sitting
  with a cooler full of Nestle chocolate milk.  I don&#39;t think I have
  ever been so happy to drink milk, and it started a tradition for me
  of having a chocolate milkshake whenever possible in town.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We hiked about halfway up the next mountain after our refreshment
  and set up camp for the night in the middle of the woods.  This is
  known as &quot;stealth camping&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8pltuMntIbQ/TOW_4ePY2kI/AAAAAAAAAjY/bsjfBmAyuhI/s400/DSCF0096.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-8pltuMntIbQ/TOW_4ePY2kI/AAAAAAAAAjY/bsjfBmAyuhI/s400/DSCF0096.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We finished climbing the mountain the next morning, and went in the
  fog past Speck Pond.  It made for a couple of rather pretty pictures of some
  lilypads:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r0GHcdVF2X0/TOW_5EmEoJI/AAAAAAAAAjk/fDU5DQ9XK3U/s400/DSCF0097.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-r0GHcdVF2X0/TOW_5EmEoJI/AAAAAAAAAjk/fDU5DQ9XK3U/s400/DSCF0097.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DSra0_gp7yw/TOW_5dWrUaI/AAAAAAAAAjs/VUN6H4ISAeM/s400/DSCF0098.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-DSra0_gp7yw/TOW_5dWrUaI/AAAAAAAAAjs/VUN6H4ISAeM/s400/DSCF0098.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Going down from the pond, we had more trails on slippery sheer
  rocks.  Grinner got stuck for a couple of minutes at one point and I
  had to help her get down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the bottom of the hill, we had finally reached Mahoosuc Notch.
  Unfortunately I don&#39;t have any pictures of it (I was trying to
  remain as focussed as possible), because it is one of the most
  interesting features of the trail.  It looks like someone took a
  bunch of house-sized boulders and shook them so that they landed
  randomly at the bottom of a valley.  There are some pictures at the
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahoosuc_Notch&quot;&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; that give a good impression of what it is like.  Note
  especially the arrow painted on the rock &amp;ndash; those are essential to
  making it through in a reasonable amount of time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In any case, we did the one mile through the notch in about two
  hours.  For me, it was not the most enjoyable: I took a bad fall
  right at the entrance to the notch, so my hands were hurting from
  stopping the fall, and I was a bit shaken up.  It was all I could do
  to keep my concentration and not fall again.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Finally, we got through the notch and I found that I was out of
  water.  There was no choice but to go on to the shelter to get
  water.  I hiked up the hill as quickly as I could, and fortuitously
  found a water bottle that someone else had dropped.  Not knowing the
  provenance of the water in the bottle, I wasn&#39;t able to drink from
  it, but it would come in handy later in the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I set up my hammock and Picker and Grinner decided to stay in the
  shelter.  It was their first time staying in a shelter with other
  people (they had tented until then), and Picker came over to gripe
  about it a bit.  After supper, I went to throw my bear bag.  At that
  point, I still wasn&#39;t great at it (and I guess I&#39;m still not), but
  one throw was so unfortunate as to be comical.  I had attached my
  water bottle to the line that would hold the bag up on the branch.
  On this particular throw, the water bottle arced behind me and came
  straight down on a sharp rock, splitting into multiple pieces.  I
  was glad I had found the other water bottle, but it was a pretty bad
  end to a rather unpleasant day, which should have been a lot more
  fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Run to the border &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;  
  The trail away from the shelter was nearly as hard as the trail to
  it.  There were ladders and rocks to climb up.  Early in the
  morning, as I was trying to climb up one of these rocks, I lost my
  grip and fell again &amp;ndash; this time five to ten feet.  I was extremely
  lucky not to get hurt.  I think the weight of my backpack caused me
  to fall backwards onto it, keeping me from being too badly injured.
  However, I struck my jaw on a rock on the way down, and it would be
  sore for a couple of days afterwards.  After bad falls two days in a
  row, I was eager to get to town.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  First, though, we needed to cross the border between Maine and New
  Hampshire.  Here is a picture proving we did it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-YsZqdhHRV8c/TOW_7TpBdlI/AAAAAAAADfU/yupECnTzq0A/s400/DSCF0100.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-YsZqdhHRV8c/TOW_7TpBdlI/AAAAAAAADfU/yupECnTzq0A/s400/DSCF0100.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We didn&#39;t make it to town that night, but we made it within about
  six miles.  When we finally got to Gorham, NH the next morning,
  things were already seeming better to me.  We were in town and could
  hang out in a hostel for a fairly cheap zero day.  Also, the trail
  angel in whose car Picker had left her poles had left them at the
  hostel, so she got those back.  There was a place for me to get a
  milkshake.  So at least for a day and a half of not-hiking, I was a
  pretty happy hiker.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Next time &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Just past Gorham is the beginning of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Mountains_(New_Hampshire)&quot;&gt;White mountains&lt;/a&gt;.  I will go
  off on my own in one of the toughest sections of the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/southern-maine/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/southern-maine/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Mid-Maine</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/mid-maine/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/mid-maine/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-12-01T07:47:32Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-28T16:52:35Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leaving Monson &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  When I last left my hiking tale, Picker, Grinner, Frosty and I had
  just gotten to Monson in time for breakfast.  We were hustled into
  showers and given clean clothes to put on while ours were in the
  washer.  We decided to stay in Monson for the rest of the day.  A
  bit of hiking terminology: a &lt;i&gt;zero&lt;/i&gt; is a day in which no walking is
  done.  What we were doing is called a &lt;i&gt;nearo&lt;/i&gt; (sometimes written
  &lt;i&gt;near-0&lt;/i&gt;), short for near-zero.  It&#39;s one of the most enjoyable ways
  to spend a day.  You only need to pay for one night at the hostel or
  hotel, but you have all the fun of a town day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, breakfast was great &amp;ndash; unlimited pancakes, eggs, and some of
  the best home fries I had on the trail.  The big event of the day
  was the World Cup final.  The town of Monson is extremely small.
  There was one bar and one convenience store as well as the hostel we
  were staying at, named Shaw&#39;s.  We watched the final at the bar.  I
  was disappointed that the Netherlands lost, but I remember it being
  a really dirty game, so I guess the better team won in the end.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Frosty got a six-pack of beer for us to split, and it was through
  this beer that we met Wounded Knee.  The four of us had taken a seat
  to chat and drink the beer, when Wounded Knee showed up with one of
  the beers in his hand.  He began regaling us with hiking stories and
  bad jokes.  Later, we figured that he probably thought he was paying
  for the beer by telling us his great stories.  I think we would have
  been happier if he had just taken the beer and left us alone.
  (Cruel, but true &amp;ndash; at least he did provide an excellent topic of
  conversation over the next month.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After a rather fitful sleep, Picker, Grinner, and I left Frosty in
  Monson.  He wanted to stay another day to rest after the 100-mile
  wilderness.  Unfortunately, it was the last time we would see him on
  our hike &amp;ndash; he got a stress fracture in his foot and stopped about
  50 miles later.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As we were being driven back to the trail, we were given a warning
  about a &quot;bahd hikeah&quot; (a bad hiker in the heavy Northeastern accent
  that is common in Maine).  He had apparently chosen to swim a
  dangerous river for which a ferry is provided after heaping abuse on
  the ferry operator.  He would not be served in Monson &amp;ndash; my first
  hint that there is a little network of hostel operators up and down
  the trail.  We actually did cross paths with the guy, and he looked
  more like a motorcycle enthusiast than a hiker, but other than that,
  there was no indication that he was really a bad guy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, Grinner was not feeling great.  I think it was for
  this reason that we did not go very far.  On the subsequent day, it
  became clear that Grinner was really sick.  Luckily, they had a cell
  phone with them, and were able to call Shaw&#39;s.  Grinner was picked
  up, and as she left, she told me to take care of Picker.  Which
  showed that she hadn&#39;t lost her sense of humor, because Picker is a
  bad-ass Army veteran who had been in Iraq.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Without Grinner &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Picker was obviously concerned about his wife, so we made a plan to
  get to the next town as quickly as possible.  We got to the Kennebec
  river (the one with the ferry) unfortunately after the ferry had
  stopped for the night.  Partly to give myself something to do, and
  partly to cheer Picker up, I decided to find us some sodas.  The
  small town of Caratunk is near the trail at that point, but it
  didn&#39;t even have a convenience store, so I had to hitchhike to a
  small resort that had vending machines.  It was my first time
  hitching a ride, and I was glad that it worked out well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, we caught the first ferry across the river.  When one
  imagines a ferry, it is usually a fairly large boat.  This was not.
  It was a small canoe, operated by a local hippie.  I helped row us
  across the river, and we set out as fast as possible.  That was our
  first twenty-mile day.  The scenery was great, with a nice waterfall
  near the trail, but we were in a rush to see Grinner again.  Near
  the end of the day, the trail was rerouted, adding an extra couple
  of miles to our day.  We were quite glad to get to the campsite on
  the North side of Little Bigelow Mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  This put us only about 15 miles from Stratton, where we assumed that
  Grinner would be.  However, there were two big climbs between here
  and there.  We must have gotten to the top of the first fairly early
  in the morning.  We crossed a road in which someone had &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/2Qwgtnn5g3HJZgZp52HULHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;painted&lt;/a&gt;
  &quot;2000 mi.&quot;, meaning that we still had two thousand miles to go --
  even after almost two weeks of hiking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When we got to the camp site five miles from Stratton, there was a
  decision to make.  We had done 10 miles, but it had been 10 hard
  miles.  The rest of the way to the road would be all downhill, and
  there would be no more camping possibilities.  Picker left the
  decision up to me, but I could tell that he really wanted to go on.
  After a rest for my back (which still hadn&#39;t gotten as strong as
  would get), I decided that we should try to get to the road.  We
  also talked to a northbounder who said that the trail was pretty
  easy and that we could make it.  At that point, I had not learned to
  mistrust everything northbounders say.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I would have done well to mistrust the northbounder.  The descent
  was really difficult.  However, I did see a &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/bBFYuVIz4Xp42kq3LKPhEHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;beaver&lt;/a&gt;, so that made it
  kind of worth it.  When we got within two miles of the road, Picker
  started running.  I trotted along behind him, and we got to the road
  within thirty minutes.  We called the Stratton motel and were
  heartened to find that Grinner was already there.  She was feeling
  better, which was a huge relief.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Stratton &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Since we had gone faster than expected between Monson and Stratton,
  and since Grinner still wasn&#39;t 100%, I decided to take an actual
  zero in Stratton.  I got a ride to Rangeley to get some better shoes
  and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001Q1P0K2/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=217145&amp;amp;creative=399373&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001Q1P0K2&quot;&gt;hiking poles&lt;/a&gt; at the outfitter there.  I still have those poles
  after more than 4000 miles, so I feel comfortable recommending
  them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The other big event from our zero day in Stratton is that we found a
  lady that was selling pies from her house.  She didn&#39;t have the
  proper food license to sell slices, so we were forced to buy a whole
  cheesecake.  We had no choice in the matter.  I think we showed
  great restraint by not eating the entire cheesecake in one sitting
  &amp;ndash; we saved some for breakfast the next day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Oh, and one final story from Stratton.  We had caught up to Wounded
  Knee by getting there a day earlier than scheduled.  During
  conversation, he mentioned that he had an injury that he needed some
  help putting a bandage on.  Somehow, I was volunteered to help him
  out.  It turned out that he had a really bad chafe on his bum and
  couldn&#39;t quite see it to put the bandage on himself.  So I got to
  help out with that.  Blech.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Next time &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In the next installment, we go through Southern Maine.  This
  includes some of the most scenic and dangerous parts of the trail,
  including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahoosuc_Notch&quot;&gt;Mahoosuc Notch&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/mid-maine/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/mid-maine/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>100-Mile Wilderness</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-12-01T07:47:22Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-19T20:34:35Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m sitting in an airport, breathing the recycled air and jet exhaust,
so I thought I&#39;d write a bit more about my hiking experiences.  I
don&#39;t have my trail guide with me, so I won&#39;t be able to include as
many details as I would like, but hopefully I can recall the things
that made the biggest impression on me. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The 100-Mile Wilderness &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Right after the huge challenge of climbing Mount Katahdin,
  southbound hikers on the Appalachian Trail must deal with about 100
  miles without any stores or conveniences.  As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/hiking/at-01/&quot;&gt;last hiking post&lt;/a&gt;, this means big and heavy packs for the hikers.  Also,
  my lack of experience meant that I was carrying things that I didn&#39;t
  really need, so when I set out on the first morning I was really
  loaded down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got out of camp a bit later than Oblio and his dad, and walked out
  of Baxter Park.  I don&#39;t remember too much about the first day.
  There was a decent-sized river that we walked beside for a while and
  I thought I saw a beaver or some other water animal, but I couldn&#39;t
  get close enough to get a picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We officially entered the 100-mile wilderness when we passed this
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/PZEL0R-SlLrRdqSIKN-5UHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;sign&lt;/a&gt;, and didn&#39;t walk more than 100 yards before we saw some moose
  dung.  That seemed like a good sign to me.  Where there&#39;s dung,
  there&#39;s animals.  A couple of miles later, it was time to call it a
  day at the first shelter on the AT.  The log in the shelter warned
  of rodents, so I immediately decided not to sleep in it.  We also
  met some northbounders (nobos in AT parlance).  At that time, I
  viewed them as something like heroes.  These were people that were
  just 10 or 12 miles from finishing the same hike that I was on.
  Wow!  They were so close to the finish line that they were going
  on.  They would probably do half the miles that we had done in the
  entire day in that evening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, I got up fairly early.  There was a small hill, and
  then the trail goes around a lake.  The trail was mucky and the
  boards (called &quot;bog boards&quot;) that were placed for people to walk on
  were disintegrating.  Finally we got away from the lake and the
  trail conditions became a bit better.  We crossed &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/mv9x4neQvulRVGCYQzUTNHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;this bridge&lt;/a&gt; and
  got to &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/D2nJ4h_FzubDnoCOSgy6u3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;the Rainbow Stream shelter&lt;/a&gt; (I see that Picker and Grinner got
  there before me).  I took a small nap on the pine needles behind the
  shelter and cleaned off my legs in the pool below &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/GFBLdt6vU4QgYQIJRgkYinIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;this waterfall&lt;/a&gt;.
  Finally, I started walking again.  About two miles later, I stumbled
  and decided that I must be getting tired and that I should look for
  a place to camp.  Luckily, I found that Oblio and his dad camped
  just a few hundred yards later, so I stopped there for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t really remember much about the next couple of days.  On one
  of them, I got bitten by a mosquito on the lip, and my lip swelled
  to twice its normal size.  There was also a river that was reputed
  to have good swimming, but the water was quite warm because it is
  lake-fed.  I hiked a couple of miles past it and camped at the lake
  that was the source.  A float plane landed on the lake while I was
  there, but it was all the way on the other side of the lake, so it
  wasn&#39;t too bothersome.  I had a quiet night, but Picker and Grinner
  didn&#39;t; there was a group of Quebecois Girl Scouts at the campsite
  next to the river and they stayed up late chattering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Picker and Grinner passed me early the next morning in what would
  become a pattern.  The two of them were much more efficient than me
  in the morning, especially while I was still cooking oatmeal for
  breakfast.  That day was the first where I had a big choice to
  make.  Would I hike fast and get over White Cap or would I stop just
  before it?  I didn&#39;t have a data book at that point, so I had no
  real way of knowing how hard White Cap would be, but people had been
  hyping it for a while as a pretty hard climb.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-1&quot;&gt;White Cap &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   When I got to the shelter just before White Cap, I made the choice
   to go on.  The next shelter was just two or three miles away and it
   wasn&#39;t yet late.  This turned out to be a slight mistake.  The
   climb up White Cap wasn&#39;t too bad (though it would turn out to be
   too much for Oblio&#39;s dad &amp;ndash; he had to be helped down the mountain
   and he and Oblio called it quits there), but there were about three
   more mountains to go over before I got to the campsite.  It was in
   that moment that I first learned the value of having a data book,
   though I don&#39;t think it quite sunk in until I got through with
   Maine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Another reason that hiking over White Cap that evening was a
   mistake was that there was a large group of Quebecois boys at the
   campsite and they kept making noise until about one the next
   morning.  However, I did get woken up by a moose, so maybe that&#39;s a
   wash.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-2&quot;&gt;Chairback &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The next day was probably my shortest full day of hiking on the
   trail.  I was clearly tired from my adventure (and the noise made
   by the boys) the night before and I just walked pretty slow in the
   morning.  I also had not counted on the climb up the next mountain
   &amp;ndash; Chairback Mountain &amp;ndash; being &lt;b&gt;straight up&lt;/b&gt;.  People in Maine have
   clearly not heard of switchbacks, because there were none.  When I
   was getting very close to the shelter at Chairback Mountain, there
   was a large climb on talus (big rocks that are just sitting on each
   other with nothing to keep them from falling).  That&#39;s also not my
   favorite thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I had told myself that if I didn&#39;t get to the shelter by 3, then I
   would stay there.  I met an older man that was already staying at
   the shelter and asked him what time it was &amp;ndash; he said that it was
   after three, and I was quite relieved.  We talked for a while --
   his trail name was Frosty and had been on the trail for a day
   longer than me.  I was a bit proud of myself for passing someone
   already, but Frosty had taken a bit of a side trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I went to set up my hammock, and while I was doing that, I heard
   Picker and Grinner arrive.  They had stayed at the shelter before
   White Cap and we had not seen each other that day.  She asked
   Frosty if he&#39;d seen me, and when he pointed me out, Grinner came
   running over and gave me a big hug.  That was a huge help for me to
   have someone glad to see me at the end of what was my first really
   hard day on the trail.  It was just one of the reasons that I give
   a lot of credit for my success on the trail to Picker and Grinner.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-3&quot;&gt;The rest &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I stayed with Picker, Grinner, and Frosty for the rest of the
   100-mile wilderness.  There were more mountains and campsites, but
   nothing that stands out too vividly in my memory (though this
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/bUFnjNFdRFDtm2PT7cNbdnIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;waterfall&lt;/a&gt; is pretty nice).  Frosty turned out to be a great hiking
   companion as well.  His pack was lighter than everyone else&#39;s, so
   he had no problems keeping up, and he has a great sense of humor.
   He had planned a lot better than I had, and finished all the food
   in his pack by breakfast on the final day before we got to Monson.
   I think he had to eat turkey stuffing because he had eaten some
   breakfasts for supper on an earlier night.  Luckily, we were only a
   few miles from the road, so no one starved.  (That being said,
   everyone was talking about food at that point &amp;ndash; we were getting
   pretty hungry and all of us lost quite a bit of weight.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-4&quot;&gt;Monson &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   We called Shaw&#39;s in Monson from the road and they came and picked
   us up.  It was great to get out of the wilderness.  The people at
   Shaw&#39;s were so nice and especially great at dealing with tired
   hikers.  They quickly got us into the showers and gave us a nice
   all-you-can-eat pancake breakfast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I think I won&#39;t get into all that happened in Monson today, but
   leave that until the next installment of the saga, where we&#39;ll meet
   Wounded Knee.  Stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Appalachian Trail Tales</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-12-01T07:47:10Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-13T15:57:32Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Starting on the Appalachian Trail &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This is my first post about hiking, so I think it should be about my
  first days really hiking.  That would be July 1 and 2, 2010.  It
  already seems like an eternity ago, so much has happened since
  then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;July 1 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I had been at a conference in Quebec City in the days leading up to
  July 1.  It had gone well and I had given a talk that I thought was
  pretty well-received.  But more important for me on that day was
  that I had gone to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt; and bought a bunch of backpacking gear.  In
  fact, I had mailed all my possessions home from Germany to Calgary
  the week before, so I was really planning to live on the trail.  I
  had no alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I shaved one last time before my trip, took my new gear, and walked
  to the rental-car agency.  I had booked a car the day before and
  knew it would be open, even though it was Canada Day.  The drive
  from Quebec to Maine was long and pretty boring.  The only
  slightly-eventful thing that happened was that the border guards
  really gave me a hard time, eventually saying something like &quot;Well,
  we have to let him in, he&#39;s a citizen.&quot;  I guess they don&#39;t have
  much to do at that particular crossing, so they make the most of it
  when they get someone with even a slightly strange story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I arrived in Bangor, Maine and needed to do some food shopping.  I
  knew that I had the dreaded 100-mile wilderness ahead of me, meaning
  that I might not get to a store for 10 days.  The stuff I bought
  then seems rather comical now.  I had a pound of rice and four or
  five Indian meals that were not dehydrated.  Also a full jar of
  peanut butter and a full jar of jelly.  And two different kinds of
  non-dehydrated hummus.  I&#39;m pretty sure it all fit into my
  food bag eventually, but it took some doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I returned the car at the airport and then took the airport bus from
  the airport to the bus terminal.  It turned out that the bus
  terminal was walking distance from the rental-car agency, but I
  didn&#39;t find that out until I was already on the bus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got to the bus terminal and asked for a ticket to Millinocket.  It
  turned out that I wasn&#39;t the first to do that on that day: two other
  people were already there that were going to the trailhead.  They
  would become known to me as Picker and Grinner, and I would walk
  with them for about 1000 miles.  They obviously knew what they were
  doing.  They had sent their food ahead to the Inn at Millinocket and
  had booked a ride there.  Grinner had also already hiked the trail,
  so I was sure that I was safe tagging along with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the inn, I met a couple more people that were starting the same
  day as me: Oblio and his dad.  We had a beer at the bar down the
  street and discussed the trail ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;July 2 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After a night of pretty poor sleep (I was excited and there were
  snorers), we got up bright and early at 5:30 the next morning.  The
  inn came with a deal that you get breakfast at the diner, so I met
  up with Oblio and his dad, and we came up with trail names for
  ourselves. Since I had been doing my postdoc in Computational
  Geometry just before the trail, I became known as Dr. Geo.  Oblio&#39;s
  dad was in marketing, and assured me that this was a fine name.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We piled into the innkeeper&#39;s truck and headed for the trail.  The
  first task of a southbound AT thru-hike is to climb Mount Katahdin.
  In fact, the climb doesn&#39;t even count, because the trail starts at
  the top.  Since we would be coming back, we left our full packs at
  the Baxter Park ranger station, and took the loaner day-packs that
  they provide.  That would be the only time that I hiked without my
  full pack over the next 4500 miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a good thing that we had light packs, because Katahdin is a
  monster.  It is probably the most technical climbing on the trail,
  requiring you to pull yourself up with your hands at many points.
  However, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xaCB5S_gJwWabCsdMwPVU3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;views&lt;/a&gt; are great.  At some points, you &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/om0LnphpOAtHNxIX9QwkqHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;feel&lt;/a&gt; like you are
  in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8rHwtx0OcApK-34CYXmkM3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;airplane&lt;/a&gt;, you can see so far.  There are even great &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ig4QqEE10V3TTXk9BfL9TXIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;waterfalls&lt;/a&gt;
  near the base.  I know some people bathed in the pools beneath the
  falls, but the water was far too cold for me.  However, I did get my
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/betCZRWpaGuJGmFtjulKJnIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;picture&lt;/a&gt; taken at the summit so that I could prove that I had started
  the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We started our hike from the summit back down the mountain.  It was
  even harder going down than going up.  When we got to the bottom,
  everyone was pretty tired.  Especially for the first day of hiking,
  Katahdin is really hard.  We made our camp at Baxter Park.  Of
  course, I was very poorly organized and hadn&#39;t realized that you
  must book a campsite there, so I shared with Oblio and his dad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a night of firsts for me.  I hadn&#39;t lit my stove before.  It
  didn&#39;t want to work with my flint, so I had to borrow a lighter.  I
  hadn&#39;t used a water filter before, so I needed to do that for the
  first time as well.  Cooking outside was also a new experience, and
  I undercooked the rice pretty woefully.  But after a hard day of
  hiking, any warm food is pretty good.  After that, I set up my
  brand-new hammock for the first time and climbed into my brand-new
  sleeping bag.  The hammock sagged so much that my bum almost touched
  the ground, but I didn&#39;t care &amp;ndash; I was in bed and my journey had
  started.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
