<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged AT</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/AT/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-11-21T00:31:34Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>100-mile-wilderness</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/"/>






	<category term="at" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-11-21T00:31:34Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-19T20:34:35Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m sitting in an airport, breathing the recycled air and jet exhaust,
so I thought I&#39;d write a bit more about my hiking experiences.  I
don&#39;t have my trail guide with me, so I won&#39;t be able to include as
many details as I would like, but hopefully I can recall the things
that made the biggest impression on me. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;The 100-Mile Wilderness &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Right after the huge challenge of climbing Mount Katahdin,
  southbound hikers on the Appalachian Trail must deal with about 100
  miles without any stores or conveniences.  As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/hiking/at-01/&quot;&gt;last hiking post&lt;/a&gt;, this means big and heavy packs for the hikers.  Also,
  my lack of experience meant that I was carrying things that I didn&#39;t
  really need, so when I set out on the first morning I was really
  loaded down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got out of camp a bit later than Oblio and his dad, and walked out
  of Baxter Park.  I don&#39;t remember too much about the first day.
  There was a decent-sized river that we walked beside for a while and
  I thought I saw a beaver or some other water animal, but I couldn&#39;t
  get close enough to get a picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We officially entered the 100-mile wilderness when we passed this
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/PZEL0R-SlLrRdqSIKN-5UHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;sign&lt;/a&gt;, and didn&#39;t walk more than 100 yards before we saw some moose
  dung.  That seemed like a good sign to me.  Where there&#39;s dung,
  there&#39;s animals.  A couple of miles later, it was time to call it a
  day at the first shelter on the AT.  The log in the shelter warned
  of rodents, so I immediately decided not to sleep in it.  We also
  met some northbounders (nobos in AT parlance).  At that time, I
  viewed them as something like heroes.  These were people that were
  just 10 or 12 miles from finishing the same hike that I was on.
  Wow!  They were so close to the finish line that they were going
  on.  They would probably do half the miles that we had done in the
  entire day in that evening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day, I got up fairly early.  There was a small hill, and
  then the trail goes around a lake.  The trail was mucky and the
  boards (called &quot;bog boards&quot;) that were placed for people to walk on
  were disintegrating.  Finally we got away from the lake and the
  trail conditions became a bit better.  We crossed &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/mv9x4neQvulRVGCYQzUTNHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;this bridge&lt;/a&gt; and
  got to &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/D2nJ4h_FzubDnoCOSgy6u3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;the Rainbow Stream shelter&lt;/a&gt; (I see that Picker and Grinner got
  there before me).  I took a small nap on the pine needles behind the
  shelter and cleaned off my legs in the pool below &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/GFBLdt6vU4QgYQIJRgkYinIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;this waterfall&lt;/a&gt;.
  Finally, I started walking again.  About two miles later, I stumbled
  and decided that I must be getting tired and that I should look for
  a place to camp.  Luckily, I found that Oblio and his dad camped
  just a few hundred yards later, so I stopped there for the night.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t really remember much about the next couple of days.  On one
  of them, I got bitten by a mosquito on the lip, and my lip swelled
  to twice its normal size.  There was also a river that was reputed
  to have good swimming, but the water was quite warm because it is
  lake-fed.  I hiked a couple of miles past it and camped at the lake
  that was the source.  A float plane landed on the lake while I was
  there, but it was all the way on the other side of the lake, so it
  wasn&#39;t too bothersome.  I had a quiet night, but Picker and Grinner
  didn&#39;t; there was a group of Quebecois Girl Scouts at the campsite
  next to the river and they stayed up late chattering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Picker and Grinner passed me early the next morning in what would
  become a pattern.  The two of them were much more efficient than me
  in the morning, especially while I was still cooking oatmeal for
  breakfast.  That day was the first where I had a big choice to
  make.  Would I hike fast and get over White Cap or would I stop just
  before it?  I didn&#39;t have a data book at that point, so I had no
  real way of knowing how hard White Cap would be, but people had been
  hyping it for a while as a pretty hard climb.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-1&quot;&gt;White Cap &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   When I got to the shelter just before White Cap, I made the choice
   to go on.  The next shelter was just two or three miles away and it
   wasn&#39;t yet late.  This turned out to be a slight mistake.  The
   climb up White Cap wasn&#39;t too bad (though it would turn out to be
   too much for Oblio&#39;s dad &amp;ndash; he had to be helped down the mountain
   and he and Oblio called it quits there), but there were about three
   more mountains to go over before I got to the campsite.  It was in
   that moment that I first learned the value of having a data book,
   though I don&#39;t think it quite sunk in until I got through with
   Maine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Another reason that hiking over White Cap that evening was a
   mistake was that there was a large group of Quebecois boys at the
   campsite and they kept making noise until about one the next
   morning.  However, I did get woken up by a moose, so maybe that&#39;s a
   wash.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-2&quot;&gt;Chairback &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The next day was probably my shortest full day of hiking on the
   trail.  I was clearly tired from my adventure (and the noise made
   by the boys) the night before and I just walked pretty slow in the
   morning.  I also had not counted on the climb up the next mountain
   &amp;ndash; Chairback Mountain &amp;ndash; being &lt;b&gt;straight up&lt;/b&gt;.  People in Maine have
   clearly not heard of switchbacks, because there were none.  When I
   was getting very close to the shelter at Chairback Mountain, there
   was a large climb on talus (big rocks that are just sitting on each
   other with nothing to keep them from falling).  That&#39;s also not my
   favorite thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I had told myself that if I didn&#39;t get to the shelter by 3, then I
   would stay there.  I met an older man that was already staying at
   the shelter and asked him what time it was &amp;ndash; he said that it was
   after three, and I was quite relieved.  We talked for a while --
   his trail name was Frosty and had been on the trail for a day
   longer than me.  I was a bit proud of myself for passing someone
   already, but Frosty had taken a bit of a side trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I went to set up my hammock, and while I was doing that, I heard
   Picker and Grinner arrive.  They had stayed at the shelter before
   White Cap and we had not seen each other that day.  She asked
   Frosty if he&#39;d seen me, and when he pointed me out, Grinner came
   running over and gave me a big hug.  That was a huge help for me to
   have someone glad to see me at the end of what was my first really
   hard day on the trail.  It was just one of the reasons that I give
   a lot of credit for my success on the trail to Picker and Grinner.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-3&quot;&gt;The rest &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I stayed with Picker, Grinner, and Frosty for the rest of the
   100-mile wilderness.  There were more mountains and campsites, but
   nothing that stands out too vividly in my memory (though this
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/bUFnjNFdRFDtm2PT7cNbdnIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;waterfall&lt;/a&gt; is pretty nice).  Frosty turned out to be a great hiking
   companion as well.  His pack was lighter than everyone else&#39;s, so
   he had no problems keeping up, and he has a great sense of humor.
   He had planned a lot better than I had, and finished all the food
   in his pack by breakfast on the final day before we got to Monson.
   I think he had to eat turkey stuffing because he had eaten some
   breakfasts for supper on an earlier night.  Luckily, we were only a
   few miles from the road, so no one starved.  (That being said,
   everyone was talking about food at that point &amp;ndash; we were getting
   pretty hungry and all of us lost quite a bit of weight.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-4&quot;&gt;Monson &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   We called Shaw&#39;s in Monson from the road and they came and picked
   us up.  It was great to get out of the wilderness.  The people at
   Shaw&#39;s were so nice and especially great at dealing with tired
   hikers.  They quickly got us into the showers and gave us a nice
   all-you-can-eat pancake breakfast.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I think I won&#39;t get into all that happened in Monson today, but
   leave that until the next installment of the saga, where we&#39;ll meet
   Wounded Knee.  Stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/100-mile-wilderness/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>at-01</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-11-13T16:05:46Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-13T15:57:32Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Starting on the Appalachian Trail &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This is my first post about hiking, so I think it should be about my
  first days really hiking.  That would be July 1 and 2, 2010.  It
  already seems like an eternity ago, so much has happened since
  then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;July 1 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I had been at a conference in Quebec City in the days leading up to
  July 1.  It had gone well and I had given a talk that I thought was
  pretty well-received.  But more important for me on that day was
  that I had gone to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt; and bought a bunch of backpacking gear.  In
  fact, I had mailed all my possessions home from Germany to Calgary
  the week before, so I was really planning to live on the trail.  I
  had no alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I shaved one last time before my trip, took my new gear, and walked
  to the rental-car agency.  I had booked a car the day before and
  knew it would be open, even though it was Canada Day.  The drive
  from Quebec to Maine was long and pretty boring.  The only
  slightly-eventful thing that happened was that the border guards
  really gave me a hard time, eventually saying something like &quot;Well,
  we have to let him in, he&#39;s a citizen.&quot;  I guess they don&#39;t have
  much to do at that particular crossing, so they make the most of it
  when they get someone with even a slightly strange story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I arrived in Bangor, Maine and needed to do some food shopping.  I
  knew that I had the dreaded 100-mile wilderness ahead of me, meaning
  that I might not get to a store for 10 days.  The stuff I bought
  then seems rather comical now.  I had a pound of rice and four or
  five Indian meals that were not dehydrated.  Also a full jar of
  peanut butter and a full jar of jelly.  And two different kinds of
  non-dehydrated hummus.  I&#39;m pretty sure it all fit into my
  food bag eventually, but it took some doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I returned the car at the airport and then took the airport bus from
  the airport to the bus terminal.  It turned out that the bus
  terminal was walking distance from the rental-car agency, but I
  didn&#39;t find that out until I was already on the bus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got to the bus terminal and asked for a ticket to Millinocket.  It
  turned out that I wasn&#39;t the first to do that on that day: two other
  people were already there that were going to the trailhead.  They
  would become known to me as Picker and Grinner, and I would walk
  with them for about 1000 miles.  They obviously knew what they were
  doing.  They had sent their food ahead to the Inn at Millinocket and
  had booked a ride there.  Grinner had also already hiked the trail,
  so I was sure that I was safe tagging along with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the inn, I met a couple more people that were starting the same
  day as me: Oblio and his dad.  We had a beer at the bar down the
  street and discussed the trail ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;July 2 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After a night of pretty poor sleep (I was excited and there were
  snorers), we got up bright and early at 5:30 the next morning.  The
  inn came with a deal that you get breakfast at the diner, so I met
  up with Oblio and his dad, and we came up with trail names for
  ourselves. Since I had been doing my postdoc in Computational
  Geometry just before the trail, I became known as Dr. Geo.  Oblio&#39;s
  dad was in marketing, and assured me that this was a fine name.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We piled into the innkeeper&#39;s truck and headed for the trail.  The
  first task of a southbound AT thru-hike is to climb Mount Katahdin.
  In fact, the climb doesn&#39;t even count, because the trail starts at
  the top.  Since we would be coming back, we left our full packs at
  the Baxter Park ranger station, and took the loaner day-packs that
  they provide.  That would be the only time that I hiked without my
  full pack over the next 4500 miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a good thing that we had light packs, because Katahdin is a
  monster.  It is probably the most technical climbing on the trail,
  requiring you to pull yourself up with your hands at many points.
  However, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xaCB5S_gJwWabCsdMwPVU3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;views&lt;/a&gt; are great.  At some points, you &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/om0LnphpOAtHNxIX9QwkqHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;feel&lt;/a&gt; like you are
  in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8rHwtx0OcApK-34CYXmkM3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;airplane&lt;/a&gt;, you can see so far.  There are even great &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ig4QqEE10V3TTXk9BfL9TXIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;waterfalls&lt;/a&gt;
  near the base.  I know some people bathed in the pools beneath the
  falls, but the water was far too cold for me.  However, I did get my
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/betCZRWpaGuJGmFtjulKJnIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;picture&lt;/a&gt; taken at the summit so that I could prove that I had started
  the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We started our hike from the summit back down the mountain.  It was
  even harder going down than going up.  When we got to the bottom,
  everyone was pretty tired.  Especially for the first day of hiking,
  Katahdin is really hard.  We made our camp at Baxter Park.  Of
  course, I was very poorly organized and hadn&#39;t realized that you
  must book a campsite there, so I shared with Oblio and his dad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a night of firsts for me.  I hadn&#39;t lit my stove before.  It
  didn&#39;t want to work with my flint, so I had to borrow a lighter.  I
  hadn&#39;t used a water filter before, so I needed to do that for the
  first time as well.  Cooking outside was also a new experience, and
  I undercooked the rice pretty woefully.  But after a hard day of
  hiking, any warm food is pretty good.  After that, I set up my
  brand-new hammock for the first time and climbed into my brand-new
  sleeping bag.  The hammock sagged so much that my bum almost touched
  the ground, but I didn&#39;t care &amp;ndash; I was in bed and my journey had
  started.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
