<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged hiking</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/hiking/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/hiking/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/hiking/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-11-16T16:20:05Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>spot-tracks</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/spot-tracks/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/spot-tracks/"/>






	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="spot" />


	<updated>2011-11-16T16:20:05Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-16T16:20:05Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Where I was &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I finally have a Clojurescript application that works basically the
  way I want it to.  It shows a Google Map of the US onto which is
  added a series of markers.  The markers are placed at the positions
  that I sent a SPOT message on one of my hikes.  They are dropped at
  intervals that correspond to the intervals between me sending them
  out.  The whole thing takes a minute to watch.  There are a couple
  of parts where it seems like nothing is happening &amp;ndash; those are
  winter when I wasn&#39;t hiking and a period of time between when the
  SPOT stopped working and when I got the replacement.  The app is
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/spot-tracks/view.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/spot-tracks&quot;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; is on my github page, but it is mostly
  unedifying. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/spot-tracks/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/spot-tracks/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>at-01</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/at-01/"/>






	<category term="AT" />

	<category term="hiking" />


	<updated>2011-11-13T16:05:46Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-13T15:57:32Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Starting on the Appalachian Trail &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This is my first post about hiking, so I think it should be about my
  first days really hiking.  That would be July 1 and 2, 2010.  It
  already seems like an eternity ago, so much has happened since
  then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;July 1 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I had been at a conference in Quebec City in the days leading up to
  July 1.  It had gone well and I had given a talk that I thought was
  pretty well-received.  But more important for me on that day was
  that I had gone to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt; and bought a bunch of backpacking gear.  In
  fact, I had mailed all my possessions home from Germany to Calgary
  the week before, so I was really planning to live on the trail.  I
  had no alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I shaved one last time before my trip, took my new gear, and walked
  to the rental-car agency.  I had booked a car the day before and
  knew it would be open, even though it was Canada Day.  The drive
  from Quebec to Maine was long and pretty boring.  The only
  slightly-eventful thing that happened was that the border guards
  really gave me a hard time, eventually saying something like &quot;Well,
  we have to let him in, he&#39;s a citizen.&quot;  I guess they don&#39;t have
  much to do at that particular crossing, so they make the most of it
  when they get someone with even a slightly strange story.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I arrived in Bangor, Maine and needed to do some food shopping.  I
  knew that I had the dreaded 100-mile wilderness ahead of me, meaning
  that I might not get to a store for 10 days.  The stuff I bought
  then seems rather comical now.  I had a pound of rice and four or
  five Indian meals that were not dehydrated.  Also a full jar of
  peanut butter and a full jar of jelly.  And two different kinds of
  non-dehydrated hummus.  I&#39;m pretty sure it all fit into my
  food bag eventually, but it took some doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I returned the car at the airport and then took the airport bus from
  the airport to the bus terminal.  It turned out that the bus
  terminal was walking distance from the rental-car agency, but I
  didn&#39;t find that out until I was already on the bus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I got to the bus terminal and asked for a ticket to Millinocket.  It
  turned out that I wasn&#39;t the first to do that on that day: two other
  people were already there that were going to the trailhead.  They
  would become known to me as Picker and Grinner, and I would walk
  with them for about 1000 miles.  They obviously knew what they were
  doing.  They had sent their food ahead to the Inn at Millinocket and
  had booked a ride there.  Grinner had also already hiked the trail,
  so I was sure that I was safe tagging along with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  At the inn, I met a couple more people that were starting the same
  day as me: Oblio and his dad.  We had a beer at the bar down the
  street and discussed the trail ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;July 2 &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  After a night of pretty poor sleep (I was excited and there were
  snorers), we got up bright and early at 5:30 the next morning.  The
  inn came with a deal that you get breakfast at the diner, so I met
  up with Oblio and his dad, and we came up with trail names for
  ourselves. Since I had been doing my postdoc in Computational
  Geometry just before the trail, I became known as Dr. Geo.  Oblio&#39;s
  dad was in marketing, and assured me that this was a fine name.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We piled into the innkeeper&#39;s truck and headed for the trail.  The
  first task of a southbound AT thru-hike is to climb Mount Katahdin.
  In fact, the climb doesn&#39;t even count, because the trail starts at
  the top.  Since we would be coming back, we left our full packs at
  the Baxter Park ranger station, and took the loaner day-packs that
  they provide.  That would be the only time that I hiked without my
  full pack over the next 4500 miles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a good thing that we had light packs, because Katahdin is a
  monster.  It is probably the most technical climbing on the trail,
  requiring you to pull yourself up with your hands at many points.
  However, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xaCB5S_gJwWabCsdMwPVU3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;views&lt;/a&gt; are great.  At some points, you &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/om0LnphpOAtHNxIX9QwkqHIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;feel&lt;/a&gt; like you are
  in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8rHwtx0OcApK-34CYXmkM3IQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;airplane&lt;/a&gt;, you can see so far.  There are even great &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ig4QqEE10V3TTXk9BfL9TXIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;waterfalls&lt;/a&gt;
  near the base.  I know some people bathed in the pools beneath the
  falls, but the water was far too cold for me.  However, I did get my
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/betCZRWpaGuJGmFtjulKJnIQdffm0dM4kWIdDklkn2s?feat=directlink&quot;&gt;picture&lt;/a&gt; taken at the summit so that I could prove that I had started
  the trail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We started our hike from the summit back down the mountain.  It was
  even harder going down than going up.  When we got to the bottom,
  everyone was pretty tired.  Especially for the first day of hiking,
  Katahdin is really hard.  We made our camp at Baxter Park.  Of
  course, I was very poorly organized and hadn&#39;t realized that you
  must book a campsite there, so I shared with Oblio and his dad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It was a night of firsts for me.  I hadn&#39;t lit my stove before.  It
  didn&#39;t want to work with my flint, so I had to borrow a lighter.  I
  hadn&#39;t used a water filter before, so I needed to do that for the
  first time as well.  Cooking outside was also a new experience, and
  I undercooked the rice pretty woefully.  But after a hard day of
  hiking, any warm food is pretty good.  After that, I set up my
  brand-new hammock for the first time and climbed into my brand-new
  sleeping bag.  The hammock sagged so much that my bum almost touched
  the ground, but I didn&#39;t care &amp;ndash; I was in bed and my journey had
  started.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/hiking/at-01/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>blogging-about-blogging</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/blogging-about-blogging/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/blogging-about-blogging/"/>






	<category term="blogging" />

	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="git" />

	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2011-11-11T02:13:21Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-11T02:13:21Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;A new system &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This is the obligatory post about how the new blogging system
  works.  Isn&#39;t that exciting?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By my standards, this is a fairly simple system.  It is based on
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ikiwiki.info&quot;&gt;ikiwiki&lt;/a&gt;, which allows me to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://orgmode&quot;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; to edit my posts and &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; as
  the version control system.  Since I already know those tools, I
  don&#39;t have to think about them and can just focus on writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m less comfortable with making web pages look nice, but I took the
  CSS file from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AntPortal/ikiwiked/raw/master/theme/gray-orange/local.css&quot;&gt;the nice people at antportal.com&lt;/a&gt; and added my own
  panoramic photo that I took while hiking.  I think the output is
  simple and looks pretty good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Finally, I am currently hosting the pages on &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;What I intend to write about &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The blog is currently called &quot;Hiking and Coding&quot;.  So far I&#39;ve only
  written about the latter, but I&#39;m planning some posts about the
  former.  My current objective is to write once a day as a way to
  solidify what I&#39;m thinking about for the day, so my posts will
  likely be about what I&#39;m working on.  As such, expect them to be
  really boring.  I&#39;m okay with that.  I&#39;m also okay with you not
  subscribing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I will try to write about adventures I had while hiking on days that
  I&#39;m not really working on anything.  Those posts will be tagged with
  the hiking tag.  They might be more exciting (though they might
  not).
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/blogging-about-blogging/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/blogging-about-blogging/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
