<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged ikiwiki</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/ikiwiki/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/ikiwiki/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/ikiwiki/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-12-07T22:42:09Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Lessons learned (so far) from the ikiwiki plugin</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2011-12-07T22:42:09Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-07T22:00:36Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	
&lt;p&gt;Writing my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/ikiwiki/./../../posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin&quot;&gt;new plugin&lt;/a&gt; in Emacs Lisp, I learned a few things.  Here are
some of them, in no particular order.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;xml-rpc.el has some problems &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I don&#39;t mean to be unkind here.  xml-rpc.el seems pretty good if you
  are doing exactly one kind of thing: calling a method on a server
  that can be reached by http.  For anything else, it is very hard to
  use.   My plugin has the following requirements:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It must be called by another program through xml-rpc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It must read from and write to files (and not http).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;    
  Neither of these things is made easy with xml-rpc.  The first I can
  understand &amp;ndash; xml-rpc would have to somehow insinuate itself into
  the emacs event loop and watch for calls all the time.  The second
  is less easy to understand.  Parsing xml-rpc is not really related
  to reading from http.  So why are the two things tied together?  In
  my opinion, xml-rpc.el would be a much nicer library if parsing the
  xml-rpc was separated completely from the http stuff.  There could
  be convenience functions, but they would be a layer of abstraction
  on top of the other two layers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;xml.el has some problems &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There isn&#39;t a function to get a list of all nodes with a given name?
  Are you kidding me?  Here is my implementation, but I bet there is a
  better one somewhere:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;xml-find-nodes-matching&lt;/span&gt; (node name)
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&quot;Returns all children of `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;node&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39; that have an `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;xml-node-name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39; equal to `&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&#39;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (or (eq node &#39;()) (not (listp node)))
      &#39;()
    (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (equal (xml-node-name node) name)
        (cons node (delq nil (mapcar (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; (nd) (xml-find-nodes-matching nd name)) (xml-node-children node))))
      (delq nil (apply &#39;append (mapcar (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; (nd) (xml-find-nodes-matching nd name)) (xml-node-children node)))))))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  In general, both xml-rpc.el and xml.el use a distressing number of
  calls to &lt;code&gt;car&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;cdaddr&lt;/code&gt; (and all the versions in
  between).  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Perl has some problems &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Ikiwiki sends named parameters as an even-lengthed xml-rpc array
  rather than as an xml-rpc struct.  This is because not all of the
  functions that can be called via xml-rpc take named parameters and I
  guess Perl isn&#39;t smart enough to tell a hash from an even-lengthed
  array.  This isn&#39;t a huge problem, but it does mean that I need to
  convert the input to each of the functions that I write into a hash
  before I use it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Ikiwiki has some problems &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I would like to be able to ignore files that don&#39;t have a particular
  extension.  For &lt;code&gt;htmlify&lt;/code&gt;, this is the way it works by default.  It
  seems like most of the functions that plugins can implement are not
  this way by default, though, and that is a shame.  If the plugin is
  not external &amp;ndash; that is, it is written in Perl &amp;ndash; there is really no
  problem.  The function is called, checks the extension of the source
  file, and returns without doing anything.  However, when the plugin
  is external and the call must happen through xml-rpc, ikiwiki must
  transmit the data via xml-rpc and receive the returned data back via
  xml-rpc.  Unnecessary calls take a lot longer in that context.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So I would like for most calls to &lt;code&gt;hook&lt;/code&gt; to take an optional
  &lt;code&gt;extension&lt;/code&gt; parameter that takes an extension (or even better, a
  regexp), and only call the function if the file name has the same
  extension (or matches the regexp).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;Working with emacs buffers is pretty nice &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Does a function that you&#39;re trying to write in emacs lisp give you a
  string?  It&#39;s pretty easy to throw it in a temporary buffer and then
  tell emacs to do the things that you would normally do while you
  were editing in order to get the proper information out of the
  string.  The &lt;code&gt;with-temporary-buffer&lt;/code&gt; macro makes it especially easy
  to do just that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Getting info from a structured list is easier to do as a recursive function &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  One of the things that took me the longest was to figure out what
  this couple of lines of code was doing:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(setq valtype (car (caddar xml-list))
      valvalue (caddr (caddar xml-list)))  
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  What should the value of &lt;code&gt;xml-list&lt;/code&gt; look like in order to get the
  correct thing out of it?  It turned out that I needed to take the
  &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;cdaddr&lt;/code&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;caddar&lt;/code&gt; of the parsed xml in order to
  get the correct value.  That only worked when ikiwiki was responding
  to a method call, though.  I had a much easier time getting the
  right values out when I simply started using the
  &lt;code&gt;xml-find-nodes-matching&lt;/code&gt; function that I showed above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When you see yourself writing more than a few &lt;code&gt;car&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;cdr&lt;/code&gt; calls
  in a row (or &lt;code&gt;first&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rest&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;nth&lt;/code&gt; calls in Clojure), stop and
  try to write a function that finds what you are looking for.  The
  function doesn&#39;t have to be recursive, but that might be the easiest
  way to do it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-7&quot;&gt;It&#39;s nice when all calls and responses are dumped to a file &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In a sense, this is just saying that code can be easier to debug if
  you&#39;re tracing it.  But since the calls between ikiwiki and the
  plugin must go through files anyway, we get the program traced
  automatically.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin-3/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Plugin for org files in ikiwiki</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin/"/>






	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="ikiwiki-org-plugin" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2011-12-02T23:32:03Z</updated>
	<published>2011-12-02T23:29:47Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;A new plugin &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Ikiwiki users who want to write org-mode files have long only had
  one plugin for ikiwiki to convert their files to html.  That plugin
  is good as it goes, but it is somewhat limited.  Thus, I am happy to
  announce a new plugin for converting org-mode.  It is located in my
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/ikiwiki-org-plugin&quot;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It is still a bit rough around the edges, but it should be
  completely usable very soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/org-ikiwiki-plugin/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Convex Hulls</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/convex-hulls/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/convex-hulls/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="computational-geometry" />

	<category term="convex-hull" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />


	<updated>2011-12-02T22:05:50Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-30T18:06:31Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Convex Hulls Three Ways &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Whenever I watch cooking competition shows, they always have chefs
  presenting a foodstuff cooked in multiple different ways.  Today,
  I&#39;m doing that with algorithms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The algorithm in question today is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull&quot;&gt;convex hull&lt;/a&gt; algorithm.  In
  order of implementation complexity, and descending order of
  theoretical running time, there is the Jarvis March, Graham&#39;s Scan,
  and Chan&#39;s Algorithm.  All three are implemented in Clojure in my
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/convex-hull&quot;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-1&quot;&gt;Jarvis March &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The simplest of the algorithms, the Jarvis March was also one of
   the first output-sensitive computational geometry algorithms.  In a
   nutshell, you first find a point that you know to be on the convex
   hull, and then you find the next point by looking at all the rest
   of the points and determining which one has a segment that has the
   property that all the rest of the points are on one side of it.
   You repeatedly find the next point using this procedure until you
   get back to the first point.  There is basically no way to
   implement this algorithm that does not have a running time of
   \(O(hn)\), where \(h\) is the number of points on the convex hull
   and \(n\) is the number of input points.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   The one implementation detail of the Jarvis March that is
   interesting is that whenever you see the concept of &quot;finding the
   next thing&quot; given some previous information, the Clojure
   implementation should almost always be lazy.  It turns out that
   implementing Jarvis March lazily will help in implementing Chan&#39;s
   Algorithm, so keep that in mind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-2&quot;&gt;Graham&#39;s Scan &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Graham&#39;s Scan is one of the algorithms I remember most vividly from
   the undergraduate computational geometry course that I took.  The
   professor, Godfried Toussaint, always referred to it as the &quot;three
   coins&quot; algorithm, so I have kept up that tradition in some of my
   function names in my implementation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   The algorithm first makes a polygon of the input points by sorting
   them by angle about the bottom-most point.  Then it goes around the
   polygon with a stack, pushing and popping points as it goes.  If
   that sounds familiar, it should &amp;ndash; it&#39;s the same idea as what I was
   talking about when I brought up the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/parsing-polygons/&quot;&gt;parsing polygons&lt;/a&gt; a week
   and a half ago. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Thus, I used the same polygon-parsing monad in my implementation as
   when I computed the visibility polygons last week.  It still works
   just as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Since the points must be sorted, Graham&#39;s Scan takes \(\Theta(n
   \log n)\).  Sorting can be reduced to computing convex hulls, so
   computing convex hulls has a \(\Omega(n \log n)\) lower bound,
   meaning that this algorithm is optimal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   But Chan&#39;s algorithm is better.  Weird huh?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-3&quot;&gt;Chan&#39;s Algorithm &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I must confess that I had always been a little intimidated by
   Chan&#39;s Algorithm.  It was invented by Timothy Chan, who has a
   well-earned reputation for being a genius, so I thought it would be
   really complicated.  It&#39;s not.  There is a decent &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chan&#39;s_algorithm&quot;&gt;description&lt;/a&gt; of it
   on Wikipedia, so I won&#39;t go into the details.  The gist is that you
   combine the two previous algorithms that I discussed.  The Jarvis
   March needs to be modified so that the points can be input as a
   list of smaller convex hulls, and the next point on the convex hull
   is found by doing a binary search on the smaller convex hulls.  But
   that is really the hardest part about the algorithm.  I have put
   the whole thing below, because I think it&#39;s pretty beautiful.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;defn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;chans-algorithm&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;&quot;Finds the convex hull of a set of points by&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8fb28f;&quot;&gt;   the algorithm known as &#39;Chan&#39;s Algorithm&#39;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  [pts]
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; [bottom-pt (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt; min-key &lt;span style=&quot;color: #dca3a3; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;:y&lt;/span&gt; pts)]
   (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt; [m 3] &lt;span style=&quot;color: #708070;&quot;&gt;; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f9f7f;&quot;&gt;start out with triangles&lt;/span&gt;
     (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; [partitioned-pts (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;partition&lt;/span&gt; m m [] pts)
           c-hs (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; grahams-scan partitioned-pts)
           potential-ch (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;take&lt;/span&gt; m (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt; jarvis-march pts c-hs))]
       (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bottom-pt (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;last&lt;/span&gt; potential-ch)) &lt;span style=&quot;color: #708070;&quot;&gt;; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f9f7f;&quot;&gt;assumes jarvis-march returns bottom-pt last&lt;/span&gt;
         potential-ch
         (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #8cd0d3;&quot;&gt;recur&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;min&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; m m) (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #f0dfaf;&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; pts))))))))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
   The great thing about Chan&#39;s Algorithm is that it is also
   output-sensitive.  But instead of being \(O(nh)\) (which is
   \(O(n^2)\) in the worst case), it is \(O(n \log h)\), which is at
   least as good as Graham&#39;s Scan, but often better.  It is also quite
   simple to implement, given decent implementations of Jarvis March
   and Graham&#39;s Scan.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Convex hull algorithms are great.  If I was ever to teach a
  computational geometry course (admittedly that&#39;s looking like a long
  shot now), I might start and finish the course with them.  The
  progression from the ultra-simple Jarvis March to the
  more-complicated Chan&#39;s Algorithm is really nice, and there are
  interesting new things to talk about the whole way.  They also show
  that computational geometry is not so hard to do in a functional
  style.  In fact, using laziness is what makes the implementation of
  Chan&#39;s Algorithm so simple.  So this might make a nice talk to give
  people who are already into functional programming as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next thing I have in mind for this project is to animate the
  algorithms.  Viewing the output of algorithms is already pretty easy
  using Processing, but I would like to be able to see them as they
  are operating.  It would be great if I could do that without
  changing the code too much.  I have a couple of ideas, but I&#39;m not
  sure if they&#39;ll work yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Also, it is slightly embarrassing to admit, but my blogging system
  seems to not support putting images in posts.  So I am going to have
  to figure out how to work around (or even fix) that before I can
  show any results.
&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/convex-hulls/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/convex-hulls/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>
<entry>
	<title>Blogging About Blogging</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/blogging-about-blogging/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/blogging-about-blogging/"/>






	<category term="blogging" />

	<category term="emacs" />

	<category term="git" />

	<category term="hiking" />

	<category term="ikiwiki" />

	<category term="org-mode" />


	<updated>2011-12-01T07:37:21Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-11T02:13:21Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;A new system &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This is the obligatory post about how the new blogging system
  works.  Isn&#39;t that exciting?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By my standards, this is a fairly simple system.  It is based on
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://ikiwiki.info&quot;&gt;ikiwiki&lt;/a&gt;, which allows me to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://orgmode.org&quot;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; to edit my posts and &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; as
  the version control system.  Since I already know those tools, I
  don&#39;t have to think about them and can just focus on writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m less comfortable with making web pages look nice, but I took the
  CSS file from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AntPortal/ikiwiked/raw/master/theme/gray-orange/local.css&quot;&gt;the nice people at antportal.com&lt;/a&gt; and added my own
  panoramic photo that I took while hiking.  I think the output is
  simple and looks pretty good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Finally, I am currently hosting the pages on &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;What I intend to write about &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The blog is currently called &quot;Hiking and Coding&quot;.  So far I&#39;ve only
  written about the latter, but I&#39;m planning some posts about the
  former.  My current objective is to write once a day as a way to
  solidify what I&#39;m thinking about for the day, so my posts will
  likely be about what I&#39;m working on.  As such, expect them to be
  really boring.  I&#39;m okay with that.  I&#39;m also okay with you not
  subscribing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I will try to write about adventures I had while hiking on days that
  I&#39;m not really working on anything.  Those posts will be tagged with
  the hiking tag.  They might be more exciting (though they might
  not).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/blogging-about-blogging/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/blogging-about-blogging/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
