<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" >
<channel>
<title>pages tagged programming</title>
<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/programming/</link>
<description>Hiking and Coding</description>
<item>

	<title>Tail-call optimization in emacs lisp</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/emacs-tco/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/emacs-tco/</link>


	<category>C</category>

	<category>emacs</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>programming</category>


	<pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 10:38:28 -0800</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2012-12-09T18:38:28Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been a while since I wrote about any coding here.  Most of my
coding lately has been done at my job, and while it has been
interesting, it&#39;s not for public consumption.  However, I started a
fun little project last weekend and finished it this weekend: adding
tail-call optimization (TCO) to emacs lisp.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  If you&#39;re not familiar with TCO, it&#39;s not too complicated.  Most
  programming language interpreters (including the CPU) use a stack to
  keep track of the local variables in a function.  When a new
  function is called, its arguments are pushed on the stack before the
  call and read from the stack.  When the function returns, the
  arguments are removed from the stack and the old local variables are
  available just as they were before.  However, in the case where the
  result of the function call is being returned unmodified, this is
  somewhat wasteful: the old local variables are not going to be used
  any more so we could just put the arguments on the stack where the
  old variables were.  We can then just jump into the new function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  
  Using this technique, multiple tail-calls won&#39;t grow the stack, and
  tail-recursive functions (that is, functions that only recurse when
  they are about to return) become a good alternative to loops.  This
  is heavily used in Scheme, where tail-call elimination is part of
  the standard.  Note that the reason this is an optimization isn&#39;t
  speed of execution; it&#39;s more about the amount of memory that is
  used.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Until recently, TCO was not possible at all in emacs lisp.  This is
  because, until recently, all of emacs lisp was dynamically scoped.
  Dynamic scoping essentially means that local variables shadow global
  variables in functions that are called while the local variables are
  in scope.  So if you have global variable &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and function &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; does
  something that depends on &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;, then you can change the behavior of
  &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; when you call it from &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; by setting the value of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; locally.
  This rule, while unconventional, can be quite useful in configuring
  the behavior of the editor.  Anyway, dynamic scoping means that
  before any function returns, all the bound local variables must be
  unbound so that they no longer affect other functions.  This means
  that a function call is almost never followed by a return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  However, emacs 24 added the option to compile files using lexical
  scope (the more common scoping rule that you are probably already
  familiar with if you&#39;ve gotten this far).  There is no need to
  explicitly unbind variables before a return in lexical scope because
  local variables aren&#39;t bound.  Thus we can do TCO on these
  functions.  In short, this is what I added.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Implementation Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  The first thing to decide was where to add the TCO code.  Since
  emacs byte-code doesn&#39;t have the ability to jump into a function, I
  quickly decided that I needed to modify the byte-code interpreter
  instead.  This means going into the C guts of emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first thing I did was to follow the path that a call to a
  lexically-bound function would make from the byte-code interpreter.
  I added all this code plus a &lt;code&gt;goto&lt;/code&gt; statement in case the operation
  that followed the call was a &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;.  It wasn&#39;t a whole lot of
  code, so I was feeling fairly good about things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first problem with this approach is that the emacs stack could
  be a different size from what was needed by the calling function.
  Since the stack is allocated by &lt;code&gt;alloca&lt;/code&gt; (which allocates on the
  processor&#39;s stack), and because there is only one &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; from the
  byte-code interpreter, I thought I would be fine changing the
  &lt;code&gt;alloca&lt;/code&gt; to a combination of &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;free&lt;/code&gt;.  Strangely, when I
  went to recompile the emacs lisp files, I kept getting errors.  This
  left me fairly befuddled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I finally figured it out when I realized the garbage collector was
  looking at the processor&#39;s stack to find variables that are in use.
  Thus to work properly, the emacs stack must be allocated on the
  processor&#39;s stack.  That meant I had to go back to &lt;code&gt;alloca&lt;/code&gt; (or
  modify the garbage collector &amp;ndash; something I was not likely to do
  correctly).  Since the (emacs) stack size could change, the memory
  allocated for it would also need to change.  I needed something that
  let me blow away part of the (CPU) stack &amp;ndash; &lt;code&gt;goto&lt;/code&gt; keeps the stack
  in place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In my spelunking in the emacs C code, I had seen functions &lt;code&gt;setjmp&lt;/code&gt;
  and &lt;code&gt;longjmp&lt;/code&gt; used to implement emacs&#39;s exception mechanism.  I had
  never used these functions before (and with good reason &amp;ndash; if you
  think &lt;code&gt;goto&lt;/code&gt; creates spaghetti code, these functions are much
  worse), but it seemed like they might do what I want.  That is, when
  you call &lt;code&gt;longjmp&lt;/code&gt;, you get the effect of a &lt;code&gt;goto&lt;/code&gt;, but the
  processor&#39;s stack is restored to the state that it was when you were
  at the place that jumped to.  So by using a &lt;code&gt;longjmp&lt;/code&gt; within the
  function, I could allocate the emacs stack on the processor&#39;s stack
  and still do TCO without growing the amount of memory used for each
  tail call.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  By the way, I also learned more about the &lt;code&gt;volatile&lt;/code&gt; keyword than I
  wanted to know, including this beauty:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot;&gt;funargs = *(volatile Lisp_Object *) &amp;amp;funargs;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  That means (as far as I understand it) &quot;put this in memory &lt;b&gt;right now&lt;/b&gt;&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Benefits / Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There is an obvious benefit from this work: people can now write
  tail-recursive functions and not worry about the the size of the
  input causing the function to stop working.  It does, however, have
  some limitations.  It
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only works for lexically-bound functions,
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only works for byte-compiled functions, and
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;could cause problems with debugging.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;    
  I&#39;ve gone through the reasons for the first two, and the third
  should be well known to people who are familiar with TCO.  The main
  reason is that since the function call can&#39;t add to the memory
  usage, it must also not add information about itself to the list of
  function calls displayed in a backtrace.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I am going to test this for a while longer before I release it.
  However, I think it&#39;s really going to work, and it will allow an
  entirely different style of programming in emacs lisp.  That&#39;s
  pretty exciting for me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/emacs-tco/#comments</comments>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
