<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" >
<channel>
<title>pages tagged clojure</title>
<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/clojure/</link>
<description>Hiking and Coding</description>
<item>

	<title>processing</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/processing/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/processing/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>processing</category>

	<category>visibility-polygon</category>


	<pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 12:29:29 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-22T21:00:04Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Viewing visibility polygons &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I mentioned yesterday that it would be nice to see the output of my
  visibility polygon solution.  To that end, I created an extremely
  simple drawing editor using &lt;a href=&quot;http://processing.org/&quot;&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt;.  I have to say, I loved it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most important feature to me is the extreme interactivity.  I
  can change functions extremely quickly with my tools &amp;ndash; redefining a
  Clojure function is either one or two keystrokes in emacs, depending
  how I choose to do it &amp;ndash; so I like a graphics environment that
  changes just as quickly.  This is what Processing, and in particular
  &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;, offers.  I was able to define a function that
  draws the various objects (in this case, the polygon, the point
  where the mouse is, and the visibility polygon of the mouse point
  inside the polygon).  If I wanted to make any changes to this
  function &amp;ndash; for example, changing the color of the point where the
  mouse is &amp;ndash; I can simply redefine the function using my emacs tools
  and the change shows up immediately on the drawing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was able to use this to find a couple of minor bugs in my
  visibility-polygon-finding code, but in general, it worked really
  well on the first try.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-1-1&quot;&gt;Shortcomings &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-1-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   There were a couple of things that slightly bothered me about
   &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;.  First, it used quite a lot of CPU just to
   display a simple polygon without too many points.  I am probably
   using it rather naïvely, so it is possible that this is my problem
   and not the problem of &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt;.  However, the second
   problem is just that &lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt; is showing its age.  I think
   it was probably one of the first Clojure libraries out there and
   much of the coding style hasn&#39;t evolved with the Clojure best
   practices that people use.  For example, some of the features do
   not work if you only &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; the library &amp;ndash; you must &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; it.  I
   try to only &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; libraries, to avoid my namespace becoming
   overly populated, so it is frustrating when that doesn&#39;t work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Going forward &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I need to clean up the code a bit before I can put it up on github,
  but it should be there soon.  It currently needs me to explicitly
  call the function in order to find the visibility polygon.  I would
  really like it to find the visibility polygon of any point where the
  mouse is inside the polygon.  However, determining if a point is
  inside a non-convex polygon tends to be a bit harder than it
  sounds.  You can shoot a ray in one direction from a point, and
  count the number of polygon edges that it crosses &amp;ndash; if it&#39;s even
  you are outside and if it&#39;s odd you are inside &amp;ndash; but what happens
  if the ray crosses a vertex?  There was a good experimental paper on
  this problem at a recent EuroCG.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So that&#39;s a slightly non-trivial problem.  I also coded an
  implementation of the Voronoi Diagram problem recently.  I should
  add a Processing UI to that as well.  I have a feeling that would be
  the easier task to do next, and I would surely discover some bugs in
  it while I did.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/processing/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>visibility-polygon</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/visibility-polygon/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/visibility-polygon/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>computational-geometry</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>visibility-polygon</category>


	<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 12:44:43 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-21T19:58:03Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Visibility Polygon &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;ve put up some preliminary code for finding visibility polygons on
  my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/visibility-polygon&quot;&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt;.  I have only tested it with one polygon, but so far
  things are looking good.  My idea from yesterday of using monads to
  &quot;parse&quot; the polygon seems to be paying off.  Here is the relevant
  code:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defn- add-new-pt [poly]
  (fn [pt stack]
    (when (or (empty? stack) ; First two points are guaranteed to be visible
              (empty? (rest stack))
              (visible? pt (first poly) (first stack)))
      [pt (rest poly) (cons (first poly) stack)])))

(defn- pop-stack [poly]
  (fn [pt stack]
    (let [the-seg (seg/new-seg pt (first poly))
          top-seg (seg/new-seg (first stack) (second stack))]
      (when (pt/left-turn? (second stack) (first stack) (first poly))
        (if (seg/intersection-on-seg? the-seg top-seg)
          [pt poly (cons (seg/intersection the-seg top-seg) stack)]
          [pt poly (rest stack)])))))

(defn- skip-pt [poly]
  (fn [pt stack]
   (let [the-seg (seg/new-seg pt (first stack))
         poly-seg (seg/new-seg (first poly) (second poly))]
     (when (not (pt/left-turn? (second stack) (first stack) (first poly)))
       (if (seg/intersection-on-seg? the-seg poly-seg)
         [pt (cons (seg/intersection the-seg poly-seg) (rest poly)) stack]
         [pt (rest poly) stack])))))

(defn- all-conditions [poly]
  (with-monad polygon-parser-m
    (m-plus (add-new-pt poly) (pop-stack poly) (skip-pt poly))))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  This defines three actions to be performed when the polygon and
  stack are in certain configurations.  The first executes when the
  next point on the polygon doesn&#39;t obscure any of the stack.  In that
  case, it removes the point from &lt;code&gt;poly&lt;/code&gt; and puts it on &lt;code&gt;stack&lt;/code&gt;.  The
  second executes by popping points off the stack until the next point
  on the polygon no longer obscures the stack.  The final condition
  activates when the next point on the polygon is hidden by the
  stack.  It skips the points of &lt;code&gt;poly&lt;/code&gt; until it finds one that would
  be visible.  We combine the three conditions using &lt;code&gt;m-plus&lt;/code&gt;, which
  is defined to try the conditions in order until one returns
  something that is not &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Is this solution any better than a functional programming solution
  without monads?  I think it is.  First, the conditions are easy to
  see and very explicitly laid out.  Using a &lt;code&gt;cond&lt;/code&gt; to accomplish the
  same thing is certainly possible, but gets more complicated as the
  number of conditions grows.  Also, we are explicitly managing state
  in this solution.  Doing so in an ad-hoc manner would be much more
  difficult.  In fact, I am not really sure how I would loop until
  there are no more points in &lt;code&gt;poly&lt;/code&gt; in a solution without monads
  (especially since not all the conditions consume a point from
  &lt;code&gt;poly&lt;/code&gt;).  With monads, it is quite simple:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defn- visibility-polygon-helper [pt poly]
  ((with-monad polygon-parser-m
     (m-until empty? all-conditions poly)) pt []))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  Doing something like that with a &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; seems like it would veer
  off into unreadability fairly quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Are there downsides to this solution?  I think there is at least
  one.  That is, the conditions must be functions that return functions.
  This makes them a bit more confusing than they really should be.  I
  needed to do this so that I could have a test in the &lt;code&gt;m-until&lt;/code&gt;
  function above.  On the whole, though, this is a fairly cosmetic
  gripe, and can be hidden by using helper functions like the one
  above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;On the horizon &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I would like to test the code quite a bit more.  However, doing so
  by drawing out polygons by hand and then figuring out their
  visibility polygons is quite tedious.  Therefore, I need some sort
  of GUI to be able to draw polygons and then I will be able to
  see whether the computed visibility polygon makes sense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I am thinking that it might be nice to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rosado/clj-processing&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;clj-processing&lt;/code&gt; library&lt;/a&gt; to do this.  Unfortunately, that library is currently only
  using Clojure 1.2.  Since I am using Clojure 1.3, that might be a
  problem.  So I might need to do some porting from 1.2 to 1.3.
  However, doing so should give me a good idea of how processing
  works, and could give a nice tool for more interactive geometry
  programs. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/visibility-polygon/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>luhnybin</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/luhnybin/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/luhnybin/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>programming-challenge</category>

	<category>thrush</category>


	<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 13:22:19 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-15T22:18:05Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Another programming challenge &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I woke up with another programming challenge in my inbox this
  morning.  This one is from &lt;a href=&quot;http://squareup.com&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/a&gt;.  They are a company that gives
  you a little device so that you can accept credit cards using a
  smart phone.  The challenge is &lt;a href=&quot;http://corner.squareup.com/2011/11/luhny-bin.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; basically it&#39;s about removing
  credit cards numbers from logs.  There are some details about what
  constitutes a credit card number, and how they are distinct from
  other numbers.  I won&#39;t repeat that here, but you should read it to
  understand what&#39;s coming up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As usual, I implemented my solution in Clojure.  I particularly
  liked the function I called &lt;code&gt;luhn-check&lt;/code&gt;.  Here it is:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defn luhn-check
  &lt;span&gt;&quot;Takes a sequence of digits and determines whether they pass the Luhn test.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;   The sequence must be in order from right to left.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  [digits]
  (-&amp;gt;&amp;gt; digits
       (partition 2 2 (repeat 0))
       (mapcat #(vector (first %) (* 2 (second %))))
       (reduce #(+ %1 (int (/ %2 10)) (int (mod %2 10))))
       (#(mod % 10))
       (= 0)))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  I think this is a good illustration of the &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; operator in
  Clojure, which is also called the &quot;thrush&quot; operator.  Basically,
  this operator can be thought of as taking the result from one
  expression and putting it at the end of the next expression.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In this case, we start out with a list of digits.  We then partition
  them into pairs, padding with a zero if necessary.  We then take the
  pairs and double the second number in the pair, concatenating all
  the pairs back into a single list.  We then sum up all the digits in
  the list, using the &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; function.  This leaves us with a
  number.  We get its value \(\mod 10\) and test whether it is equal
  to zero.  If it is, we return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, otherwise we return &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  All of this could be written with nested expressions (and the thrush
  operator is simply a macro that rewrites what you see as nested
  expressions), but I think the way it is written nicely shows what
  the data is doing in the function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Anyway, I don&#39;t know if this solution will get me a job, but it was
  a bit of fun coding and didn&#39;t take too long.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/luhnybin/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>scattered</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/scattered/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/scattered/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>clojurescript</category>

	<category>email</category>

	<category>git</category>

	<category>git-annex</category>

	<category>notmuch</category>

	<category>spot</category>


	<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:11:23 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-14T18:14:04Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Scattered &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I am doing a bunch of things today, all fairly small.  I think it&#39;s
  because I finished working on the time series framework yesterday,
  so I&#39;m kind of at loose ends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;New programming project &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  One thing that I would like to do is to take all the messages that I
  sent with my &lt;a href=&quot;http://findmespot.com&quot;&gt;SPOT&lt;/a&gt; device while hiking and make a small animation of
  them on Google Maps.  This would be another use of Clojurescript.
  My previous project &amp;ndash; a Clojurescript program for computing the
  Voronoi Diagram of a set of points input by a user &amp;ndash; is a bit
  stalled at the moment, so it&#39;s good to have something else to work
  on.  Also, I feel like adding points to a Google Map is something
  that Clojurescript is better suited to, rather than the fiddly
  numeric stuff that I was trying to make it do.  I will come back to
  the Voronoi Diagram at some point (hopefully fairly soon), but I am
  putting it on the back burner for the moment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So far, I see two major tasks:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-1&quot;&gt;Getting the coordinates and times of the SPOT messages &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Every SPOT message is an email that contains the coordinates of
   where and when the message was sent.  Parsing the email can be done
   offline, so I will probably just use Clojure for that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-2&quot;&gt;Putting them on the Google Map &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/apis/maps/documentation/javascript/overlays.html#Markers&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt; for using Google Maps appears to be easy to use and
   well-thought-out.  There&#39;s even a way to drop the markers at
   different intervals &amp;ndash; just what I want to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Notmuch &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I am also playing with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://notmuch.org&quot;&gt;notmuch&lt;/a&gt; email client.  So far I quite
  like it.  It&#39;s a heck of a lot faster than my previous mail client,
  mainly because it doesn&#39;t do as much.  Like gmail, it is optimized
  towards two operations: searching and tagging.  I never really used
  tags in gmail, because doing so involves clicking around, but it&#39;s
  much faster in notmuch.  So far, this seems like the big advantage
  for notmuch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Git annex &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In an effort to use all the software written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://joey.kitenet.net/&quot;&gt;Joey Hess&lt;/a&gt; (not
  really, but it seems like it), I am also trying out &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-annex.branchable.com/&quot;&gt;git annex&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So far, I have come up with one really compelling use case --
  syncing podcasts to my mp3 player.  My mp3 player has the problem
  that it will delete all the files on it at random times.  Thus, I
  need to keep a backup of all the files on it on my computer.
  However, when I am done listening to a podcast, I like to remove the
  file.  Hopefully, I will be able to sync the files that I remove
  myself (that is, remove them from the laptop), but not the files
  that get removed by the stupid thing crashing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another thing that I would like to do is put my music and video
  collections in git annex.  I&#39;m not sure that anything special would
  come from doing that, but it seems nice to have these things in
  version control.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/scattered/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>time-series-2</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/time-series-2/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/time-series-2/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>programming-challenge</category>

	<category>time-series</category>


	<pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 07:12:16 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-15T20:22:53Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;What we have so far &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Well, yesterday was either a very productive day or a very lucky day
  for me.  I read up on monads &amp;ndash; I found that &lt;a href=&quot;http://onclojure.com/2009/03/05/a-monad-tutorial-for-clojure-programmers-part-1/&quot;&gt;khinsen&#39;s tutorials&lt;/a&gt; and
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://intensivesystems.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/tutorials/monads_101.html&quot;&gt;Jim Duey&#39;s tutorials&lt;/a&gt; complemented each other nicely.  Then I went
  for a long run (about 18 miles I think) and let the ideas sink in.
  When I got home, I found &lt;code&gt;state-m&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;m-seq&lt;/code&gt; and the job was
  almost done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Just as a reminder, &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/time-series-1&quot;&gt;yesterday&#39;s task&lt;/a&gt; was to build a time-series
  framework where a function \(f\) accepts the previous \(n\) outputs of
  \(f\) as input to generate a new output.  Here is my solution, edited
  for clarity (the actual solution is in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/chrismgray/time-series&quot;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt;):
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defn time-series [f init-state n num-iterations]
 (let [call-f (fn [state]
                (let [retval (f state)
                      num (count state)
                      new-state (vec (if (= num n) (drop 1 (conj state retval)) (conj state retval)))]
                  [retval new-state]))]
   ((with-monad state-m
      (m-seq (repeat num-iterations call-f)))
    (vector init-state))))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  As you can see, the heavy lifting is done by the &lt;code&gt;state&lt;/code&gt; monad and
  by &lt;code&gt;m-seq&lt;/code&gt;.  What do they do?  Well, &lt;code&gt;m-seq&lt;/code&gt; can be thought of as
  taking a list of functions and calling them in order, returning a
  list of their return values.  The list of functions in this case is
  the same function (&lt;code&gt;call-f&lt;/code&gt;) over and over.  All &lt;code&gt;call-f&lt;/code&gt; does is
  call \(f\) and change the state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It might appear that &lt;code&gt;call-f&lt;/code&gt; is an \(O(n)\) function.  After all, we
  call &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; on the state, which is a vector of at most \(n\)
  elements.  However, almost all the behind-the-scenes data structures
  that Clojure uses (including the vector data structure) are
  guaranteed to have \(O(1)\) performance for calling &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;.  So
  that&#39;s nice, and &lt;code&gt;call-f&lt;/code&gt; has the performance characteristics that I
  desired.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Monads &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  They&#39;re still a slightly confusing and magical-seeming thing to me,
  but monads have some obvious utility.  I guess the way to think
  about them is that if you put your input and output in a common
  format, then they aid you in stringing functions together very
  easily.  I used them in this case to encapsulate state, and that is
  probably the most common use of them in Clojure (judging by the
  number of state functions in the Clojure monads library).  However,
  I think I should probably try to understand all the monads in the
  library and know how to combine them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I could have written the function above without monads, but the code
  would not have been nearly as concise, and there probably would have
  been many more edge-cases to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;The rest &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I also wrote some stuff to make debugging easier, and used incanter
  to compare multiple time series.  However, neither required me to
  bend my brain as much as monads, so I won&#39;t talk about them very
  much.  In fact, not at all, because that is the end of my post.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/time-series-2/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>time-series-1</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/time-series-1/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/time-series-1/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>programming-challenge</category>

	<category>time-series</category>


	<pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 09:27:15 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-15T20:22:37Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Programming challenges &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  One of the interesting aspects of looking for a job this time around
  is that most of the companies that I have applied at have asked me
  to do a programming challenge as a kind of weed-out step.  It has
  been fun and a good way of keeping in practice.  In fact, I have
  resolved to learn at least one new feature of the programming
  language that I am using for each one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Time series framework &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  My latest programming challenge is to build a framework for &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_series&quot;&gt;time series&lt;/a&gt; generation.  The framework will take a function \(f\) that
  looks at the \(n\) previous timesteps and returns the next timestep.
  The other goals are:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency

&lt;p&gt;    
    Adding a new timestep should be a \(O(1)\) operation.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ease of debugging

&lt;p&gt;    
    If an error occurs in computing the next timestep, the stack trace
    should be easily comprehensible and show the current state of the
    time series.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traceability

&lt;p&gt;    
    It should be possible to see the differences between two different
    functions.  
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Ideas so far &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This seems like the perfect time to learn about &lt;a href=&quot;http://onclojure.com/2009/03/05/a-monad-tutorial-for-clojure-programmers-part-1/&quot;&gt;monads&lt;/a&gt;.  Yikes!
  I&#39;ve tried before, but have never seen a practical use for them.  As
  far as I understand so far, they should be very good for storing the
  state (&lt;i&gt;i.e.&lt;/i&gt; the previous \(n\) timesteps).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  A simpler solution might be just to use lazy sequences.  There&#39;s not
  much to such a solution, so I might just implement it first and then
  try to replicate it with monads.  In this solution, the previous \(n\)
  timesteps are simply the last \(n\) elements of the lazy sequence.
  Getting those elements might be tough to do in constant time, but I
  have a feeling it&#39;s possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  On the debugging front, there shouldn&#39;t be too much complexity: it
  should just be a combination of &lt;code&gt;try&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;catch&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;throw&lt;/code&gt;.
  There&#39;s also &lt;code&gt;clojure.stacktrace&lt;/code&gt; if I want to get even fancier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As far as tracing goes, I might have a look at &lt;code&gt;tools.trace&lt;/code&gt; to see
  if there&#39;s anything interesting there that I can use.  I think that
  monads might provide another way of doing the same thing.  We&#39;ll see
  which is simpler.  It might also be nice to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://incanter.org&quot;&gt;incanter&lt;/a&gt; to display
  the differences between two (or more) different functions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  On to the coding!
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/time-series-1/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>cljs-name-resolving-2</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-name-resolving-2/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-name-resolving-2/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>clojurescript</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>rationals</category>


	<pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2011 18:07:52 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-12T01:28:40Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Done! &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I was close with my guess in the last post.  What ended up working
  was
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(let [name (munge (symbol (str (-&amp;gt; env :ns :name) &lt;span&gt;&quot;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (munge (str sym)))))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  For some reason, &lt;code&gt;(name sym)&lt;/code&gt; would crash the compiler from the
  &lt;code&gt;parse&lt;/code&gt; method but it wouldn&#39;t from other functions caled from the
  &lt;code&gt;parse&lt;/code&gt; method.  I finally gave up worrying about that and just used
  &lt;code&gt;(str sym)&lt;/code&gt; instead, since that is guaranteed to be the same in this
  case &amp;ndash; there is an &lt;code&gt;(assert (not (namespace sym)))&lt;/code&gt; just before the
  &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; line.  I gave up on worrying about it, but someone who knows
  more about the compiler than me might want to try to figure out why
  it is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I also needed to allow names defined in &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt; but redefined in
  another namespace to be called or referred to.  This involved
  changing the &lt;code&gt;resolve-existing-var&lt;/code&gt; function.  Again, &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt; is
  hardcoded:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(let [full-ns (if (and (core-name? env sym) (nil? (get-in @namespaces [(-&amp;gt; env :ns :name) :defs sym])))
                &#39;cljs.core
                (-&amp;gt; env :ns :name))]
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  I added the second test: it simply asks whether the variable has
  been defined in the namespace.  If it hasn&#39;t, and the variable is
  defined in &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;, only then is the namespace set to
  &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Remove the macros &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It was also necessary to remove many of the macros from &lt;code&gt;core.clj&lt;/code&gt;
  in order to redefine the functions that I needed to in my project.
  As I noted earlier, my project is to implement rationals in
  Clojurescript, so I need to redefine most of the functions that work
  with numbers.  (At least, that is the way I am implementing it --
  there may be a better way that I don&#39;t know about.)  Many of these
  functions were implemented twice: once as a macro in &lt;code&gt;core.clj&lt;/code&gt; and
  once as a function in &lt;code&gt;core.cljs&lt;/code&gt;.  I am obviously biased towards
  being able to redefine these functions, so I think the macros should
  be removed, but at least one of the implementations is redundant.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/cljs-name-resolving-2/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>cljs-name-resolving</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-name-resolving/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/cljs-name-resolving/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>clojurescript</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>rationals</category>


	<pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2011 07:23:38 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-12T01:25:21Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Resolving names as they are compiled in Clojurescript &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I think I found the bug in the Clojurescript compiler that I was
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/more-rationals&quot;&gt;looking for yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.  Just to refresh the memory, when defining a
  function that has a function of the same name in &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;, the
  compiler will assume that you are trying to redefine the function
  from &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;, rather than the function in the namespace that you
  are actually in.  Since I am trying to redefine functions like &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;
  and &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;, this is a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Let&#39;s look at the evidence.  First, there&#39;s this:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(defmethod parse &#39;def
  [op env form name]
  (let [pfn (fn ([_ sym] {:sym sym})
              ([_ sym init] {:sym sym :init init})
              ([_ sym doc init] {:sym sym :doc doc :init init}))
        args (apply pfn form)
        sym (:sym args)]
    (assert (not (namespace sym)) &lt;span&gt;&quot;Can&#39;t def ns-qualified name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
    (let [name (munge (:name (resolve-var (dissoc env :locals) sym)))
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  The important line there is the last: when defining a new name,
  &lt;code&gt;resolve-var&lt;/code&gt; is called on the symbol.  Let&#39;s have a look at that
  function.  There is a &lt;code&gt;cond&lt;/code&gt;, and when none of the tests return
  true, the following is done:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(munge (symbol (str
                (if (core-name? env sym)
                  &#39;cljs.core
                  (-&amp;gt; env :ns :name))
                &lt;span&gt;&quot;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (munge (name sym))))))]
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  This is seeing if the symbol name is in &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;, and if it is
  setting the namespace of the symbol to &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt;.  Normally that
  would be correct &amp;ndash; one doesn&#39;t want to need to &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt; in
  every file &amp;ndash; but it doesn&#39;t allow for redefinition of functions
  that are in &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt; (at least without completely shadowing
  them).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;What to do &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So what can we do about this?  The first thing that seems odd to me
  is that the symbol being defined is being resolved first.  Every
  symbol that is defined is defined within its own namespace, so there
  should be no need to resolve it.  That suggests that we should be
  able to take the part of &lt;code&gt;resolve-var&lt;/code&gt; that doesn&#39;t have a special
  case for &lt;code&gt;cljs.core&lt;/code&gt; and put it into the &lt;code&gt;parse&lt;/code&gt; method.  Something
  like
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-clojure&quot;&gt;(let [name (munge (:name (symbol (str (-&amp;gt; env :ns :name) &lt;span&gt;&quot;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt; (munge (name sym))))))])
&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
  might work in the &lt;code&gt;parse&lt;/code&gt; method.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/cljs-name-resolving/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>more-rationals</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/more-rationals/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/more-rationals/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>clojurescript</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>rationals</category>


	<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 09:55:06 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-12T01:24:52Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;More about rationals &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  While attempting to implement &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/rationals-in-cljs/&quot;&gt;support for rationals&lt;/a&gt; yesterday, I
  stumbled on what is (or at least, seems to me to be) a bug in the
  Clojure compiler itself.  That is, one can not refer to the function
  &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; in namespaces other than &lt;code&gt;clojure.core&lt;/code&gt;.  Now, this is probably
  the first time that anyone has wanted to do this, so it&#39;s not
  surprising that no one had seen the bug before.  But what was
  surprising to me was that I could fix it fairly easily.  I submitted
  my patch, and I should be a real-life contributor to Clojure pretty
  soon.  As a person who doesn&#39;t see himself as a compiler guy, that&#39;s
  pretty exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next problem that I&#39;m having is that redefining the basic
  arithmetic operations does not seem to work properly in
  Clojurescript.  The compiled javascript is trying (at least as far
  as I can tell) to redefine &lt;code&gt;cljs.core/+&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;rationals/+&lt;/code&gt;,
  for example.  This is the problem that I am going to try to solve
  today.  
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/more-rationals/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>rationals-followup</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/rationals-followup/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/rationals-followup/</link>


	<category>clojure</category>

	<category>clojurescript</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>rationals</category>


	<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 15:03:16 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-12T01:24:45Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;A small followup &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  My previous post said that I would be using the macros defined in
  Clojurescript&#39;s &lt;code&gt;core.clj&lt;/code&gt;.  It turns out that doesn&#39;t make a lot of
  sense.  I am using the functions defined in &lt;code&gt;core.cljs&lt;/code&gt; instead.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/rationals-followup/#comments</comments>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
