<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" >
<channel>
<title>pages tagged visibility-polygon</title>
<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/visibility-polygon/</link>
<description>Hiking and Coding</description>
<item>

	<title>parsing-polygons</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/parsing-polygons/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/parsing-polygons/</link>


	<category>computational-geometry</category>

	<category>lab-notes</category>

	<category>visibility-polygon</category>


	<pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2011 17:58:28 -0700</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2011-11-21T01:16:32Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Functional programming &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;ve gotten a bit obsessed by functional programming over the last
  couple of years.  I have even seriously thought about writing a book
  that looks at computational geometry (which is the subject in which
  I was trained) in the light of functional programming.  Most of the
  standard computational-geometry texts these days approach the
  writing of code from an imperative standpoint.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I think functional programming is a good way to think about
  computational geometry for a couple of reasons.  First, most
  problems in computational geometry can be expressed in a purely
  functional manner.  That is, the answers to the problems are usually
  the same given the same inputs.  Secondly, I have bought into the
  idea that parallel and distributed computing are much easier when
  state is not being modified.  Functional programming forces you to
  think this way.  While many problems in computational geometry are
  inherently sequential, not all of them are.  Using a programming
  method that allows for the easy addition of more cores seems like a
  good practice when a problem is encountered that is easily made
  parallel. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  One of the things I have been thinking about as a final chapter for
  the book that I would like to write is the introduction of monads as
  a way to &quot;parse&quot; polygons.  Monads are commonly used (well, commonly
  in the functional programming world) to parse strings.  They
  generally scan through with the aid of a stack.  There are many
  algorithms that scan through the points of a polygon with a stack --
  the example that I have thought about the most is the visibility
  polygon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Visibility polygons &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  A &lt;i&gt;visibility polygon&lt;/i&gt; is the subset of a polygon that can be &quot;seen&quot;
  from a point inside the polygon.  Here, we regard the segments of
  the polygon as opaque walls.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The standard algorithm for computing the visibility polygon is not
  too difficult to implement in an imperative language.  In fact, I
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.win.tue.nl/~cgray/ipelets.html&quot;&gt;implemented&lt;/a&gt; it already in C++ for the drawing editor &lt;a href=&quot;http://tclab.kaist.ac.kr/ipe/&quot;&gt;ipe&lt;/a&gt;.  (Though I
  think that code is now obsolete since the release of ipe 7.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;ve already tipped my hand at how I would think about implementing
  such an algorithm in a functional language.  I would use a variant
  of a monadic parser to go through the polygon and find the parts
  that are visible.  (That last sentence doesn&#39;t give much of a hint
  about how it&#39;s done, but the whole algorithm would take too much
  space to describe.  Suffice it to say that a stack is kept with the
  &quot;currently visible&quot; portion of the polygon always on the stack.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Monads &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I used monads &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com/posts/time-series-2/&quot;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; to make a framework for creating and comparing
  time-series.  However, I only used a monad that was already defined
  by someone else.  I think I might need to define a monad on my own
  this time &amp;ndash; a slightly daunting idea.  I definitely need to read
  the rest of &lt;a href=&quot;http://intensivesystems.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/tutorials/monads_201.html&quot;&gt;Jim Duey&#39;s tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to make sense of how to do it.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/parsing-polygons/#comments</comments>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
