<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged sort</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/sort/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/sort/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/sort/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-11-27T17:07:34Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>clojure-sorting</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-sorting/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/clojure-sorting/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="lab-notes" />

	<category term="sort" />


	<updated>2011-11-27T17:07:34Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-27T14:23:34Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Penance &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In a job interview last week I said a couple of things related to
  sorting in Clojure that turned out to be incorrect when I checked
  them.  This is my way of making up for them &amp;ndash; if I can make them
  true, then no one will notice.  Though to be fair, I&#39;m sure that I&#39;m
  the only one that thinks that way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first thing I said was that heap-sort is my favorite sorting
  algorithm, but then I declined to implement it, preferring to
  implement merge-sort instead.  I think this is actually pretty
  reasonable in an interview situation &amp;ndash; heap-sort is a conceptually
  more difficult sorting algorithm, so being able to remember it on
  the spot is more difficult.  The second thing I said was that
  Clojure itself uses heap-sort and that given its love affair with
  laziness that it would not be unreasonable to assume that &lt;code&gt;(first   (sort lst))&lt;/code&gt; was a linear-time operation.  I might have read
  something like this on a mailing list or IRC, but it is not
  correct.  Clojure currently uses Java&#39;s &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt; function, which is a
  slightly-modified merge-sort.  There is not much point in making
  that algorithm lazy, because getting the first element from the
  sorted list requires \(O(n \log n)\) time anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Heap Sort &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  For those that are not familiar with it, heap-sort is something that
  is usually taught in a second-year undergraduate Computer Science
  class.  So it&#39;s not &lt;b&gt;that&lt;/b&gt; difficult an algorithm, but it does
  require some thinking, and there is some fancy analysis that goes
  into part of it.  For a full discussion, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0262033844/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=217145&amp;amp;creative=399369&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0262033844&quot;&gt;Introduction to Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; book by Cormen, Lieserson, Rivest, and Stein.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-1&quot;&gt;Heap &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   To start with, a &lt;i&gt;heap&lt;/i&gt; is conceptually a tree where values are
   stored at the nodes.  The largest value of all the values stored in
   subtrees is stored at the root and the two descendant trees are
   heaps.  Heaps are usually required to be as close to balanced as
   possible &amp;ndash; if any level of the tree has leaves, they are all
   bunched to the right, and all the rest of the leaves are at the
   next level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Such a tree is usually implemented as an array, where the child
   nodes of a node can be obtained by some simple arithmetic on the
   index of the node in the array.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-2&quot;&gt;Building a Heap &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Given the definition, there is an intuitive algorithm for building
   such a heap on a set of numbers: first find the largest number in
   your set and have it be the root of the heap, then split the rest
   of the numbers in half, and recursively make heaps on those sets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Such an algorithm is clearly correct, but it is also clearly
   \(\Theta(n \log n)\).  We can do better with a bottom-up algorithm.
   If we continue imagining the heap as a tree, we start by putting
   the input numbers into the tree willy-nilly.  This clearly does not
   satisfy the heap properties laid out above.  However, some of it
   does satisfy the heap properties &amp;ndash; the leaves of the tree are
   trivially heaps.  If we go up one level from the leaves, we can fix
   the trees rooted there by exchanging the root of the tree with its
   largest child (or not exchanging it if it&#39;s already the largest of
   the three).  Higher levels are a bit more difficult, because if the
   root of a tree is exchanged, then we must make sure to fix the tree
   that it ends up being the root of.  You can imagine the root of a
   tree traveling down the heap until it is larger than both of its
   children.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   The correctness of this algorithm is a bit harder to see and it
   also appears to take \(O(n \log n)\) time.  It does, but there is a
   slightly more sophisticated analysis that shows that it is really
   \(\Theta(n)\).  I won&#39;t go into the analysis, but a hint is that
   most of the values don&#39;t actually travel very far in the tree.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-3&quot;&gt;Using a heap to sort &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   With the heap properties in mind, we can easily see how to get the
   largest value of a set of numbers &amp;ndash; just take the top element from
   the heap.  How can we use the heap properties to sort?  Well, we
   want the largest number, then the largest number that remains, then
   the largest number that remains after that, and so on.  So if we
   can take the largest number from the heap and then fix the heap so
   that it retains the heap properties, then we&#39;d be done.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   We just devised a way to fix heaps when building the heap, so we
   use that.  What we do is to take the very last node in the heap
   (which is not necessarily the smallest, but it doesn&#39;t hurt to
   think about it as the smallest) and put that at the top of the
   heap.  The resulting tree is clearly not a heap, but if we call the
   algorithm to fix heaps on the root of the tree, then we end up with
   a heap again.  The node that we put on top of the heap might end up
   traveling all the way to the bottom, so this update takes
   \(\Theta(\log n)\) time.  Thus if we sort the entire input set, we
   have a \(\Theta(n \log n)\) algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-4&quot;&gt;Advantages &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   That&#39;s the best we can do theoretically, which is great, but the
   Java &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt; algorithm is also \(\Theta(n \log n)\), so why is there
   any advantage to using heap-sort?  In a language where laziness is
   embraced (such as Clojure), heap-sort can be made lazy.  That is,
   the next element of the sorted list can be computed only when it is
   needed.  Since the build-heap procedure described above takes
   linear time, getting the first element from the sorted list takes
   \(O(n)\) time.  Each subsequent element then takes \(O(\log n)\)
   time.  Thus, if only a small number of elements from the sorted
   list are needed, then this lazy version of heap-sort is
   theoretically faster than other sorts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   I can think of situations where this would actually have practical
   advantages.  For example, what if you were writing a search engine
   and wanted to obtain the \(k\) best results?  You could write an
   ad-hoc function that found the best result, removed it and recursed
   \(k - 1\) times.  Or you could just &lt;code&gt;(take k (heap-sort input))&lt;/code&gt;.
   The first would take \(O(kn)\) time, whereas the second would take
   \(O(k \log n + n)\) time.  In many practical situations, \(k\) is
   \(O(\log n)\), which means that the first takes \(O(n \log n)\)
   time, whereas the second takes only \(O(n)\) time.  Essentially,
   the first is no better than the second solution with a non-lazy
   sorting algorithm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-5&quot;&gt;Disadvantages &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Heap-sort has some disadvantages compared to other sorts of &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt;
   algorithms.  The least theoretically significant is that the
   constants hidden in the big-O notation are higher than other
   sorting algorithms (tuned versions of quicksort can have extremely
   small constants).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   Another disadvantage can be seen when dealing with data sets so
   large that they no longer fit in the computer&#39;s main memory.
   Something like merge-sort can be modified fairly easily so that the
   number I/O operations is minimized.  I haven&#39;t thought about it too
   deeply, but this doesn&#39;t seem quite so easy with heap-sort.
   However, I think that people dealing with such large datasets
   should probably be using specialized libraries anyway, so perhaps
   that isn&#39;t too bad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Implementation &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  This whole discussion is a bit useless if it only remains at the
  theoretical level.  I have an implementation &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chrismgray/clojure-heap-sort&quot;&gt;in my github repo&lt;/a&gt; that
  implements most of the ideas that are given above.  The code is
  highly optimized so that it is somewhat competitive with the native
  Java implementation.  This makes the code on the HEAD of the
  &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch somewhat less than readable.  However, the first
  commit to the repository used Clojure vectors and a functional
  style, so if you would like to understand the code, you might start
  there. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I (unfortunately) needed to use Java arrays and mutation rather than
  the more functional style that I have gotten used to, but the
  results speak for themselves.  Finding the first few elements of a
  sorted array is significantly faster than the Java version.  Finding
  the entire sorted list is somewhat slower than the Java version, but
  not too much.  This is not surprising for a couple of reasons.
  First, heap-sort tends to have larger constants than other sorting
  methods.  Secondly, this code is one day old.  The Java sort method
  has had years to be optimized.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  It may be dreaming, but I would love to see this idea (if not this
  implementation) put into Clojure proper.  I think the advantages
  from laziness outweigh the small constant slowdown versus using
  Java&#39;s &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-sorting/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/clojure-sorting/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
