<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>pages tagged email</title>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/email/"/>
<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/email/index.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<author>

<name>Hiking and Coding</name>

</author>




<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/email/</id>

<subtitle type="html">Hiking and Coding</subtitle>
<generator uri="http://ikiwiki.info/" version="3.20111106">ikiwiki</generator>
<updated>2011-12-01T07:43:31Z</updated>
<entry>
	<title>Scattered</title>

	<id>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/scattered/</id>

	<link href="http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/scattered/"/>






	<category term="clojure" />

	<category term="clojurescript" />

	<category term="email" />

	<category term="git" />

	<category term="git-annex" />

	<category term="notmuch" />

	<category term="spot" />


	<updated>2011-12-01T07:43:31Z</updated>
	<published>2011-11-14T17:11:23Z</published>

	<content type="html" xml:lang="en">
	&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Scattered &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I am doing a bunch of things today, all fairly small.  I think it&#39;s
  because I finished working on the time series framework yesterday,
  so I&#39;m kind of at loose ends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;New programming project &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  One thing that I would like to do is to take all the messages that I
  sent with my &lt;a href=&quot;http://findmespot.com&quot;&gt;SPOT&lt;/a&gt; device while hiking and make a small animation of
  them on Google Maps.  This would be another use of Clojurescript.
  My previous project &amp;ndash; a Clojurescript program for computing the
  Voronoi Diagram of a set of points input by a user &amp;ndash; is a bit
  stalled at the moment, so it&#39;s good to have something else to work
  on.  Also, I feel like adding points to a Google Map is something
  that Clojurescript is better suited to, rather than the fiddly
  numeric stuff that I was trying to make it do.  I will come back to
  the Voronoi Diagram at some point (hopefully fairly soon), but I am
  putting it on the back burner for the moment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So far, I see two major tasks:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-1&quot;&gt;Getting the coordinates and times of the SPOT messages &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Every SPOT message is an email that contains the coordinates of
   where and when the message was sent.  Parsing the email can be done
   offline, so I will probably just use Clojure for that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-2-2&quot;&gt;Putting them on the Google Map &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-2-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/apis/maps/documentation/javascript/overlays.html#Markers&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt; for using Google Maps appears to be easy to use and
   well-thought-out.  There&#39;s even a way to drop the markers at
   different intervals &amp;ndash; just what I want to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Notmuch &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I am also playing with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://notmuch.org&quot;&gt;notmuch&lt;/a&gt; email client.  So far I quite
  like it.  It&#39;s a heck of a lot faster than my previous mail client,
  mainly because it doesn&#39;t do as much.  Like gmail, it is optimized
  towards two operations: searching and tagging.  I never really used
  tags in gmail, because doing so involves clicking around, but it&#39;s
  much faster in notmuch.  So far, this seems like the big advantage
  for notmuch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Git annex &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  In an effort to use all the software written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://joey.kitenet.net/&quot;&gt;Joey Hess&lt;/a&gt; (not
  really, but it seems like it), I am also trying out &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-annex.branchable.com/&quot;&gt;git annex&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So far, I have come up with one really compelling use case --
  syncing podcasts to my mp3 player.  My mp3 player has the problem
  that it will delete all the files on it at random times.  Thus, I
  need to keep a backup of all the files on it on my computer.
  However, when I am done listening to a podcast, I like to remove the
  file.  Hopefully, I will be able to sync the files that I remove
  myself (that is, remove them from the laptop), but not the files
  that get removed by the stupid thing crashing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another thing that I would like to do is put my music and video
  collections in git annex.  I&#39;m not sure that anything special would
  come from doing that, but it seems nice to have these things in
  version control.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

	</content>


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/scattered/#comments" type="text/html" />


	<link rel="comments" href="/posts/scattered/comments.atom" type="application/atom+xml" />

</entry>

</feed>
