<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" >
<channel>
<title>pages tagged PCT</title>
<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/PCT/</link>
<description>Hiking and Coding</description>
<item>

	<title>California Section B</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-02/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-02/</link>


	<category>hiking</category>

	<category>pct</category>


	<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 17:04:48 -0600</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2012-04-23T00:33:42Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Warner Springs to Idyllwild&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Leaving Warner Springs, my feet were getting tired.  I had started
  with shoes that had almost no padding (the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004IHNHQK/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004IHNHQK&quot;&gt;Merrell Trail Glove&lt;/a&gt;), and
  it was turning out that they were too minimal for the task at hand.
  They were fine for forests, but the rocky desert that I was walking
  on was not forgiving enough.  I had ordered some of my favorite
  trail runners to be sent to a cafe that was a couple of days away,
  though, so I was keen to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The first day out of Warner Springs, I met up with the group of
  three ladies that I met the day before Warner Springs.  We made it
  to a water tank by the early afternoon and then sat and shot the
  breeze during the really hot part of the day.  Annie&#39;s blisters were
  still really bad, but she had gotten epsom salts in town, and she
  spent quite a while soaking her feet in a plastic bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We eventually hiked on, but it was starting to get dark quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-2OWhQv6J7RU/Tdk1sPcwPXI/AAAAAAAABcE/tiQCf5BoyCQ/s640/DSCF0533.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-2OWhQv6J7RU/Tdk1sPcwPXI/AAAAAAAABcE/tiQCf5BoyCQ/s640/DSCF0533.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we got to a spot with some flat areas where tents could
  be set up.  Unfortunately for me, there were no trees where I could
  hang my hammock, so I had to &quot;cowboy camp&quot;.  It&#39;s a pretty common
  thing to do, especially on the PCT, where there is very little
  rain.  Basically, it is camping without any shelter.  I put the tarp
  of my hammock down and my mat and sleeping back on top of it.  The
  bugs were pretty bad (I kept Annie awake by slapping at mosquitoes),
  and the ground was a lot less comfortable than my hammock, but I
  made it through the night.  Thankfully, it was one of the very few
  times that I was forced to sleep on the ground during the whole
  trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next day was, for me, a big day.  I wanted to get to the cafe as
  quickly as possible to get my shoes.  We started early, but before
  long it was hot again.  Raven, Lovebird, and Garby, who had all left
  Warner Springs a bit after I had, caught and passed me.  Eventually
  we all met at a water cache and again tried to wait out the sun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I found that I couldn&#39;t wait.  New shoes were just too close and too
  tantalizing.  It was really hot, but they would have cold drinks at
  the cafe.  I walked on, up and down hills, and across dirt roads
  with no trail magic until I finally got to the top of a hill where I
  could see the road with the cafe.  I could see Annie ahead of me, and
  I knew that she would have no trouble getting a ride.  I was also
  really excited about the cafe.  So I started running down the hill
  towards the road.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Annie really had no trouble getting the ride &amp;ndash; I think someone
  stopped before she had enough put out her thumb, so I was on my
  own.  Before long Raven and Lovebird showed up and the three of us
  got a ride together.  After a short ride, we were at Paradise Valley
  Cafe. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Paradise Valley Cafe really is a paradise, especially for
  thru-hikers.  First, it has one of the best waitresses I have ever
  seen.  She was a marvel of efficiency, giving us ice water as soon
  as we came in and refilling our drinks well before they ran dry.
  She was even reading hiking books in an effort to connect better
  with her clientele.  It also has really good burgers (of course I
  got the veggie patty), and is in a really beautiful location.  What
  made me the happiest, though, was my new shoes.  After 150 miles of
  shoes with no padding at all, they felt like walking on cushions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually we had to leave paradise.  It was late, and there was a
  little trail behind the cafe back to the PCT, so I walked down that
  until I found a couple of trees where I could hang my hammock.  All
  the trees were too big or too far apart until I got nearly all the
  way to the trail.  Even then, I had to be very creative to make the
  hammock work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I was up early the next day and moving a lot faster.  We were
  heading into the San Jacinto mountains, and the elevation gain meant
  that we would get some respite from the heat.  Down below was the
  desert and Palm Springs, and I was glad not to be there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pM9l-VDxsJs/Tdk20nApc3I/AAAAAAAABdI/xgHbg9636UM/s800/DSCF0544.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pM9l-VDxsJs/Tdk20nApc3I/AAAAAAAABdI/xgHbg9636UM/s800/DSCF0544.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ycRPfwUCUxk/Tdk2gFfAcQI/AAAAAAAABc8/UMgJkDT8O-U/s800/DSCF0541.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ycRPfwUCUxk/Tdk2gFfAcQI/AAAAAAAABc8/UMgJkDT8O-U/s800/DSCF0541.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3G_8V1I7vcg/Tdk3S3oDeqI/AAAAAAAABdg/1RSwB_PPTPU/s800/DSCF0549.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-3G_8V1I7vcg/Tdk3S3oDeqI/AAAAAAAABdg/1RSwB_PPTPU/s800/DSCF0549.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I slept on the side of a mountain that night, and the next morning
  came to some snow-covered trail.  At that point, it was still enough
  of a novelty that I took a picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Q7sN1vpeiXg/Tdk39Isin5I/AAAAAAAABeA/piFJkqioW0U/s800/DSCF0555.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Q7sN1vpeiXg/Tdk39Isin5I/AAAAAAAABeA/piFJkqioW0U/s800/DSCF0555.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LXdf2CTd3m8/Tdk4QqnTBLI/AAAAAAAABeY/folE9Emn3AE/s800/DSCF0558.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LXdf2CTd3m8/Tdk4QqnTBLI/AAAAAAAABeY/folE9Emn3AE/s800/DSCF0558.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Later that day I made it down a steep side trail to Idyllwild, and
  met up with the rest of the crew.  We had a Mexican feast and
  listened to some really good live music until &quot;hiker midnight&quot; (9
  PM).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Fuller Ridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Up early the next day to hike back up the side trail.  We had more
  snow ahead of us, and the dreaded Fuller Ridge.  People had been
  hyping Fuller Ridge for at least 50 miles, and as with most things
  in life, it didn&#39;t live up to the hype.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Though I&#39;m writing about it now with some bravado, I must admit that
  I was glad to be with a group.  Even better was having Lovebird and
  Raven in the group, who are from the Yukon and have a lot of
  experience hiking on snow.  Garby showed me how to shorten one
  hiking pole while walking on the side of a ridge, but all in all
  Fuller Ridge really wasn&#39;t that bad.  The most difficult thing was
  navigating on the snow.  We had a good idea of where we were on the
  map, and using some intuition and my altimeter watch, we were able
  to stay at the right elevation.  When we walked over the wilderness
  sign that was buried almost to its top in the snow, we knew we were
  at the right place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We ended the day at a trailhead whose elevation was not much
  different from the top of the ridge.  It had already been raining a
  bit during the day, and it continued into the night.  Because of the
  elevation, it froze over night and I awoke to find a thin layer of
  ice covering my hammock&#39;s tarp.  Since my new shoes were frozen, I
  wore my old ones for a while that morning as we started our
  descent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The descent from Fuller Ridge is kind of amazing.  The factoid on
  the map states that it&#39;s 4.3 miles in a straight line but 15.2 miles
  on the trail.  It&#39;s just one switchback after another.  It&#39;s a
  little boring, but we made quick work of it.  We got to the bottom
  by noon.  We had lost about 7000 feet of elevation in the morning
  and were in the boiling heat of the sun once more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Some editing will be in order if I ever want to finish writing about
  this hike.  I remember it all so vividly, though, and I enjoy
  reliving the details.  Anyway, we will go past a wind farm and get
  caught in the rain.  We will miss some of the best sights on the
  trail because we stupidly followed the law and took a marked
  detour.  And a Best Western will never have seemed so good after a
  tough day with some more rain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/hiking/socal-02/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>California Section A</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/socal-01/</link>


	<category>PCT</category>

	<category>hiking</category>


	<pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2012 13:16:46 -0600</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2012-04-15T19:21:52Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>
&lt;p&gt;Here we go on the first post of my recap of my experience on the
Pacific Crest Trail.  It&#39;s been nearly a year since I started, and I
didn&#39;t keep records of where I stayed as well as on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/PCT/./../AT&quot;&gt;AT&lt;/a&gt;, so this
recap will probably be a bit less detailed than that one (which might
be a good thing).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s the obligatory &quot;before&quot; photo:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4xYuJjCRfeo/TdkxHjmx2MI/AAAAAAAABXU/8_DU5RSDSio/s800/DSCF0494.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Across the wall behind me is Mexico.  My shirt is clean, my pack&#39;s
color is vivid, and my face is clean-shaven.  None of those things
would be true for very long on this hike.  I had arrived at the border
at around 6:30 PM, so I didn&#39;t plan to go very far that evening.  I
passed the first mile-marker on my way to the small town near the
trailhead:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Ia1Kk0DJplw/TdkxihMR9VI/AAAAAAAABX0/fR580G6sFbQ/s640/DSCF0495.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had food with me, but no water.  The store owner (because the town
was little more than a convenience store) made me buy water.  Since
Southern California is mostly a desert, I felt it was the best idea to
go along with it.  I walked a bit longer (I made maybe about three
miles on the first evening), found a place to set up my hammock, made
supper and went to bed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day really showed the rigors of desert hiking.  With the sun
beating down and hardly any shade, it wasn&#39;t long before things got
really hot.  I heard my first rattlesnake in bushes nearby, but I just
kept trudging on.  At lunchtime, though, I found a bit of shade at the
bottom of a hill near a flowing stream.  There was another hiker there
with the trail name Hikeaholic.  He had hiked the PCT before and had
even been a maintainer of the trail in Washington, and he was quite
encouraging about my chances.  After lunch, we parted ways, and I went
on to the Lake Morena campsite for the first day of what is known as
the Kickoff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://adzpctko.org&quot;&gt;Kickoff&lt;/a&gt; is an annual event where many of the northbound hikers
(which is just about everyone on the PCT) get together.  Gear
companies show up along with trail &quot;alumni&quot; who want to re-live the
fun and scare the newbies.  There were a few hundred tents set up in
the campsite by the evening, and the next morning I thought that I had
seen enough.  I go hiking to avoid crowds of that size, so I started
down the trail in the cool of the morning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GHRj21tyVm8/Tdkx1FUfjMI/AAAAAAAABYY/zH2C1pKtysk/s800/DSCF0499.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was on my own for most of the day, but I met two couples that I
would later hike with for long distances: Raven and Lovebird, and
Funyan and Meow-Meow.  Of course, they didn&#39;t have their trail names
at that point, but after a while it becomes more natural to refer to
people by their trail names than their actual names.  At the end of
the day, I set up camp just above a dry creek bed with another person
with whom I would hike most of Southern California: a tall guy who got
the trail name Garby from his ability to clean everyone&#39;s plates
like a garbage disposal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day actually had some pine forest, which was a bit of a
surprise.  I enjoyed the shade, but it didn&#39;t last long, and
eventually I was back in the sun.  I ended the day in a campsite that
was the last bit of green on the map for many miles.  I had gotten
there minutes after Lovebird, Raven, and Garby.  There was another
person that I hadn&#39;t met before, who introduced himself as Swope.  I
told the group that my intention was to stay at the campsite so that I
could be sure to find a place to hang my hammock.  I very quickly
regretted it as Swope announced that that made us hiking buddies,
because he was staying there as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ZRMjGMQuBCo/TdkzIapsZWI/AAAAAAAABaQ/tmmio8Ram0w/s800/DSCF0510.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could tell that Swope was a little off, and as the evening went on,
it became even more clear.  He talked a mile a minute about some very
strange topics, he clearly hadn&#39;t been long-distance hiking before,
and he had a massive pack (around 50 pounds) whose weight he had
reduced from about 80 pounds the day before.  He even had a satellite
phone with him &amp;ndash; pretty strange for someone who wanted to get away
from civilization.  Eventually, I had all that I could take and
escaped to my hammock for some shuteye.  (Sorry Swope if you ever read
this.  Some people are just not natural hiking companions.)  Swope got
out of camp ahead of me the next morning, but given his huge pack, I
had no trouble passing him very quickly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The hiking was turning out to be slightly different than I had
expected.  When I think of the desert, I imagine really sandy areas
with almost no vegetation.  This was fairly rocky with shrubs and
brushy trees.  Desert is actually a misnomer: the ecosystem is known
as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaparral&quot;&gt;chaparral&lt;/a&gt;.  It was still hot, though, and when I got to a water
tank at around noon, I decided to wait out the sun for a while.  While
I was waiting, I met Skinny D.  We talked for a while, and then she
went on ahead of me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Gj3_sGqRax4/Tdkzbwn54EI/AAAAAAAABaA/At4SK3R1Y5c/s800/DSCF0513.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We met again at Scissors Crossing &amp;ndash; an awkward intersection of roads
&amp;ndash; where trail angels had left water, energy drinks, beer, and even a
pie.  It was supper time, so we ate supper and then had the pie for
desert.  Skinny D went a bit farther, but I found some trees near a
dried creek bed, and hung out there.  It was surprisingly cold over
night &amp;ndash; the lack of moisture in the air causes that to happen &amp;ndash; and
I was glad to get moving the next morning so that I could get warm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That day highlighted another big difference between the PCT and the
AT.  The whole day was spent going over one big hill.  On the AT, the
hills come thick and fast, but on the PCT they are much more gradual.
The net effect is that you spend a long time going up and then a long
time going down.  We finished the day just past mile 100, where I met
up with many of the people I had met earlier as well as two new ones:
Liz and Annie.  Annie had terrible blisters, but she was pushing
through the pain, which eventually led to her trail name &quot;Push&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was only about 7 miles to the first trail town &amp;ndash; Warner Springs.
There&#39;s really not much more to the town than a small resort and a
gas-station convenience store, where I picked up my first resupply.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After getting to Warner Springs nice and early, I got a room at the
resort with Garby, and we had a lot of fun there with Raven and
Lovebird as well.  While we were eating at the pub, a
bedraggled-looking Swope walked in.  He was clearly the worse for
wear, and had only hiked as far as Scissors Crossing (meaning that he
had somehow gotten a day behind me despite starting at the same time
two days earlier).  He then hitchhiked to Warner Springs and was
intending to get a ride back to Scissors Crossing and return to Warner
Springs by running.  It was, as always, an unconventional approach.
It was the last I would see of him, but I did hear that he made it
farther than I had expected (though I don&#39;t know if he finished).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later that night, the four of us went for a dip in the hot pool that
is fed by the hot springs.  It&#39;s debatable whether it hurt or helped
our hiking, but it was nice and relaxing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  There will be fewer characters to introduce, so hopefully I can
  write about more than one section.  The trail goes from chaparral to
  mountains and back, and we have a snow storm in the mountains and a
  rain storm in the desert.  Hopefully I&#39;ll be able to get to the part
  where I get massively lost by walking down the wrong mountain
  ridge.  That was fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/hiking/socal-01/#comments</comments>

</item>
<item>

	<title>Hiking Philosophy</title>


	<guid isPermaLink="false">http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/</guid>

	<link>http://chrismgray.github.com//posts/hiking/philosophy/</link>


	<category>AT</category>

	<category>PCT</category>

	<category>gear</category>

	<category>hiking</category>


	<pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 13:50:44 -0600</pubDate>
	<dcterms:modified>2012-03-15T17:24:18Z</dcterms:modified>

	<description>
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have written an account of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrismgray.github.com//tags/PCT/./../AT&quot;&gt;AT hike&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I would
write down some things that I think are true about hiking before
writing about the next hike.  The first thing to note is that I
subscribe completely to the hike-your-own-hike (HYOH) philosophy, so
this should be read as descriptive more than prescriptive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-1&quot;&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, I lied.  This is the one prescription.  Read the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lnt.org/programs/principles.php&quot;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;
  and follow them.  Also follow any other rules that are in place for
  the area that you&#39;re in.  If it says not to make camp fires, then
  don&#39;t.  It&#39;s a pity to need to say this, but I&#39;ve seen experienced
  hikers break the rules (and I&#39;m not perfect either, but I do my
  best).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-2&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  So much of the conversation about hiking with non-hikers or
  inexperienced hikers is about dangerous animals.  I probably saw
  less than one bear for every month of hiking that I did, and they
  were all running away from me.  I never hiked in grizzy country, and
  if I ever do, I&#39;ll think about maybe carrying bear spray, though I
  doubt I will in the end.  Wilderness is vast and bears and other
  dangerous animals are sparse.  They generally don&#39;t want anything to
  do with us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The most scared I was of an animal on the AT was the time I saw a
  skunk on the trail in the Shenandoahs.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQT9D0utAWY/TOXBZQbjviI/AAAAAAAAA4s/EEd3ZzaoEgs/s800/DSCF0277.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-3&quot;&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m generally not an ultralighter, though I&#39;m moving more in that
  direction.  This is the gear that I used.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-1&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-1&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I love my hammock.  It&#39;s lighter than many tents, far more
   comfortable than sleeping on the ground, and you don&#39;t need to find
   a flat spot to set it up.  On the other hand, you do need to find
   suitable trees.  This is easy in a pine forest and is probably
   impossible in the plains.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WYbtmOhGn-k/TOW_oCdtkCI/AAAAAAAAAfM/RN-5a_C5hK4/s400/DSCF0060.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-2&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-2&quot;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-2&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   Not boots.  I grew to be very happy with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004C0ZOEG/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004C0ZOEG&quot;&gt;North Face Singletrack&lt;/a&gt;
   trail-running shoe.  It is a bit more rugged than a normal running
   shoe, but far less stiff and heavy than a boot.  I like my shoes to
   last at least 10 miles per dollar.  The Singletrack normally costs
   about $100 and lasts about 1000 miles, so that works out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ZuTaogQEfio/Tnu_74fePGI/AAAAAAAACbI/_rAU6IqEAQg/s640/DSCF0597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-3&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-3&quot;&gt;Pack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-3&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I wore the same pack for both of my thru-hikes: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0034NUZ8M/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0034NUZ8M&quot;&gt;Black Diamond Infinity 60&lt;/a&gt;.  It worked well, though I came to feel that it was
   heavier than it needed to be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-4&quot;&gt;Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   All synthetic.  For the AT hike, I wore the same shirt and shorts
   most of the way.  I got a new pair of shorts in Damascus, just
   because I was getting tired of the pair that I was wearing.  I
   started my AT hike with three pairs of socks and they lasted me the
   whole way.  I would generally change socks only as needed because
   they were wet or once per week during dry sections.  I carried the
   following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One short-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One long-sleeved shirt
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two pairs of underwear
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of shorts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair of long pants
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three pairs of socks
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One fleece
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One rain jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One down jacket
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;     
   On sections that I knew would be very cold, I carried a hat and
   gloves.  In the Sierras I carried wool tights as well, and there
   were nights where I wore everything that I was carrying.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-5&quot;&gt;Sleeping Bag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have a fairly generic down sleeping bag from &lt;a href=&quot;http://mec.ca&quot;&gt;MEC&lt;/a&gt;.  Since it&#39;s
   down, I must be very careful to keep it dry.  To do this, I keep it
   in a trash bag inside its stuff sack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-6&quot;&gt;Bear canister&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   It&#39;s the law that you must carry one in the Sierras, so I did.
   They are the worst &amp;ndash; heavy and bulky, and they still don&#39;t fit as
   much food as a normal food bag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-7&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-7&quot;&gt;Hiking poles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-7&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   As far as I can tell, simpler is better.  A strap is good and
   telescoping is good so that they fit in cars when hitching.  I&#39;ve
   never used poles with shock absorbers, but I really don&#39;t see how
   they would help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-8&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-8&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-8&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   The main change between my hikes was my stove.  On my AT hike, I
   used a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004P78F88/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004P78F88&quot;&gt;MSR Whisperlite&lt;/a&gt; stove.  It&#39;s a great stove &amp;ndash; it puts out
   varying levels of heat and is very fuel efficient &amp;ndash; but I thought
   it was a bit heavy for one person.  So on my PCT hike, I took a
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003LDCVBY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=hikiandcodi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B003LDCVBY&quot;&gt;Vargo&lt;/a&gt; titanium alcohol stove.  It was lighter, but only had one
   temperature, was more prone to accidents, was a pain to fill, and
   required more fuel.  I know that if I was going on a hike with more
   than one person, I would take the Whisperlite, but I don&#39;t know
   what I&#39;d do on another solo hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-9&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-9&quot;&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-9&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   For some hikes, they are necessary, for others emphatically not.  I
   took the &lt;a href=&quot;http://theatguide.com/&quot;&gt;AWOL guide&lt;/a&gt; on my AT hike and printed out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pctmap.net/&quot;&gt;Halfmile maps&lt;/a&gt;
   for my PCT hike.  Since the AT is so well marked, only an elevation
   profile is necessary so that you know how difficult the next
   stretch of trail will be.  On the other hand, it is important to
   have maps on the PCT because there are places where the trail is
   not obvious.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-3-10&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sec-3-10&quot;&gt;Bear Line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-3-10&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
   I have about 50 feet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parachute_cord&quot;&gt;parachute cord&lt;/a&gt; that I attach the lightest
   possible carabiner to.  I then use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qgBLDMuPuvE&quot;&gt;PCT Method&lt;/a&gt; to hang the food
   bag from the tree (with varying degrees of success).  As I noted
   earlier, I&#39;m generally not too concerned about actual bears, but
   hanging food is always a good thing, especially near established
   campsites where there is a high probability of rodents.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-4&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-4&quot;&gt;Packing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-4&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I&#39;m a firm believer that you should always pack in a consistent
  manner.  This saves you time rooting around in your pack.  The only
  tip that I have is that the sleeping bag should go on the bottom.
  You won&#39;t need it all day, and it&#39;s nice to have something soft on
  the bottom of your pack if you put it down quickly or fall down
  backwards.  Other than that, I don&#39;t think the order matters too
  much as long as it&#39;s consistent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-5&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-5&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-5&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  Both of my long hikes have been solo hikes in the sense that I made
  no explicit arrangement with anyone else to hike together.  In both
  hikes, I have had periods of being truly alone and periods where I
  would regularly meet up with the same people nearly every night.  I
  probably enjoyed myself the most when I was in groups of three or
  four, but I also think that it would be nearly impossible for me to
  stay with one single group for an entire hike.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The community aspect of hiking is one of its strongest
  selling-points.  You meet all kinds of people who are all doing the
  same thing as you.  So that gives you something to talk about right
  away.  Nothing bonds like shared misery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There is also a strong sense that everyone is looking out for each
  other.  This was put into the starkest relief for me when I was
  hiking in the Sierras on the PCT, so I&#39;ll go into it in more detail
  when I get around to writing about that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sec-6&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-6&quot;&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
  I might write another of these more general posts about hiking later.
  I still haven&#39;t touched on things like a daily schedule or what town
  stops are like.  For now, however, I think this post has gotten long
  enough.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>


	<comments>/posts/hiking/philosophy/#comments</comments>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
